[
  {
    "question": "Regarding deep stall characteristics, identify whether the following statements are correct or incorrect:\n\n1) An aeroplane with a low horizontal tail and wings with sweepback is normally prone to deep stall\n2) An aeroplane with a canard is normally prone to deep stall",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pitch up effect of an aeroplane with swept back wing during a stall is due to the:",
    "feedback": "wing tip stalling first"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n1) A propeller with a small blade angle is referred to as being in fine pitch\n2) A propeller with a significant blade twist is referred to as being in coarse pitch",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of high lift device is shown in the figures?",
    "feedback": "Krueger flap"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which figure represents the change in the CL/alpha curve with increasing aspect ratio?",
    "feedback": "Figure 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the static lateral stability of an aeroplane is increased, whilst its static directional stability remains constant:",
    "feedback": "its sensitivity to Dutch roll increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 100 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value of 1.96:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 40 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "VRA is the speed recommended for:",
    "feedback": "penetration of severe turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly decreases the speed by 100 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "decrease to 0.25"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a given RPM of a fixed pitch propeller, the blade angle of attack will:",
    "feedback": "decrease when the TAS increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following variables are required to calculate lift from the lift formula?",
    "feedback": "Dynamic pressure, lift coefficient and wing area"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane leaving ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle increases\n2) The induced angle of attack increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.\nIf an aeroplane is flying such that the speed stability is negative, the CAS is in the region of the curve where ......",
    "feedback": "parasite drag is less than induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the elevator trim tab is deflected up, the cockpit trim indicator presents:",
    "feedback": "nose-down."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane, being manually flown in the speed unstable region, experiences a disturbance that causes a speed reduction. If the altitude is maintained and thrust remains constant, the aeroplane speed will:",
    "feedback": "further decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "The units of wing loading (I) W / S and (II) dynamic pressure q are:",
    "feedback": "(I) N / m², (II) N / m²."
  },
  {
    "question": "If the sum of all the moments in flight is not zero, the aeroplane will rotate about the:",
    "feedback": "centre of gravity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement with respect to the transonic speed range is correct ?",
    "feedback": "The transonic speed range starts at Mcrit and extends to Mach numbers above M=1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a constant load factor, which of these statements about the variation of induced drag with changes of speed and mass are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed decreases, induced drag increases\n2) When mass decreases, induced drag increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is greater than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "during a pull-up manoeuvre"
  },
  {
    "question": "Coefficient of lift is:",
    "feedback": "A variable depending on dynamic pressure and the wing area"
  },
  {
    "question": "The boundary layer will separate from the aerofoil immediately ......",
    "feedback": "behind the shock wave on the upper wing surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "The gust load factor due to a vertical upgust increases when:",
    "feedback": "the gradient of the CL-alpha graph increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at a constant CAS in the unstable speed region and encounter a wind shear which changes a headwind into a tailwind. Which is correct?",
    "feedback": "Airspeed will decrease because the total drag is increasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "A positively cambered aerofoil will generate zero lift:",
    "feedback": "at a negative angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "A wing has a \"Fineness Ratio\" which is the ratio of:",
    "feedback": "the chord to the thickness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a constant load factor, which of these statements about the variation of induced drag with changes of speed and mass are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed increases, induced drag increases\n2) When mass increases, induced drag increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The negative manoeuvring limit load factor for a light aeroplane in the utility category in the clean configuration may not be less than:",
    "feedback": "-1.76"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) At a given RPM the propeller efficiency of a fixed pitch propeller is maximum at only one value of TAS\n2) A constant speed propeller maintains near maximum efficiency over a wider range of aeroplane speeds than a fixed pitch propeller",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Should a transport aeroplane fly at a higher Mach number than the 'buffet-onset' Mach number?",
    "feedback": "No, this is not acceptable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The drag divergence Mach number is lower than Mcrit\n2) Below the drag divergence Mach number and for a given angle of attack the drag coefficient CD increases as the Mach number increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed increases the buffet free range increases\n2) When altitude decreases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a left turn, the slip indicator is right of neutral. One way to co-ordinate the turn is to apply:",
    "feedback": "more left bank"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for a propeller of given diameter and at constant RPM?\n\n1) Assuming blade shape does not change power absorption increases if the number of blades increases\n2) Power absorption decreases if the mean chord of the blades increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.5 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 1.75, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 1.8 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "n = 1.90"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat\n2) The total pressure in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stalling speed in IAS will change according to the following factors:",
    "feedback": "Increase during turn, increased mass and forward c.g. location"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nThe maximum achievable load factor without buffet onset at FL 380 at a mass of 90 tons is approximately:",
    "feedback": "1.75g at M = 0.80"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about the effects on drag of removing external tip tanks from the wings of an aeroplane, is correct?\n\n1) Parasite drag increases\n2) Induced drag decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The density behind an oblique shock wave is lower than in front of it\n2) The local speed of sound behind an oblique shock wave is lower than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n1) A propeller with little blade twist is referred to as being in fine pitch\n2) A propeller with a significant blade twist is referred to as being in coarse pitch",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram represents a left turn with too much left bank?",
    "feedback": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The increase in stall speed (IAS) with increasing altitude is due to:",
    "feedback": "compressibility effects"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nLevel flight (1G)\nCruise level FL340\nAircraft mass 110.000 kg\nCG: 35 %\n\nThe low-speed buffet boundary is .... (i) and the high-speed buffet boundary is .... (ii):",
    "feedback": "(i) M 0,52  (ii) M 0,84"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the letter which correctly represents the Angle of Advance (Helix Angle) in the diagram:",
    "feedback": "D"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mean geometric chord of a wing is the:",
    "feedback": "wing area divided by the wing span"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sensitivity for spiral dive will occur when :",
    "feedback": "the static directional stability is positive and the static lateral stability is relatively weak."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the influence of increasing aeroplane mass on Mcrit at constant IAS? (n = 1)",
    "feedback": "Mcrit decreases as a result of flying at a larger angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "An increase in the speed at which an airfoil passes through the air increases lift because",
    "feedback": "The increased speed of air passing over the airfoil's upper surface decreases the pressure, thus creating a greater pressure differential between upper and lower surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate value of the lift of an aeroplane at a gross weight of 50 000 N, in a horizontal coordinated 45 degrees banked turn ?",
    "feedback": "70 000 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) If flutter occurs, IAS should be reduced\n2) Resistance to flutter increases with increasing wing stiffness",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "As it applies to airfoils, which statement is in agreement with Bernoulli's Principle?",
    "feedback": "The static pressure of a fluid decreases at points where the speed of the fluid increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure decreases as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity decreases as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Total drag is the sum of:",
    "feedback": "parasite drag and induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "What data may be obtained from the Buffet Onset Boundary chart?",
    "feedback": "The values of the Mach Number at which low speed and Mach Buffet occur at different weights and altitudes."
  },
  {
    "question": "When are wing tip vortex created?",
    "feedback": "When the wing produces lift."
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is less than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "during a steady wings level descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "The resistance, or skin friction, due to the viscosity of the air as it passes along the surface of the wing is part of the:",
    "feedback": "Parasite drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "Dividing lift by weight gives:",
    "feedback": "load factor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram represents a right turn with insufficient rudder?",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aeroplane drag in straight and level flight is lowest when the:",
    "feedback": "parasite drag  is equal to the induced drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "For most jet transport aeroplanes, slat extension has:",
    "feedback": "a greater effect on stall speed than flap extension"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bow wave will appear first at:",
    "feedback": "a free stream Mach number just above M=1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) A stick pusher activates at a lower angle of attack than a stick shaker\n2) A stick shaker prevents the pilot from increasing the angle of attack further",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.7 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "35%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane entering ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL increases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect of a ventral fin on the static stability of an aeroplane is as follows :\n(1=longitudinal, 2=lateral, 3=directional)",
    "feedback": "1 : no effect, 2 : negative, 3 : positive"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has the following flap settings : 0°, 15°, 30° and 45°. Slats can be selected too. Which of the above selections will produce the greatest negative influence on the CL/CD ratio?",
    "feedback": "Flaps from 30° to 45°."
  },
  {
    "question": "When power assisted controls are used for pitch control, this:",
    "feedback": "ensures that a part of the aerodynamic forces is still felt on the column."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the position of the elevator in relation to the trimmable horizontal stabilizer of an aeroplane with fully hydraulically operated flight controls that is in trim?",
    "feedback": "Elevator deflection is zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly decreases the speed by 40 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "decrease to 0.64"
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) An elevator trim tab is more suitable to cope with the large trim changes generated by the high lift devices on most jet transport aeroplanes\n2) A stabiliser trim runaway causes less control difficulty",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 12\nThrust per engine: 21000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a four-engine aeroplane, the one-engine inoperative climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "4.3 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Tuck under\" is:",
    "feedback": "the tendency to nose down when speed is increased into the transonic flight regime."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is descending at a constant Mach number from FL 350. What is the effect on true airspeed ?",
    "feedback": "It increases as temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approximately how long does it take to fly a complete circle during a horizontal steady co-ordinated turn with a bank angle of 45° and a TAS of 200 kt?",
    "feedback": "65 s"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a straight steady climb:\n\n1) lift is less than weight\n2) lift is greater than weight\n3) load factor is less than 1\n4) load factor is greater than 1\n5) lift is equal to weight\n6) load factor is equal to 1\n\nWhich of the following lists all the correct statements?",
    "feedback": "1 and 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "When inner and outer ailerons are mounted, outer ailerons are used:",
    "feedback": "at low speeds"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane with one fixed value of VA the following applies. VA is :",
    "feedback": "the speed at which the aeroplane stalls at the manoeuvring limit load factor at MTOW."
  },
  {
    "question": "A twin-engine jet aircraft is flying straight and level when suddenly an engine fails. Which combination of environmental factors would require a larger rudder input to control the yaw moment after an engine failure?",
    "feedback": "Low temperature and high atmospheric pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bernoulli's equation is:\n\nNote:\nrho = actual density\npstat = static pressure\npdyn = dynamic pressure\nptot = total pressure",
    "feedback": "pstat + 1/2 rho * TAS^2 = constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is one of the disadvantages of increasing the number of propeller blades ?",
    "feedback": "decrease propeller efficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane transitions from steady straight and level flight into a horizontal co-ordinated turn with a load factor of 2, the speed remains constant and the:",
    "feedback": "induced drag increases by a factor of 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the undisturbed airflow is the same as in the throat\n2) The total pressure in the undisturbed airflow and in the throat is the same",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A light aeroplane has flown in icing conditions and accumulated ice on the horizontal stabiliser. If the pilot does nothing to account for the ice, then during the landing flare, the aircraft might suffer a tail stall and .......",
    "feedback": "a nose-down pitch causing the nose wheel to contact the runway first"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane stalls due to excessive:",
    "feedback": "Angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Superstall is a condition",
    "feedback": "which is a stable stall with almost a constant pitch attitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is on final approach at a CAS within the non-stable region of the CAS/drag graph. The aeroplane experiences wind shear consisting of a change in the wind direction to be less of a headwind with little change in wind speed. The wind shear will cause....",
    "feedback": "a reduction in airspeed, which will cause an increase in total drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Induced drag increases as angle of attack increases\n2) At constant load factor, induced drag decreases with increasing aeroplane mass",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 12\nThrust per engine: 21000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a four-engine aeroplane, the all-engines climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "8.5 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the C.G. position is moved forward, the elevator deflection for a manoeuvre with a load factor greater than 1 will be:",
    "feedback": "larger."
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding deep stall characteristics, identify whether the following statements are correct or incorrect:\n\n1) The combination of a wing with sweepback and a T-tail make an aeroplane prone to deep stall\n2) A stick pusher system can be fitted to an aeroplane that exhibits abnormal stall characteristics",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a turn, the load factor n and the stalling speed VS will be:",
    "feedback": "n greater than 1, VS higher than in straight and level flight."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about a propeller is correct?\n\n1) Asymmetric blade effect is unaffected when engine power is increased\n2) Asymmetric blade effect is independent of the angle between the propeller axis and airflow through the propeller disc",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of elevator trim tab adjustment on the static longitudinal stability of an aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "no effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly decreases the speed by 60 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "decrease to 0.49"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.4 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2.4, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "irrelevant, since the aeroplane would already be in a stalled condition at 1.4 VS with that gust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Line 3 corresponds to aerofoil 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly increases the speed by 40 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "increase to 1.44"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane entering ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL decreases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Maintaining directional control with one engine inoperative using the banking method, compared to the wings-level method, can result in directional control problems at .....",
    "feedback": "light aeroplane masses, due to the reduced lateral component of weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "A negative contribution to the static longitudinal stability of conventional jet transport aeroplanes is provided by:",
    "feedback": "the fuselage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying in icing conditions may result in the stall warning system failing to trigger. This is due to the aeroplane stalling at a lower ....... because of premature boundary layer separation.",
    "feedback": "Angle of Attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the manoeuvre stability of an aeroplane is 125 N/g. The stick force required to achieve a load factor of 4 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is:",
    "feedback": "375 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The drag divergence Mach number is higher than Mcrit\n2) Below the drag divergence Mach number and for a given angle of attack the drag coefficient CD increases as the Mach number increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "During which of the following phases of flight is a fixed pitch propeller's angle of attack lowest?",
    "feedback": "High-speed glide"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of attack at which an aircraft stalls:",
    "feedback": "Remains constant regardless of gross weight."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect on induced drag of an increase in aspect ratio?",
    "feedback": "Induced drag decreases, because the effect of tip vortices decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the CL-CD graph.If curve 1 represents a clean wing, the extension or deployment of which device(s) could cause the change represented by curve 2?",
    "feedback": "Trailing-edge flaps"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about propellers is correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A cruise propeller has a smaller geometric pitch compared with a climb propeller\n2) A coarse pitch propeller is more efficient during take off and in the climb, but is less efficient in cruise, when compared with a fine pitch propeller",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about the effects on drag of fitting external tip tanks to the wings of an aeroplane, is correct?\n\n1) Parasite drag decreases\n2) Induced drag increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about CG limits is correct?",
    "feedback": "The forward CG limit is mainly determined by the amount of pitch control available from the elevator"
  },
  {
    "question": "A commercial jet aeroplane is performing a straight descent at a constant Mach Number with constant mass. The operational speed limit that may be exceeded is:",
    "feedback": "VMO."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?\nI When the critical engine fails during take-off the speed VMCL can be limiting.\nII The speed VMCL can be limited by the available maximum roll rate",
    "feedback": "I is incorrect, II is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared with level flight prior to the stall, the lift (1) and drag (2) in the stall change as follows :",
    "feedback": "(1) decreases (2) increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.5 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2.5, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "irrelevant, since the aeroplane would already be in a stalled condition at 1.5 VS with that gust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which boundary layer, when considering its velocity profile perpendicular to the flow, has the greatest change in velocity close to the surface?",
    "feedback": "Turbulent boundary layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat\n2) The speed in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The coefficient of drag can be defined as the ......",
    "feedback": "ratio of drag pressure to dynamic pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a straight and level flight the pilot pulls on the control column to gain altitude. What effect will this have on the stagnation point of the aerofoil and the angle of attack?\nThe leading edgle stagnation point of the aerofoil moves towards the ...... surface of the aerofoil as the angle of attack ...... .",
    "feedback": "Lower, increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A stabiliser trim tab is more suitable to cope with the large trim changes generated by the high lift devices on most jet transport aeroplanes\n2) A stabiliser trim runaway causes less control difficulty",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A shock wave on a lift generating wing will:",
    "feedback": "move slightly aft in front of a downward deflecting aileron"
  },
  {
    "question": "When comparing a stabiliser trim system with an elevator trim system, which of these statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "a stabiliser trim is able to compensate larger changes in pitching moments"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aeroplane manoeuvrability increases for a given control surface deflection when:",
    "feedback": "IAS increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Stall speeds are determined with the CG at the forward limit\n2) Minimum control speeds are determined with the CG at the aft limit",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In supersonic flight, any disturbance around a body affects the flow only:",
    "feedback": "within the Mach cone"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Mcrit is lower than the drag divergence Mach number\n2) Assuming a given angle of attack and for M < 1 the drag coefficient CD remains practically constant above the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) An rectangular spanwise lift distribution generates less induced drag than an elliptical lift distribution\n2) Induced drag decreases with increasing aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the transonic range the aeroplane characteristics are strongly determined by:",
    "feedback": "the Mach Number."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about a propeller is correct?\n\n1) Asymmetric blade effect reduces when engine power is increased\n2) Asymmetric blade effect is independent of the angle between the propeller axis and airflow through the propeller disc",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Large jet aeroplanes are often made with supercritical aerofoils, rather than conventional aerofoils. Which of the following is one of the benefits of this, with regards to flying at speeds greater than MCRIT?",
    "feedback": "The aeroplane may fly at a greater Mach number and, initially, only experience a slight increase in drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed :",
    "feedback": "increases with an increased weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Longitudinal stability is directly influenced by:",
    "feedback": "centre of gravity position"
  },
  {
    "question": "While performing a take-off under icing conditions, the pilot rotates the aircraft at the correct speed and rate, but notices that the aircraft does not lift off as expected. What could be the cause?",
    "feedback": "The angle of attack during rotation exceeds the lower, icing-induced critical angle of attack, preventing the aircraft from becoming airborne"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stick forces, provided by an elevator feel system, depend on:",
    "feedback": "elevator deflection, dynamic pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a constant load factor, which of these statements about the variation of induced drag with changes of speed and mass are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed decreases, induced drag increases\n2) When mass decreases, induced drag decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The true airspeed (TAS) is:",
    "feedback": "lower than the indicated airspeed (IAS) at ISA conditions and altitudes below sea level."
  },
  {
    "question": "A typical curve representing propeller efficiency of a fixed pitch propeller versus TAS at constant RPM is:",
    "feedback": "diagram 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat\n2) The total pressure in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Static lateral stability should not be too large, because:",
    "feedback": "too much aileron deflection would be required in a crosswind landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.9 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2.9, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "n = 3.00"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which design caracteristic is typical for a supercritical aerofoil when compared to a conventional positive-cambered aerofoil?",
    "feedback": "A flatter upper surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "When shock stall occurs:",
    "feedback": "there will be flow separation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift coefficient of a symmetrical aerofoil section at zero angle of attack is:",
    "feedback": "zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you pull back the RPM lever of a constant speed propeller during a glide with idle power and constant speed, the propeller pitch will:",
    "feedback": "increase and the rate of descent will decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "To perform a co-ordinated turn the aeroplane in diagram 3 should use:",
    "feedback": "more bank angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following take place at the transition point on a wing:",
    "feedback": "the boundary layer makes the transition from laminar flow to the turbulent boundary layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The application of the area rule on aeroplane design will decrease the",
    "feedback": "wave drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "Total pressure is (rho = density):",
    "feedback": "static pressure plus the dynamic pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "The helix or advance angle of a rotating propeller blade element shown in the diagram is:",
    "feedback": "angle 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The total drag of an aerofoil in two dimensional flow comprises:",
    "feedback": "pressure drag and skin friction drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane's lift/drag (L/D) ratio is ......",
    "feedback": "a measure of its efficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure increases as the streamlines diverge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines diverge",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The significance of VA for jet transport aeroplanes is reduced at high cruising altitudes because:",
    "feedback": "buffet onset limitations normally become limiting"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram represents a balanced left turn?",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding a symmetric aerofoil section, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The angle of attack has a negative value when the lift coefficient equals zero\n2) A nose up pitching moment exists when the lift coefficient equals zero",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The image illustrates an aeroplane flying at two angles of attack (AoA), 2° and 12°, and a very simplified representation of the streamlines in the 3D airflow around the wing. The pilot reduces airspeed while increasing pitch from an AoA of 2° to an AoA of 12° in order to maintain straight and level flight. At the end of the speed reduction, the lift vector will have ....",
    "feedback": "changed direction by a value greater than 10°, with the lift vector pointing more rearwards because of a larger induced AoA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is greater than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "when weight is less than lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "A boundary layer fence on a swept wing will improve:",
    "feedback": "the low speed characteristics."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a descent above the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "lift coefficient decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements about VMCG:\n\n1) VMCG is determined with the gear down\n2) VMCG is determined with the flaps in the landing position\n3) VMCG is determined by using rudder and nosewheel steering\n4) During VMCG determination the aeroplane may not deviate from the straight-line path by more than 30 ft\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "VLE is defined as the:",
    "feedback": "maximum landing gear extended speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When altitude increases the buffet free range decreases\n2) When load factor increases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices is not affected by angle of attack\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about stall speed is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Increasing forward sweep increases stall speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about wing sweepback are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Decreasing wing sweepback decreases Mcrit\n2) Decreasing wing sweepback decreases the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nThe maximum achievable load factor without buffet onset at FL 380 at a mass of 104 tons is approximately:",
    "feedback": "1.5 g at M 0.80"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which point shown in the figure corresponds with CL for minimum horizontal flight speed?",
    "feedback": "Point a"
  },
  {
    "question": "A fundamental difference between the manoeuvring limit load factor and the gust limit load factor is, that:",
    "feedback": "the gust limit load factor can be higher than the manoeuvring limit load factor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Entering the stall the centre of pressure of a straight (1) wing and of a strongly swept back wing (2) will:",
    "feedback": "(1) move aft, (2) move forward."
  },
  {
    "question": "The calibrated airspeed during approach and landing, with all engines operating, at which, when the critical engine is suddenly made inoperative, it is possible to maintain control of the aeroplane with that engine still inoperative, and maintain straight flight with an angle of bank of not more than 5°, is called ....",
    "feedback": "VMCL"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane entering ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle decreases\n2) The induced angle of attack remains constant",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a climb below the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "TAS decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) An elliptical spanwise lift distribution generates less induced drag than a rectangular lift distribution\n2) Induced drag increases with decreasing aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed range between high and low speed buffet:",
    "feedback": "increases during a descent with a constant IAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a steady, horizontal, co-ordinated turn:",
    "feedback": "thrust equals drag, because there is equilibrium of forces along the direction of flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure decreases as the streamlines diverge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines diverge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the slope of the lift versus angle of attack curve decreases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the wing loading decreases, the gust load factor decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which point in the diagram gives the lowest speed in horizontal flight?",
    "feedback": "Point a"
  },
  {
    "question": "The figure represents the same wing in two different configurations. If curve A is the CL curve for the clean configuration, the wing profile is (1) ..... and curve B illustrates the effect of (2) ..... edge flaps.",
    "feedback": "(1) symmetrical, (2) trailing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding a propeller?\n\n1) Increasing tip speed to supersonic speed increases propeller noise\n2) Increasing tip speed to supersonic speed increases propeller efficiency",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Maintaining a constant Flight Level and IAS, an aircraft flies into a colder airmass. Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "The Mach number remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle between the chord line of an airfoil and the relative wind is known as the\nangle of",
    "feedback": "attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the coefficient of lift, CL?",
    "feedback": "A dimensionless number that gives the relationship between lift force per unit wing area and dynamic pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following lists aeroplane features that each increase static lateral stability ?",
    "feedback": "High wing, sweep back, large and high vertical fin."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the high lift devices shown on the left side correspond(s) to the curve?",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed of sound is determined only by:",
    "feedback": "temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "When entering ground effect, maintaining the same coefficient of lift CL, requires ......",
    "feedback": "a lower angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "A normal shock wave is a discontinuity plane:",
    "feedback": "that is normal to the local flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding wake turbulence, choose the correct statement:",
    "feedback": "Heavy aircraft produce stronger wake turbulence than lighter ones"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a descent below the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "IAS increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the take-off roll, when the pilot raises the tail in a tail wheeled propeller driven aeroplane, the additional aeroplane yawing tendency is due to the effect of:",
    "feedback": "gyroscopic precession"
  },
  {
    "question": "VSR is:",
    "feedback": "the reference stall speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "The movement of the aerodynamic centre of the wing when an aeroplane accelerates through the transonic range causes:",
    "feedback": "an increase in static longitudinal stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a fixed-pitch propeller, the blade angle of attack",
    "feedback": "decreases during the take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat\n2) The total pressure in the undisturbed airflow and in the throat is the same",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a constant velocity airflow, a high aspect ratio wing will have (in comparison\nwith a low aspect ratio wing)",
    "feedback": "decreased drag, especially at a high angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When initiating a steady horizontal turn from steady straight and level flight the buffet free range decreases\n2) When mass decreases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "If velocity and angle of attack is kept constant and density decreases, the lift",
    "feedback": "decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane enters a horizontal turn with a load factor n=2 from straight and level flight whilst maintaining constant indicated airspeed. The:",
    "feedback": "lift doubles"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a jet transport aeroplane takes off with the CG at the aft limit and the trimmable horizontal stabiliser (THS) is positioned at the maximum allowable up position for take-off:",
    "feedback": "early nose wheel raising will take place"
  },
  {
    "question": "Static directional stability is mainly provided by:",
    "feedback": "the fin"
  },
  {
    "question": "What angle is depicted on the diagram by letter \"D\"?",
    "feedback": "Helix angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which design features reduce static lateral stability?\n\n1) Anhedral\n2) Dihedral\n3) Forward sweep\n4) Sweepback\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding high speed flight, if the angle of attack of an aeroplane is increased, its critical Mach number will ......",
    "feedback": "decrease, because of greater acceleration on the top surface of the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "A multi-engine aircraft with clockwise rotating propellers suffers an engine failure after take-off. Considering the aircraft maintains zero bank and no power changes, which situation would lead to the largest rudder deflection?",
    "feedback": "Left crosswind, left engine failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.3 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "59%."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about the lift-to-drag ratio in straight and level flight is correct?",
    "feedback": "At the highest value of the lift/drag ratio the total drag is lowest."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect on induced drag of mass and speed changes (all other factors of importance remaining constant)?",
    "feedback": "Decreases with increasing speed and decreasing mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "A wing is often designed having a different profile shape and/or a different angle of incidence along its span, creating a washout effect. Why is that?",
    "feedback": "To ensure that the wing tip stalls after the wing root to increase the stability in roll and reduce the likelihood of a wing-drop"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed in a 60° banked turn increases by the following factor:",
    "feedback": "1.41"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the gyroscopic effect of a clockwise rotating propeller on a single engine aeroplane?\n\n1) Pitch up produces left yaw\n2) Right yaw produces pitch down",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nAt a mass of 130 tons:",
    "feedback": "the buffet free range in 1g flight at FL 410 is from approximately M = 0.76 to M = 0.83"
  },
  {
    "question": "The difference between the effects of slat and flap asymmetry is that (\"large\" in the context of this question means not or hardly controllable by normal use of controls):",
    "feedback": "flap asymmetry causes a large rolling moment at any speed whereas slat asymmetry causes a large difference in CLMAX."
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of the stick pusher is:",
    "feedback": "to activate and push the stick forward at or beyond a certain value of angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which curve represents the Coefficient of Lift CL vs. Angle of Attack curve for a negatively cambered aerofoil?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect on landing speed when a trimmable horizontal stabiliser jams at high IAS?",
    "feedback": "In most cases, a higher than normal landing speed is required"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which design features improve static lateral stability?\n\n1) High wing\n2) Low wing\n3) Large and high vertical fin\n4) Ventral fin\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding wake turbulence?",
    "feedback": "Heavy aircraft produce stronger wake turbulence than lighter ones"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the mass decreases, the gust load factor decreases\n2) When the altitude increases, the gust load factor decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vortex generators on the upper side of the wing:",
    "feedback": "decrease wave drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "In general transport aeroplanes with power assisted flight controls are fitted with an adjustable stabilizer instead of trim tabs on the elevator. This is because :",
    "feedback": "effectiveness of trim tabs is insufficient for those aeroplanes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding a windmilling propeller on a multi-engine aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "The windmilling drag is much higher than for a feathered propeller"
  },
  {
    "question": "A forward CG shift:",
    "feedback": "decreases longitudinal manoeuvrability"
  },
  {
    "question": "The CG of an aeroplane is in a fixed position forward of the neutral point. Which of these statements about the stick force stability is correct?",
    "feedback": "An increase of 10 kt from the trimmed position at low speed has more effect on the stick force than an increase of 10 kt from the timmed position at high speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which drag components make up parasite drag?\n\n1) pressure drag\n2) friction drag\n3) induced drag\n4) interference drag\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "If an aeroplane is flying at transonic speed with increasing Mach number the shock wave on the upper side of the wing",
    "feedback": "moves into trailing edge direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the impact of a change in angle of attack (AoA) on a normal shock wave at a constant Mach number?",
    "feedback": "The intensity of the shock wave increases as AoA increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aerodynamic drag of a body, placed in a certain airstream depends amongst others on:",
    "feedback": "The airstream velocity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the lift coefficient and drag coefficient at normal angle of attack:",
    "feedback": "CL is much greater than CD"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a modern large aeroplane fitted with a Fly-By-Wire (FBW) system. Following a failure, the flight control system laws fall one level to the first level of degradation. What would be one of the most common consequences?",
    "feedback": "The autopilot is required to remain available according to airworthiness regulations, but, depending on the specific failure, some protections may be lost"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The total pressure in the throat is the same as in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming zero wing twist, the wing planform that gives the highest local lift coefficient at the wing root is:",
    "feedback": "rectangular"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about propeller icing is correct?\n\n1) Propeller icing reduces blade element drag and increases blade element lift\n2) Propeller icing does not affect propeller efficiency",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a descent at a constant Mach number (assume zero thrust and standard atmospheric conditions):",
    "feedback": "the angle of attack will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "The high lift device shown in the figure 2 is a:",
    "feedback": "Slat"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements are correct or incorrect regarding a sideslip, with the relative airflow coming from the left, on an aeroplane that exhibits both directional and lateral stability?\n\n1) The initial tendency of the nose of the aeroplane is to move to the right\n2) The initial tendency of the right wing is to move down",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane leaving ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL remains constant\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Mach trim system will prevent:",
    "feedback": "tuck under."
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The effects of a trim tab runaway are more serious\n2) A jammed stabiliser trim causes less control difficulty",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is maintaining straight and level flight with constant power and no flaps deployed. In this condition the CL is 0.28. What will happen to the CL if the pilot extends the flaps?",
    "feedback": "The CL  is higher than 0.28"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is in a steady turn, at a constant TAS of 300 kt, and a bank angle of 45°. Its turning radius is equal to:\n(given: g= 10 m/s²)",
    "feedback": "2381 metres."
  },
  {
    "question": "As an aeroplane leaves ground effect after lift-off, wing tip vortices and the induced angle of attack will (1) ..... and (2) ........ :",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has static longitudinal stability when the:",
    "feedback": "Centre of gravity is in front of the neutral point"
  },
  {
    "question": "During final approach, the Pilot Flying is struggling to maintain the aircraft's speed under control. At the correct altitude, the aircraft's speed keeps increasing above the desired. From the options below, what would be the most likely causes?",
    "feedback": "An inadequate flap setting"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about the effects on drag of fitting external tip tanks to the wings of an aeroplane, is correct?\n\n1) Parasite drag increases\n2) Induced drag increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the manoeuvre stability of an aeroplane is 300 N/g. The stick force required to achieve a load factor of 2.5 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is:",
    "feedback": "450 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "The C.G. position of an aeroplane is forward of the neutral point in a fixed location. Speed changes cause a departure from the trimmed position. Which of the following statements about the stick force stability is correct?",
    "feedback": "Increasing 10 kt trimmed at low speed has more effect on the stick force than increasing 10 kt trimmed at high speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "The curve identified with the number 3 corresponds to ...",
    "feedback": "induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The static temperature in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it\n2) The static pressure in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The total pressure in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane equipped with a two-position variable pitch propeller it is advisable to select a:",
    "feedback": "fine pitch for take-off and climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "When wing lift is zero, its induced drag is:",
    "feedback": "zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat\n2) The speed in the undisturbed airflow is the same than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared to a clean, polished wing at the same low angle of attack, a wing with dirt, making the surface rougher, has ....",
    "feedback": "more friction drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider an aircraft flying in unaccelerated level flight in the non-stable region. What would be the result on Indicated Airspeed (IAS) and drag following a sudden decrease in aircraft speed with no change in thrust available?",
    "feedback": "IAS would further decrease due to the increased drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Tuck under\" is caused by (i) which movement of the centre of pressure of the wing and (ii) which change of the downwash angle at the location of the stabilizer.",
    "feedback": "(i) aft (ii) decreasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a straight, steady climb and with the thrust force parallel to the flight path:",
    "feedback": "lift is the same as during a descent at the same angle and mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning sweepback is correct?",
    "feedback": "Sweepback provides a positive contribution to static lateral stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure\nGiven:Aircraft mass: 100 tBank angle/load factor: 30°Flight level: FL370\nWhat is the minimum Mach number to avoid low speed buffet?",
    "feedback": "≤ FL410, ≤ M0.71 & ≥ FL380, ≥ M0.65"
  },
  {
    "question": "The CL - alpha curve of a positive cambered aerofoil intersects with the vertical axis of the CL - alpha graph:",
    "feedback": "above the origin."
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the advantages of a supercritical aerofoil, when compared with a conventional aerofoil, is that ......",
    "feedback": "it increases MCRIT"
  },
  {
    "question": "With increasing altitude the following occurs:",
    "feedback": "drag remains the same for a given indicated airspeed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Differential aileron deflection:",
    "feedback": "equals the drag of the right and left aileron"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of  2 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 3, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 1.3 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "not greater than 1.69, because the aeroplane is stalled with a higher load factor at 1.3 VS"
  },
  {
    "question": "The parameters that can be read from the aeroplane parabolic polar curve are the:",
    "feedback": "minimum glide angle and the parasite drag coefficient"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the four points in the graph depicts the maximum lift to drag ratio?",
    "feedback": "Point 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is testing out the stalling characteristics of his aeroplane close to the stall. Calculate the coefficient of lift, given:\nWing area: 13.5 m2Density: 1.225 kg/m3Speed: 70 ktsMass: 1300 kgAssume g = 9.81",
    "feedback": "1.19"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "The short period oscillation should always be heavily dampened"
  },
  {
    "question": "The relative thickness of an aerofoil is expressed in:",
    "feedback": "% chord."
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding Dutch Roll, the correct statement is:",
    "feedback": "If the yaw damper is inoperative, consider reducing speed and altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the significance of the maximum allowed cruising altitude, based on the 1.3g margin? At this altitude:",
    "feedback": "a manoeuvre with a load factor of 1.3 will cause buffet onset"
  },
  {
    "question": "In general, directional controllability with one engine inoperative on a multi-engine aeroplane is adversely affected by:\n1) high temperature\n2) low temperature\n3) aft CG location\n4) forward CG location\n5) high altitude\n6) low altitude\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "When an aeroplane has zero static longitudinal stability, the pitching moment coefficient Cm versus angle of attack line:",
    "feedback": "is horizontal"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 300 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value 1.44:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 60 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term angle of attack in a two dimensional flow is defined as:",
    "feedback": "the angle between the wing chord line and the direction of the relative wind/airflow."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices is not affected by the angle of attack\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the aspect ratio increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A statically unstable aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "can never be dynamically stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "The forces of lift and drag on an aerofoil are, respectively, normal and parallel to the:",
    "feedback": "relative wind/airflow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about wing sweepback are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Increasing wing sweepback increases Mcrit\n2) Increasing wing sweepback increases the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a take-off roll with a strong crosswind from the right, a four-engine jet aeroplane with wing-mounted engines experiences an engine failure.  The failure of which engine will cause the greatest control problem?",
    "feedback": "The right outboard engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "If indicated air speed and angle of attack are kept constant and density decreases, the lift",
    "feedback": "remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming constant IAS, when an aeroplane leaves ground effect:",
    "feedback": "the induced angle of attack increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "When comparing the properties of laminar and turbulent boundary layers, which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "friction drag is lower in the laminar layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a multi-engine aeroplane. In order to achieve the best possible climb performance, which of the following methods is used to maintain control after an engine failure?",
    "feedback": "Rudder to stop yaw, aileron to bank towards the operating engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the time for a heading change of 360 degrees in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "2 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does stall speed (IAS) vary with altitude?",
    "feedback": "It remains constant at lower altitudes but  increases at higher altitudes due to compressibility effects."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a descent below the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "TAS increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements are correct or incorrect regarding a sideslip, with the relative airflow coming from the right, on an aeroplane that exhibits both directional and lateral stability?\n\n1) The initial tendency of the nose of the aeroplane is to move to the left\n2) The initial tendency of the left wing is to move down",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which considerations have to be taken into account by the pilot when flying a multi-engine aircraft with a failed left engine, causing a sideslip, and the nose pointed to the right?",
    "feedback": "The angle of attack AoA of the fin increases when there is an increase in rudder input towards the operating engine side of the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of buffet will occur if a jet aeroplane slowly accelerates in level flight from its cruise speed in still air at high altitude?",
    "feedback": "Mach buffet"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are the speeds (shown in the figure) at point 1 and point 2 related to the relative wind/airflow V?",
    "feedback": "V1 = 0 and V2 > V"
  },
  {
    "question": "Propeller efficiency is:",
    "feedback": "the ratio of power available (Thrust * TAS) to shaft power (Torque * RPM)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the stall of a straight wing aeroplane is correct?",
    "feedback": "Just before the stall the aeroplane will have a nose-down tendency."
  },
  {
    "question": "Increasing the aspect ratio of a wing:",
    "feedback": "decreases induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the throat is the same as in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The total pressure in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following effects are common to trailing-edge and leading-edge flaps, when compared to a clean wing?\n1) Increase in camber2) Decrease in critical angle of attack3) Increase in CLMAX4) Increase in maximum CL/CD",
    "feedback": "1 and 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The interference drag is the result of:",
    "feedback": "aerodynamic interaction between aeroplane parts (e.g. wing/fuselage)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the polar curve of a subsonic aerofoil, the maximum lift-to-drag ratio is determined by ......",
    "feedback": "drawing a tangent to the curve from the origin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where on the curve in the diagram does the aeroplane exhibit static longitudinal stability?",
    "feedback": "Part 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are required to correctly complete the statement?\nThe characteristics of wing sweep include:\n1) A decreased tendency to tip stall2) Increased take-off and landing distances3) A higher stall speed4) An increased effectiveness of trailing edge control surfaces5) A decreased effectiveness of high lift devices",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lateral axis is also called the",
    "feedback": "pitch axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Propeller gyroscopic effect occurs during aeroplane yaw changes\n2) Propeller gyroscopic effect is most noticeable during low speed flight at low propeller RPM",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A horn balance in a control system has the following purpose:",
    "feedback": "to decrease stick forces."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about the laminar and turbulent boundary layer :",
    "feedback": "friction drag is lower in the laminar layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider an aircraft flying in unaccelerated level flight in the speed stable region. What would be the result on the drag following a sudden increase in aircraft speed with no change in thrust available?",
    "feedback": "The total drag increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the air is passing through an expansion wave the static temperature will",
    "feedback": "decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "The pilots prepare and trim the aircraft for take-off, setting the trim for a CG position at 12 % of the MAC. But due to an error, the real position of the CG is at 24 % of the MAC.\nWhat could be the resulting problem?",
    "feedback": "Risk of over rotation that can lead to a tail strike"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is sensitive to Dutch roll when:",
    "feedback": "static lateral stability is much more pronounced than static directional stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?\nI VMCL is the minimum control speed in the landing configuration.\nII The speed VMCL is always limited by maximum rudder deflecton",
    "feedback": "I is correct, II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the time for a heading change of 180 degrees in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "1 minute"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the Local Speed of Sound (LSS) change with increasing altitude?",
    "feedback": "LSS will decrease in the troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about VMCG determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) VMCG must be determined using rudder control alone\n2) During VMCG determination, the lateral deviation from the runway centreline may be not more than half the distance between the runway centreline and runway edge",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dihedral of a wing is the angle between:",
    "feedback": "the wing plane and the horizontal with the aeroplane in an unbanked, level condition"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane entering ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle increases\n2) The induced angle of attack decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "From the polar diagram of the entire aeroplane one can read:",
    "feedback": "the maximum CL/CD ratio and maximum lift coefficient."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements are correct or incorrect regarding a sideslip, with the relative airflow coming from the left, on an aeroplane that exhibits both directional and lateral stability?\n\n1) The initial tendency of the nose of the aeroplane is to move to the right\n2) The initial tendency of the left wing is to move down",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The local speed of sound in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it\n2) The Mach number in front of an oblique shock wave is higher than behind it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number for an aerofoil is the free stream Mach number at which:",
    "feedback": "sonic speed (M=1) is first reached on the upper surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "When air has passed an expansion wave, the static pressure is:",
    "feedback": "decreased."
  },
  {
    "question": "The drag due to an ageing airframe is identified as?",
    "feedback": "Skin Friction Drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Wing mounted engines extending ahead of the wing contribute to wing flutter suppression\n2) Excessive free play or backlash reduces the speed at which control surface flutter occurs",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In relation to subsonic airflow flowing through a venturi tube, a, b, c, and d represent different velocities. Arrange the letters in order of increasing flow velocity.",
    "feedback": "a, d, b, c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram shows a left co-ordinated turn?",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about boundary layers is correct?",
    "feedback": "A turbulent boundary layer produces more friction drag than a laminar one"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) An elliptical spanwise lift distribution generates more induced drag than a rectangular lift distribution\n2) Induced drag decreases with decreasing aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has a stall speed of 78 KCAS at its mass of 6850 kg. What is the stall speed when the mass is 5000 kg ?",
    "feedback": "67 KCAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "The point in the diagram corresponding to the minimum value of the drag coefficient is:",
    "feedback": "point 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "When ice is present on the stabilizer, deflection of flaps may cause:",
    "feedback": "the stabilizer to stall and a vertical dive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a subsonic airflow moving steadily through a venturi tube with no leaks. The numbers identify areas of different speeds. Which of the following sequences correctly identifies the areas in order of increasing airspeed?",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "If an airplane has poor longitudinal stability in flight, what can be done to increase the stability?",
    "feedback": "increase stabiliser surface area"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vortex generators (1) ...... boundary layer separation by (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) delay, (2) adding energy to it"
  },
  {
    "question": "The movement of an aircraft is defined along three axes which all pass through:",
    "feedback": "the centre of gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you want to maintain a constant TAS during a climb, you should during the climb",
    "feedback": "Reduce to a lower IAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed in flight at which the power required is at a minimum, is:",
    "feedback": "below Vmd"
  },
  {
    "question": "In flight the C of P by increasing angle of attack, will reach its most forward point on an airfoil:",
    "feedback": "just below the stalling angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed lines in the manoeuvring load diagram originate from a point where the:",
    "feedback": "speed = 0, load factor = 0"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed lines in the manoeuvring load diagram runs through a point where the:",
    "feedback": "speed = VA, load factor = limit load factor"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed increases, when: (all other factors of importance being constant)",
    "feedback": "pulling up from a dive."
  },
  {
    "question": "When the stick force required to achieve a load factor of 2.5 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is 225 N, the value of the manoeuvre stability of that aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "150 N/g"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift coefficient CL versus angle of attack curve of a symmetrical aerofoil section intersects the vertical axis of the graph:",
    "feedback": "at the origin"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the lift coefficient CI of a negatively cambered aerofoil section is zero, the pitching moment is:",
    "feedback": "nose up (positive)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the mass increases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the altitude increases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is adverse yaw compensated for during entry into and roll out from a turn ?",
    "feedback": "Differential aileron deflection"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the undisturbed airflow is the same than in the throat\n2) The speed in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.8 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 1.9, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "n = 2.00"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approximately how long does it take to fly a complete circle during a horizontal steady co-ordinated turn with a bank angle of 15° and a TAS of 530 kt?",
    "feedback": "650 s"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given that:\n\npstat = static pressure\nrho = density\npdyn = dynamic pressure\np tot = total pressure\n\nBernoulli's equation reads as follows:",
    "feedback": "pstat + 1/2 rho * TAS^2 = constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift to drag ratio determines the:",
    "feedback": "horizontal glide distance from a given altitude at zero wind and zero thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the effect of wing downwash on the direction of the airflow approaching the tailplane, when flaps are extended the tailplane's negative angle of attack ......",
    "feedback": "increases, increasing the tailplane's effectiveness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for a side slip condition at constant speed and side slip angle, where the geometric dihedral of an aeroplane is increased ?",
    "feedback": "the required lateral control force increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly decreases the speed by 80 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "decrease to 0.36"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which aeroplane and situation experiences the most amount of induced drag reduction?",
    "feedback": "Low wing on take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aft CG shift:",
    "feedback": "decreases static longitudinal stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the blades of a propeller are in the feathered position:",
    "feedback": "the drag of the propeller is then minimal."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about weight or mass is correct?",
    "feedback": "The weight of a body can be determined by multiplying its mass by the acceleration due to gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider high speed aerodynamics: An aeroplane accelerates from low speed to a speed just below MCRIT in straight and level flight. What changes to the airflow around the aeroplane can you expect to take place?",
    "feedback": "The airflow becomes more turbulent due to the presence of areas of increased compressibility, slowing down the speed of the airflow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared with stalling airspeed (VS) in a given configuration, the airspeed at which stick shaker will be triggered is:",
    "feedback": "greater than VS."
  },
  {
    "question": "Compressibility effects depend on:",
    "feedback": "Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "At stalling speed, the stall warning vane on the leading edge of small aeroplanes moves:",
    "feedback": "Up due to movement of the stagnation point"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the wing area decreases, the gust load factor decreases\n2) When the EAS decreases, the gust load factor decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ignoring downwash effects on the tailplane, extension of Fowler flaps, will produce:",
    "feedback": "a nose down pitching moment"
  },
  {
    "question": "The glide range of an aircraft is affected by:",
    "feedback": "the lift/drag ratio"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane to possess dynamic stability, it needs:",
    "feedback": "static stability and sufficient damping"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a climb at a constant IAS, the Mach number will:",
    "feedback": "increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about propellers is correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A cruise propeller has a greater geometric pitch when compared with a climb propeller\n2) A coarse pitch propeller is less efficient during take-off and in the climb, but more efficient in the cruise, when compared with a fine pitch propeller",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following is true concerning a balance tab. It is:",
    "feedback": "a form of aerodynamic balance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Based on the two-dimensional flight drag formula, drag is ....",
    "feedback": "proportional to the square of the speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) An elliptical spanwise lift distribution generates more induced drag than a rectangular lift distribution\n2) Induced drag increases with decreasing aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about VMCG determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) VMCG must be determined using both lateral and directional control\n2) During VMCG determination, the lateral deviation from the runway centreline may be not more than half the distance between the runway centreline and runway edge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane with swept back wings is equipped with slats and/or leading edge (L.E.) flaps. One possible efficient way to arrange the leading edge devices on the wings is:",
    "feedback": "Wing roots: L.E. flaps\nWing tips: slats"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a climbing turn to the right the:",
    "feedback": "angle of attack of the left wing is larger than the angle of attack of the right wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Arrange the flaps in order of increasing L/D ratio:",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "VMO:",
    "feedback": "should be not greater than VC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Just after take-off, a pilot inadvertently rectracts the flaps instead of the landing gear. What are the consequences?",
    "feedback": "The aeroplane will stall if the speed is lower than the stall speed in clean configuration"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft climbs to FL210 with a CAS of 150 kt. Once reaching and maintaining FL210 it accelerates to cruise speed whilst maintaining the same heading. What happens to the lift coefficient?",
    "feedback": "It decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A propeller is said to be \"double acting\" when it:",
    "feedback": "uses oil pressure to move the blade toward fine and coarse"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effective angle of attack of an aeroplane in ground effect will (1) ..... due to the (2) ..... downwash.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) reduced"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.\nWhen extending spoilers, what will happen to the stall speed and critical AoA?",
    "feedback": "Higher critical AoA and higher stall speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding the lift formula, if airspeed doubles, lift will:",
    "feedback": "be 4 times greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and no compressibility effects, if an aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at the same angle of attack at two different altitudes, the:",
    "feedback": "TAS is lower at the lower altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains constant IAS in a climb. Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "The maximum coefficient of lift decreases with increasing Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "In supersonic flight aerofoil pressure distribution is:",
    "feedback": "rectangular."
  },
  {
    "question": "Excessive static lateral stability is an undesirable characteristic for a transport aeroplane because:",
    "feedback": "it would impose excessive demands on roll control during a sideslip"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the three lift augmentation devices is/are represented by the graph?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft with swept wings is better suited to cruising at higher Mach numbers due to reduced speed in the direction (1) ...... to the wing span, compared to the (2) ...... . This speed varies with the (3) ...... of the sweep angle.",
    "feedback": "(1) perpendicular, (2) free stream flow, (3) cosine"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the lift coefficient CI of a positively cambered aerofoil section is zero, the pitching moment is:",
    "feedback": "nose down (negative)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the highest speed possible without supersonic flow over the wing?",
    "feedback": "Critical Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "The induced drag:",
    "feedback": "increases as the lift coefficient increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "The de-icing of a propeller by fluid is achieved through:",
    "feedback": "slinger rings"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following series of configurations has an increasing critical angle of attack?",
    "feedback": "flaps only extended, clean wing, slats only extended."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the time for a heading change of 60 degrees in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "20 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "To perform a co-ordinated turn the aeroplane in diagram 1 should use:",
    "feedback": "more left rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and no compressibility effects, if an aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at the same angle of attack at two different altitudes, the:",
    "feedback": "TAS is higher at the higher altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "A statically stable aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "can show positive, neutral or negative dynamic longitudinal stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Moving the engines from the wing to the aft fuselage improves wing flutter suppression\n2) Excessive free play or backlash increases the speed at which control surface flutter occurs",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about a propeller is correct?\n\n1) Asymmetric blade effect reduces when engine power is increased\n2) Asymmetric blade effect increases when the angle between the propeller axis and airflow through the propeller disc increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A four-engine aeroplane has an engine failure just after take-off at the maximum take-off thrust setting. The resulting moment around the normal axis will be greatest when an ....",
    "feedback": "outboard engine fails and the airport is at low altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning longitudinal stability and control is correct?",
    "feedback": "A bob weight and a down spring have the same effect on the stick force stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane entering ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle decreases\n2) The induced angle of attack decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is less than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "when lift is less than weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following a disturbance, an aeroplane oscillates about the lateral axis at a constant amplitude. The aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "statically stable - Dynamically neutral"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a wing fitted with a \"fowler\" type trailing edge flap, the \"Full extended\" position will produce:",
    "feedback": "an increase in wing area and camber."
  },
  {
    "question": "VMCA is certified with a bank angle of not more than 5° towards the operating engine (live engine low) because:",
    "feedback": "although more bank reduces VMCA, too much bank may lead to fin stall"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying at the maximum rate of climb speed (Vy) you will obtain maximum:",
    "feedback": "Altitude in the shortest time"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which load factor determines VA?",
    "feedback": "manoeuvring limit load factor."
  },
  {
    "question": "In a single engine a/c with clockwise rotating  propeller, a left yaw is generated due to:",
    "feedback": "the slipstream,  striking the fin on the left side"
  },
  {
    "question": "Static directional stability is the:",
    "feedback": "tendency of an aeroplane to recover from a skid with the rudder free"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Tuck under\" may happen at:",
    "feedback": "high Mach numbers."
  },
  {
    "question": "Given an aeroplane with a propeller turning clockwise as seen from behind, the torque effect during the take off run will tend to:",
    "feedback": "roll the aeroplane to the left"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\n\np = pressure\nrho = density\nT = absolute temperature\n\nThe relationship between pressure, density and absolute temperature of a given mass of air can be expressed as follows:",
    "feedback": "p/ (rho * T) = constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing flutter can be prevented by:",
    "feedback": "ensuring that the wing CG is ahead of its torsional axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "During flap down selection in a continuous straight and level flight at constant IAS and weight:",
    "feedback": "the centre of pressure moves aft."
  },
  {
    "question": "An experimental aircraft has a rectangular wing that, when generating zero lift, is producing a drag value of 865 N. What would be the value if the wing area was increased by 10 %?",
    "feedback": "954 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "The boundary layer is considered to be turbulent...",
    "feedback": "between the transition and separation points"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of winglets on the drag of the wing?",
    "feedback": "Increase parasite drag, decrease induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the speed over an aerofoil section increases from subsonic to supersonic, its aerodynamic centre:",
    "feedback": "moves from 25% to about 50% of the chord"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the Mach number change during a climb at constant IAS from sea level to 40000 ft?",
    "feedback": "Increases with increasing altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight decelerates whilst maintaining its configuration. The lift coefficient will:",
    "feedback": "Increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Control surface flutter can be eliminated by:",
    "feedback": "mass balancing of the control surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "A large cargo aircraft is fully loaded, ready for departure and with the trim set. The PIC is informed that extra cargo is being loaded onto the aircraft, forward of CG. The PIC amends the load sheet and attains a revised trim setting. What would the trim adjustment be?",
    "feedback": "Aft - lowering the leading edge of the stabiliser"
  },
  {
    "question": "The static pressure acts:",
    "feedback": "in all directions."
  },
  {
    "question": "The first action in event of propeller runaway (overspeed condition), should be to:",
    "feedback": "close the throttle"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aerodynamic centre of the wing is the point, where:",
    "feedback": "pitching moment coefficient does not vary with angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight instructor is teaching a student of a multi-engine piston aeroplane the practice of an engine failure. What is the most favourable configuration during the first engine failure exercise?",
    "feedback": "An airplane mass of 4400 lbs so that the rudder has greater effectiveness"
  },
  {
    "question": "To increase the critical Mach number a conventional aerofoil section:",
    "feedback": "its thickness to chord ratio should be reduced"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can you find VMD on a polar curve graph?",
    "feedback": "Tangent from the origin"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is possible to reduce the spanwise airflow over swept wings, due to adverse pressure gradients, by:",
    "feedback": "wing fences"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram represents a left turn with not enough bank?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 2 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "25%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Propeller blade twist is the:",
    "feedback": "varying of the blade angle from the root to the tip of a propeller blade"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying in the transonic speed range in straight and level flight.\n\nIf the Mach number decreases, what additional input or action will be required to maintain straight and level flight to compensate for the centre of pressure's movement, whilst exiting the transonic region?",
    "feedback": "A pitch down input to the elevator or the stabiliser"
  },
  {
    "question": "From EAS and density altitude you can derive:",
    "feedback": "TAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "Flight in severe turbulence may lead to a stall and/or structural limitations being exceeded"
  },
  {
    "question": "A primary stop is mounted on an elevator control system in order to:",
    "feedback": "restrict the range of movement of the elevator"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "spoiler extension increases the stall speed, the minimum rate of descent and the minimum angle of descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where would you expect the forward stagnation point of an aerofoil to be during slow flight?",
    "feedback": "Lower surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the limiting value of 5 degrees bank angle during VMCA determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) As the bank angle is decreased from 5 degrees to 0 degrees, the value of VMCA increases\n2) When the bank angle is increased beyond 5 degrees, there is an increasing risk of fin stall",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of attack of a rotating propeller blade element shown in the diagram is:",
    "feedback": "angle 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a convergent tube with an incompressible sub-sonic airflow, the following pressure changes will occur:\n\nPs = static pressure\nPdyn = dynamic pressure\nPtot = total pressure",
    "feedback": "Ps decreases, Pdyn increases, Ptot remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the wing area is increased, lift will:",
    "feedback": "increase because it is directly proportional to wing area"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet aeroplane is holding over a fix when the pilot observes that the aircraft is about to enter an area of heavy tropical rain. The pilot has to ......",
    "feedback": "increase holding speed and thrust to anticipate for the increased drag due to the film of water on the aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about elevators is correct?",
    "feedback": "The elevator is the primary control surface for control about the lateral axis and is operated by a forward or backward movement of the control wheel or stick"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed corresponding to 1.1 VS with a lift coefficient CL of 1.22. What will be the new value of CL, if the aeroplane accelerates up to 1.8 VS?",
    "feedback": "0.46"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two methods to increase the critical Mach Number are:",
    "feedback": "thin aerofoils and sweep back of the wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "Rotation about the longitudinal axis of an aeroplane can be achieved by:",
    "feedback": "aileron deflection and/or rudder deflection"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a climb above the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "lift coefficient increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft with dirt on the airframe is subject to what type of drag?",
    "feedback": "Friction drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the CG position is moved forward, the elevator deflection to achieve a given load factor greater than 1 will be:",
    "feedback": "larger"
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of ailerons is to rotate the aeroplane about the:",
    "feedback": "longitudinal axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is a propeller blade twisted from root to tip?",
    "feedback": "Because the local angle of attack of a blade segment is dependent on the ratio of that segment 's speed in the plane of rotation and the true airspeed of the aeroplane."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is going to happen to the angle of attack, controllability and stall speed if an airplane encounters icing during flight?",
    "feedback": "Angle of attack and controllability are going to decrease, stall speed is going to increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "To be able to predict compressibility effects you have to determine the:",
    "feedback": "Mach Number."
  },
  {
    "question": "The dihedral construction of an aircraft wing provides:",
    "feedback": "lateral stability about the longitudinal axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two identical aeroplanes A and B, with the same mass, are flying steady level co-ordinated 20 degree bank turns. If the TAS of A is 130 kt and the TAS of B is 200 kt:",
    "feedback": "The lift coefficient of A is greater than that of B"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a normal stable aeroplane, the centre of gravity is located:",
    "feedback": "with a sufficient minimum margin ahead of the neutral point of the aeroplane."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is climbing at a constant IAS, just before the high speed buffet. What should the pilot expect during the climb?",
    "feedback": "CL remains the same"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the consequence of decreasing the wing's upwash?",
    "feedback": "Decrease induced drag since effective AoA increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices is not affected by aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "All gust lines in the gust load diagram originate from a point where the:",
    "feedback": "speed = 0, load factor = +1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The Mach number behind an oblique shock wave is lower than in front of it\n2) The total pressure behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has static directional stability if, when in a sideslip with the relative airflow coming from the left, initially the:",
    "feedback": "nose of the aeroplane tends to yaw left"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is less than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "during a steady wings level climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a swept wing aeroplane at low airspeed, the \"pitch up\" phenomenon:",
    "feedback": "is caused by wingtip stall."
  },
  {
    "question": "The point of minimum static pressure on a positively cambered aerofoil flying at a low subsonic speed at a positive angle of attack is ......",
    "feedback": "on the upper surface, where the speed is highest"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 12\nThrust per engine: 28000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a three-engine aeroplane, the one-engine inoperative climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "2.9 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the altitude is increased and the TAS remains constant in the troposphere under standard atmospheric conditions, the Mach Number will:",
    "feedback": "increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a straight and level horizontal flight at the same angle of attack at two different altitudes. (all other factors of importance being constant, assume ISA conditions and no compressibility effects)",
    "feedback": "the TAS at the higher altitude is higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the stick force required to achieve a load factor of 2.5 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is 450 N, the value of the manoeuvre stability of that aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "300 N/g"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regards to wing planforms and spanwise lift distribution, which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "An elliptical wing produces more lift closer to the root"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?\nI When the critical engine fails during take-off the speed VMCL can be limiting.\nII The speed VMCL is always limited by maximum rudder deflection",
    "feedback": "I is incorrect, II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a fixed-pitch propeller designed for cruise, the angle of attack of each blade, measured at the reference section:",
    "feedback": "is optimum when the aircraft is in a stabilized cruising flight."
  },
  {
    "question": "The purpose of deploying leading edge slats is to:",
    "feedback": "increase the stalling angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift coefficient CI versus angle of attack curve of a negatively cambered aerofoil section intersects the horizontal axis of the graph:",
    "feedback": "to the right of the origin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main purpose of a boundary layer fence on a swept wing is to:",
    "feedback": "improve the low speed handling characteristics"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number of a conventional aerofoil section decreases if:",
    "feedback": "its leading edge radius is increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Load factor is :",
    "feedback": "Lift/Weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "The (subsonic) static pressure:",
    "feedback": "decreases in a flow in a tube when the diameter decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst flying at a constant IAS and at n = 1, as the aeroplane mass increases, the value of Mcrit:",
    "feedback": "decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew calculate landing speeds for a full flap landing (30°) but, due to distraction, omit to extend flaps further than the approach setting (15°). Which of the following statements is correct assuming the correct glidepath was flown to touchdown?",
    "feedback": "Landing distance available may be insufficient and a tail strike is more likely"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.1 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2.1, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "irrelevant, since the aeroplane would already be in a stalled condition at 1.1 VS with that gust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the CL augmentation devices represented in the figure:",
    "feedback": "1) variable camber flaps, 2) Krueger flaps, 3) slats"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flaps are extended whilst maintaining straight and level flight at constant IAS, the lift coefficient will:",
    "feedback": "eventually remain the same"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which phase of the take-off is the aerodynamic effect of ice located on the wing leading edge most critical?",
    "feedback": "The rotation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no pilot input the motion of the aeroplane in the diagram shows:",
    "feedback": "dynamic longitudinal stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the total drag vary as speed is increased from stalling speed (VS) to maximum IAS (VNE) in a straight and level flight at constant weight?",
    "feedback": "Decreasing, then increasing."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of stall has the largest associated angle of attack?",
    "feedback": "Deep stall."
  },
  {
    "question": "Increasing the angle of attack  in flight will cause the:",
    "feedback": "stagnation point to move down and aft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about wing sweepback are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Decreasing wing sweepback increases Mcrit\n2) Decreasing wing sweepback decreases the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the angle called, represented in the figure?",
    "feedback": "Sideslip angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flaperons are controls, which combine the function of:",
    "feedback": "ailerons and flaps"
  },
  {
    "question": "Downwash increases when ......",
    "feedback": "wingtip vortices increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 12\nThrust per engine: 20000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a four-engine aeroplane, the all-engines climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "7.7 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.5 VS. If, at this speed,  a vertical gust causes a load factor of 1.75, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "n = 2.00"
  },
  {
    "question": "The purpose of the horizontal stabilizer  is to:",
    "feedback": "give the aeroplane sufficient longitudinal stability."
  },
  {
    "question": "What should be usually done to perform a landing with the stabiliser jammed in the cruise flight position?",
    "feedback": "choose a higher landing speed than normal and/or use a lower flap setting for landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about an expansion wave in a supersonic flow ?\n\n1- The density in front of an expansion wave is higher than behind.\n\n2- The pressure in front of an expansion wave is higher than behind.",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is flying an aeroplane whose clean configuration stall speed, as listed in the Flight Manual, is 60 kt. While in the cruise at 95 kt the pilot has to take avoiding action against another aeroplane. The pilot banks the aeroplane sharply and during the course of this manoeuvre, the aeroplane stalls. Why did the aeroplane stall at 95 kt?",
    "feedback": "A wings stalls when its critical angle of attack is exceeded, regardless of speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram shows a right co-ordinated turn?",
    "feedback": "5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wave drag above MCRIT consists of:",
    "feedback": "Energy drag and boundary layer separation"
  },
  {
    "question": "To perform a co-ordinated turn the aeroplane in diagram 4 should use:",
    "feedback": "more right rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "The variation of propeller efficiency of a fixed pitch propeller with TAS at a given RPM is shown in:",
    "feedback": "figure 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 12\nThrust per engine: 60000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a twin engine aeroplane, the all-engines climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "15.7 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the exterior view of an aeroplane change, when the trim is used during a speed decrease ?",
    "feedback": "The elevator is deflected further upwards by means of a downwards deflected trimtab."
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicated stalling speed varies with varying temperature.",
    "feedback": "FALSE"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct statement:",
    "feedback": "Aerofoil 2 corresponds to line 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The elevator deflection required for a given manoeuvre will be:",
    "feedback": "larger for a forward CG position when compared to an aft position"
  },
  {
    "question": "Using the diagram of the forces affecting a propeller in flight, which arrow represents the torque moment?",
    "feedback": "A"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of failure of the Mach trimmer:",
    "feedback": "the Mach number must be limited"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors causes form drag on an object in high-speed air flow?",
    "feedback": "The pressure difference between leading edge and trailing edge"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning the local flow pattern around a wing is correct?",
    "feedback": "By fitting winglets to the wing tip, the strength of the wing tip vortices is reduced which in turn reduces induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane weighing 100 tons is turning at FL350 at constant altitude with a bank angle of 50°. The low-speed buffet boundary is .... (i) and the high-speed buffet boundary is .... (ii):",
    "feedback": "(i) M 0,69  (ii) M 0,84"
  },
  {
    "question": "One advantage of a movable-stabilizer system compared with a fixed stabilizer system is that:",
    "feedback": "it is a more powerful means of trimming"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does stalling speed vary with load factor?",
    "feedback": "It increases proportionally with the square root of the load factor."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 200 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value of 1.44:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 40 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a right turn, the slip indicator is right of neutral. One way to co-ordinate the turn is to apply:",
    "feedback": "more right rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "When roll spoilers are extended, the part of the wing on which they are mounted:",
    "feedback": "experiences a reduction in lift, which generates the desired rolling moment. In addition there is a local increase in drag, which suppresses adverse yaw."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is in a steady turn, at a constant TAS of 200 kt. Its turning radius is equal to 1080m. What is the load factor during this turn?\n(given: g= 10 m/s²)",
    "feedback": "1.4"
  },
  {
    "question": "After take-off the slats (when installed) are always retracted later than the flaps. Why ?",
    "feedback": "Because SLATS EXTENDED gives a large decrease in stall speed with relatively less drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "How will the density and temperature change in a supersonic flow from a position in front of a shock wave to behind it ?",
    "feedback": "Density will increase, temperature will increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.9 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 1.95 the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "n = 2.00"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.9 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "28%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The total drag of a three dimensional wing consists of:",
    "feedback": "induced drag and parasite drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about a propeller is correct?\n\n1) Asymmetric blade effect reduces when engine power is increased\n2) Asymmetric blade effect reduces when the angle between the propeller axis and airflow through the propeller disc increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane entering ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle decreases\n2) The induced angle of attack increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number of an aeroplane is the Mach number:",
    "feedback": "above which, locally, supersonic flow exists somewhere over the aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct when comparing a fixed pitch propeller with a constant speed propeller?\n\n1) A fixed pitch propeller improves propeller efficiency over a range of cruise speeds\n2) A constant speed propeller improves take-off performance as compared with a coarse fixed pitch propeller",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Dynamic stability is possible only when the aeroplane is statically stable about the relevant axis."
  },
  {
    "question": "When the stick force required to achieve a load factor of 3 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is 240 N, the value of the manoeuvre stability of that aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "120 N/g"
  },
  {
    "question": "If pressure is kept constant and temperature increases, the density",
    "feedback": "decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about propeller noise is correct?\n\n1) Propeller noise increases when the blade tip speed increases\n2) For a given engine and propeller blade shape, an increase in the number of propeller blades allows for a reduction in propeller noise",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The drag divergence Mach number is equal to Mcrit\n2) Below the drag divergence Mach number and for a given angle of attack the drag coefficient CD decreases as the Mach number decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The total pressure in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing sweep has:",
    "feedback": "A negative influence on stall characteristics, as it increases stalling speed and could cause tip stall"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the pitching moment coefficient versus angle of attack lines in the diagram is correct?",
    "feedback": "The CG position is further forward at line 3 when compared with line 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "The span-wise flow on an unswept wing is from the:",
    "feedback": "lower to the upper surface via the wing tip"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about wing sweepback are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Decreasing wing sweepback decreases Mcrit\n2) Decreasing wing sweepback increases the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about the Cl and angle of attack?",
    "feedback": "for a symmetric aerofoil, if angle of attack = 0, Cl =0"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about a propeller is correct?\n\n1) Asymmetric blade effect increases when engine power is increased\n2) Asymmetric blade effect increases when the angle between the propeller axis and airflow through the propeller disc increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Stall speeds are determined with the CG at the forward limit\n2) Minimum control speeds are determined with the CG at the forward limit",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The position of the centre of pressure on an aerofoil of an aeroplane curising at supersonic speed when compared with that at subsonic speed is:",
    "feedback": "further aft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about propeller icing is correct?\n\n1) Propeller icing reduces blade element drag and increases blade element lift\n2) Propeller icing reduces propeller efficiency",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The purpose of the feathering stop on a variable pitch propeller is to:",
    "feedback": "prevent the propeller blades from moving beyond the feather position"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices increases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the aspect ratio increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.1 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "83%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transition point is the point where:",
    "feedback": "the boundary layer changes from laminar to turbulent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices is not affected by angle of attack\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A modern jet transport aeroplane is cruising at 35000 ft in an area of mountain waves. The cruising speed is at M 0.79 with the MMO at M 0.81 when the aeroplane suddenly experiences a positive wind shear. The autothrust is slow at reacting and the aeroplane reaches a speed of M 0.82 before starting to decelerate again. Apart from an overspeed warning, are there any other indications of the overspeed that may be apparent to the pilots?",
    "feedback": "With their feet resting on the floor, a slight vibration is felt through the fuselage structure, otherwise the aeroplane observes normal behaviour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Behind a normal shock wave on an aerofoil section the local Mach number is:",
    "feedback": "less than 1."
  },
  {
    "question": "A shock wave on a lift generating wing will:",
    "feedback": "move slightly forward in front of a upward deflecting aileron"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane that has positive static stability:",
    "feedback": "can be dynamically stable, neutral or unstable"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of drag will a fairing smoothening the angles where the wing meets the fuselage at the wing root reduce?",
    "feedback": "Interference drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about \"tuck under\" are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A contributing factor to \"tuck under\" is a forward movement of the centre of pressure of the wing\n2) A contributing factor to \"tuck under\" is a reduction in the downwash angle at the location of the horizontal stabiliser",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When trimmed for zero elevator stick force an elevator trim tab causes more drag\n2) A horizontal trimmable stabiliser enables a larger CG range",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane should be equipped with a Mach trimmer, if:",
    "feedback": "at transonic Mach numbers the aeroplane displays an unacceptable decrease in longitudinal stick force stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "High lift devices are used:",
    "feedback": "During approach in order to reduce flight speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wing angle of incidence usually varies from root to tip. This is called wing washout and its purpose is ......",
    "feedback": "to ensure that stall occurs at the root first, maximising controllability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements are correct or incorrect regarding a sideslip, with the relative airflow coming from the right, on an aeroplane that exhibits both directional and lateral stability?\n\n1) The initial tendency of the nose of the aeroplane is to move to the left\n2) The initial tendency of the right wing is to move down",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.\nWhat is the effect of spoilers on the angle of attack and stall speed at a constant mass?",
    "feedback": "With increasing spoilers, both the angle of attack and stall speed increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Reducing wing aspect ratio will:",
    "feedback": "Reduce the lift coefficient obtained for a given angle of attack and increase the critical angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following would cause a reduction in interference drag?",
    "feedback": "Reducing the number of external surfaces meeting at an angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the mass decreases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the altitude decreases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet transport aeroplane exhibits pitch up when thrust is suddenly increased from an equilibrium condition, because the thrust line is below the:",
    "feedback": "CG"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a glide with idle power and constant IAS, if the RPM lever of a constant speed propeller is pushed full forward from its normal cruise position, the propeller pitch will:",
    "feedback": "decrease and the rate of descent will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a given aeroplane which two main variables determine the value of VMCG?",
    "feedback": "Airport elevation and temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "A line drawn from the leading edge to the trailing edge of an airfoil and equidistant at all points from the upper and lower contours is called the",
    "feedback": "mean camber line."
  },
  {
    "question": "For a statically stable aeroplane, the relationship between the neutral point and centre of gravity (CG) is such that the neutral point is located:",
    "feedback": "aft of the CG"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions could result in the absence of a stall warning on a jet aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "Ice on the wings causing a stall at a lower angle of attack than the normal critical angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) An rectangular spanwise lift distribution generates more induced drag than an elliptical lift distribution\n2) Induced drag decreases with increasing aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following situations leads to a decreasing stall speed (IAS)?",
    "feedback": "decreasing weight."
  },
  {
    "question": "The positive manoeuvring limit load factor for a light aeroplane in the utility category in the clean configuration is:",
    "feedback": "4.4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which CG position with respect to the neutral point ensures static longitudinal stability?",
    "feedback": "CG ahead of the neutral point"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about a primary control surface controlled by a servo tab, is correct ?",
    "feedback": "The position is undetermined during taxiing, in particular with tailwind."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying straight and level. Assuming there are no mechanical malfunctions or environmental errors affecting the indicator, what can be said to remain constant if the speed indicated on the Airspeed Indicator does not change?",
    "feedback": "Dynamic pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Static lateral stability will be decreased by:",
    "feedback": "reducing wing sweepback"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight flight, as speed is reduced, whilst trimming to keep the stick force zero:",
    "feedback": "the elevator is deflected further upwards and the trim tab further downwards"
  },
  {
    "question": "In general, directional controllability with one engine inoperative on a multi-engine aeroplane is favourably affected by:\n1) high temperature\n2) low temperature\n3) aft CG location\n4) forward CG location\n5) high altitude\n6) low altitude\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure increases as the streamlines diverge\n2) the velocity increases as the streamlines diverge",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Constant-speed propellers provide a better performance than fixed-pitch propellers because they:",
    "feedback": "produce an almost maximum efficiency over a wider speed range."
  },
  {
    "question": "Angle \"Y\" in the diagram corresponds to the:",
    "feedback": "Pitch or blade angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The density in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it\n2) The total pressure in front of an oblique shock wave is higher than behind it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane without icing protection ventures into atmospheric conditions where icing will occur. What effect will this have on the aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "Stall speed will increase, and both the critical angle of attack and controllability will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Upon extension of Fowler flaps whilst maintaining the same angle of attack:",
    "feedback": "CL and CD increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "A windmilling propeller:",
    "feedback": "produces drag instead of thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will be the consequence on the speed of the aircraft while going from point B to point C and maintaining steady, straight and level flight?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft will be flown at a slower speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "A straight, cambered wing aeroplane is used to demonstrate slow flight and stalls to a student pilot. The pilot maintains straight and level flight while the speed decreases until the aeroplane eventually stalls. During this demonstration, the centre of pressure ......",
    "feedback": "moves forward until the stall, then moves aft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nTo avoid low speed buffet in a turn at 30 degrees of bank and at a mass of 100 tons the following conditions must be fulfilled (approximately):",
    "feedback": "FL < = 410 at M > = 0.69 or FL < = 380 at M > = 0.64"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line represents the total drag line of an aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "Line c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a multi-engine aeroplane with counter-rotating propellers turning inwards. If the left engine fails, to counteract the yaw moment, you would need to apply a smaller force compared to an aircraft equipped with two clockwise rotating propellers, because ....",
    "feedback": "at slow speed the thrust vector is closer towards the aircraft's longitudinal axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The units of the density of the air (I) and the force (II) are:",
    "feedback": "(I) kg / m3, (II) N."
  },
  {
    "question": "If the Mach number of an aeroplane in supersonic flight is increased, the Mach cone angle will:",
    "feedback": "decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?\n\n1) A dorsal fin increases the contribution of the vertical tail plane to the static directional stability, in particular at large angles of attack\n2) A dorsal and a ventral fin both have a positive effect on static lateral stability",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Airflow separation is characterised by:",
    "feedback": "Airflow reversal on the surface of the body"
  },
  {
    "question": "A propeller is turning to the right when viewed from behind. The asymmetric blade effect in the climb at low speed will:",
    "feedback": "yaw the aeroplane to the left"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane leaving ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL increases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi remains constant",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The subsonic speed range:",
    "feedback": "ends at Mcrit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the Mach number increases the buffet free range does not change\n2) When the load factor decreases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the retraction of the flaps at a constant angle of attack the aeroplane starts to (all other factors of importance being constant)",
    "feedback": "sink suddenly."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly increases the speed by 10 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "increase to 1.10"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about propeller icing is correct?\n\n1) Propeller icing increases blade element drag and reduces blade element lift\n2) Propeller icing reduces propeller efficiency",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "As the angle of attack increases, the stagnation point on the wing's profile moves downwards."
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the following aeroplane configurations:\n\n1) Clean wing.\n2) Slat only extended.\n3) Flaps only extended.\n\nPlace these configurations in order of increasing critical angle of attack:",
    "feedback": "3, 1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the transonic speed region the L/D ratio is ......",
    "feedback": "reduced"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?  1) When the CG moves aft the buffet free range decreases 2) When the Mach number decreases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which point shown in the figure corresponds with CL for minimum horizontal flight speed?",
    "feedback": "Point D"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about VMCG determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) In order to simulate a wet runway, nose wheel steering may not be used during VMCG determination\n2) During VMCG determination, the CG should be on the forward limit",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet aeroplane equipped with inboard and outboard ailerons is cruising at its normal cruise Mach number. In this case",
    "feedback": "only the inboard ailerons are active."
  },
  {
    "question": "What can happen to the aeroplane structure flying at a speed just exceeding VA ?",
    "feedback": "It may suffer permanent deformation if the elevator is fully deflected upwards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed decreases the buffet free range decreases\n2) When the CG moves forward the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ventral fin has its greatest effect at",
    "feedback": "Low speed, high angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aerodynamic characteristics of an aircraft in a spin is that the:",
    "feedback": "outer wing is partially stalled"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane, with a C.G. location behind the centre of pressure of the wing can only maintain a straight and level flight when the horizontal tail loading is:",
    "feedback": "upwards."
  },
  {
    "question": "The relationship between the stall speed VS and VA (EAS) for a large transport aeroplane can be expressed in the following formula:\n(SQRT= square root)",
    "feedback": "VA= VS SQRT(2.5)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A body is placed in a certain airstream. The airstream velocity increases by a factor 4. The aerodynamic drag will increase with a factor :",
    "feedback": "16 ."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a climb above the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "TAS remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft with a conventional, cambered aerofoil accelerates through the transonic speed range. Shock waves form on the upper and lower surfaces of the wing. While the aircraft continues to accelerate, the shock wave on the lower surface initially moves aft ......",
    "feedback": "more quickly than the upper shock wave"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a constant airspeed, a reduction in an aerofoil's angle of attack results in the speed of the flow over the upper surface to ......",
    "feedback": "decrease and the lifting ability of the aerofoil to decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct statement:",
    "feedback": "Aerofoil 4 corresponds to line 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The change in CL represented in the graph corresponds to what device(s)?",
    "feedback": "1 and 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared with an oblique shock wave at the same Mach number a normal shock wave has a",
    "feedback": "higher loss in total pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding the lift formula, if density doubles, lift will:",
    "feedback": "also double"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Flying at M = 0.8 provides the optimum margin with respect to buffet onset\n2) The maximum altitude that can be achieved with respect to buffet onset according EASA/CS regulations is higher at M = 0.82 than at M = 0.75",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the undisturbed airflow is the same than in the throat\n2) The total pressure in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The frontal area of a body, placed in a certain airstream is increased by a factor 3. The shape will not alter. The aerodynamic drag will increase with a factor :",
    "feedback": "3 ."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices increases as the angle of attack increases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly increases the speed by 60 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "increase to 1.69"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly increases the speed by 80 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "increase to 1.96"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The static temperature behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it\n2) The static pressure behind an oblique shock wave is lower than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight while the IAS is doubled. The change in lift coefficient will be:",
    "feedback": "x 0.25"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the approach, the pilot inadvertently retracts the flaps. Due to a malfunction, the flaps are retracted as in the figure. How should the pilot react?",
    "feedback": "Roll to the right and left rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect does ageing of an aeroplane have on the boundary layer condition?",
    "feedback": "The transition point moves forward and a larger part is turbulent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line in the Cm versus angle of attack graph shows a statically stable aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "Line 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Differential aileron deflection:",
    "feedback": "equals the drag of the right and left aileron."
  },
  {
    "question": "A twin engine jet transport aeroplane is taking off from runway 27 with a wind of 210/15 and an outside air temperature (OAT) of 20°C.\nThe failure of which engine would require the largest control inputs to maintain runway centreline?",
    "feedback": "Failure of the left engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the slope of the lift versus angle of attack curve decreases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the wing loading decreases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a steady horizontal, co-ordinated turn with 45 degrees of bank at 230 kt TAS. The same aeroplane with the same bank angle and speed, but at a lower mass will turn with:",
    "feedback": "the same turn radius"
  },
  {
    "question": "What should be usually done to perform a landing with the stabilizer jammed in the cruise flight position ?",
    "feedback": "choose a higher landing speed than normal and/or use a lower flapsetting for landing."
  },
  {
    "question": "When looking at the airflow over the wing, from the wingsurface and up, the air is",
    "feedback": "accelerated to the transition point"
  },
  {
    "question": "When an aeroplane performs a straight steady climb with a 20 % climb gradient, the load factor is equal to:",
    "feedback": "0.98"
  },
  {
    "question": "The location of the centre of pressure of a positively cambered aerofoil at increasing angle of attack will:",
    "feedback": "shift forward until approaching the critical angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aeroplane motion, schematically illustrated in the diagram, is an example of a dynamically:",
    "feedback": "unstable periodic motion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A trim tab is less suitable for jet transport aeroplanes because of their large speed range\n2) A stabiliser trim is a more powerful means of trimming",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Propeller gyroscopic effect occurs during aeroplane pitch changes\n2) Propeller gyroscopic effect is most noticeable during low speed flight at low propeller RPM",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Mean Aerodynamic Chord (MAC) for a given wing of any planform is basically:",
    "feedback": "the chord of an equivalent untwisted, rectangular wing with the same pitching moment and lift characteristics as the actual wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are vortilons used for?",
    "feedback": "Improved low speed handling characteristics"
  },
  {
    "question": "The intensity or strength of the wing tip vortices is ......",
    "feedback": "inversely proportional to the speed of the aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the lift coefficient CL and angle of attack?",
    "feedback": "For a symmetrical aerofoil section, if the angle of attack is zero, CL is zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider an aerofoil section. The relative thickness is the ratio of ......",
    "feedback": "maximum thickness to chord length"
  },
  {
    "question": "What wing shape or wing characteristic is the least sensitive to turbulence :",
    "feedback": "swept wings"
  },
  {
    "question": "If ice is present on the leading edge of the wings, it may increase the landing distance due to higher VAT by as much as:",
    "feedback": "30-40 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "A rotating propeller blade element produces an aerodynamic force F that may be resolved into two components:\n- a force T perpendicular to the plane of rotation (thrust)\n- a force R generating a torque absorbed by engine power\n\nThe diagram representing a rotating propeller blade element during cruise is:",
    "feedback": "diagram 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Behind a normal shock wave, the downwash is greatly reduced. In turn, this causes ......",
    "feedback": "tuck under"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flaps are extended in a straight and level flight at constant IAS, the lift coefficient will eventually :",
    "feedback": "remain the same."
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed line in the manoeuvring load diagram runs through a point where the:",
    "feedback": "speed = VS, load factor = +1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure increases as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity increases as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.7 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2.7, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "n = 3.00"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the radius of a turn, flown at constant IAS is increased, the angle of bank will",
    "feedback": "decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering a positive cambered aerofoil, the pitch moment when Cl=0 is:",
    "feedback": "negative (pitch-down)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Excluding constants, the coefficient of induced drag (CDi) is the ratio of :",
    "feedback": "CL² and AR (aspect ratio)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The density behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it\n2) The local speed of sound behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The the CG moves aft the buffet free range increases\n2) When the Mach number decreases the buffet free range does not change",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A swept wing will for a given angle of attack and wing area:",
    "feedback": "be more laterally stable and produce less lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane in straight and level flight, lowering the flaps (1) ...... wing tip vortices, because the production of lift moves closer to the (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) decreases, (2) root"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct statement with reference to the relationship between VMCL and CG location for a common airplane, such as a A320 or B737:",
    "feedback": "Forward CG decreases VMCL"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the relationship between speed of sound and absolute temperature?",
    "feedback": "Directly proportional to the square root of temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "Low speed pitch up can be caused by a significant thrust:",
    "feedback": "increase with podded engines located beneath a low-mounted wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed for minimum glide angle occurs at an angle of attack that corresponds to: (assume zero thrust)",
    "feedback": "(CL/CD)max"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are planning to take off on runway XX. Field elevation is 52 ft, wing span 20 m. At what height is the downwash least?",
    "feedback": "30 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors determine the distance travelled over the ground of an aeroplane in a glide?",
    "feedback": "The wind and the lift/drag ratio"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of a decreasing aeroplane weight on Mcrit at n=1, when flying at constant IAS ? The value of Mcrit:",
    "feedback": "increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of trailing edge flap named Fowler flap:",
    "feedback": "increases camber and wing area"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the Mach number increases the buffet free range increases\n2) When the load factor decreases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which definition of propeller parameters is correct?",
    "feedback": "Blade angle is the angle between the blade chord line and the propeller vertical plane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding deep stall characteristics, identify whether the following statements are correct or incorrect:\n\n1) A wing with forward sweep and a low horizontal tail makes an aeroplane prone to deep stall\n2) A stick shaker system can be fitted to an aeroplane to resolve deep stall problems",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) During a push-over manoeuvre the buffet free range increases\n2) When the mass increases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the time for a heading change of 45 degrees in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "15 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tuck under can happen:",
    "feedback": "only above the critical Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. The line representing only the effect of the wing contribution to the static stability of an aeroplane is line (1) ..... and its slope will increase as the CG moves (2) ....:",
    "feedback": "(1) Y; (2) aft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of attack of a wing profile is defined as the angle between :",
    "feedback": "The undisturbed airflow and the chordline."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When initiating a steady horizontal turn from steady straight and level flight the buffet free range increases\n2) When mass decreases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The drag due to an ageing airframe is identified as?",
    "feedback": "Parasite Drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the manoeuvre stability of an aeroplane is 50 N/g. The stick force required to achieve a load factor of 4 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is:",
    "feedback": "150 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "When landing an aircraft at an airfield during a hot day, the increased temperature of the runway will ......",
    "feedback": "add to the consequences of entering ground effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about boundary layers is correct?",
    "feedback": "A laminar boundary layer is thinner than a turbulent one"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat\n2) The total pressure in the undisturbed airflow is the same than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The four forces of lift, weight, thrust and drag  in level flight act through:",
    "feedback": "the C of G"
  },
  {
    "question": "The high lift device shown in the figure 1 is a:",
    "feedback": "Krueger flap"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation, which of these statements about the flow around an aerofoil as the angle of attack decreases are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The stagnation point moves up\n2) The point of lowest static pressure moves forward",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure does not change as the streamlines diverge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines diverge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A balance tab is installed to provide:",
    "feedback": "reduced control column movement resistance"
  },
  {
    "question": "A supercritical wing:",
    "feedback": "will develop no noticeable shock waves when flying just above MCRIT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about stick force per g is correct?",
    "feedback": "The stick force per g must have both an upper and lower limit in order to assure acceptable control characteristics."
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is equal to 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "in steady wings level horizontal flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat\n2) The total pressure in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements concerning flight in turbulence is correct?",
    "feedback": "The load factor in turbulence may fluctuate above and below 1, and can even become negative"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane leaving ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL remains constant\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you increase the propeller pitch during a glide with idle-power at constant IAS the lift to drag ratio will",
    "feedback": "increase and the rate of descent will decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "The effective pitch of a propeller is the:",
    "feedback": "actual distance a propeller advances in one revolution"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the propeller pitch of a windmilling propeller is decreased during a glide at constant IAS the propeller drag in the direction of flight will:",
    "feedback": "increase and the rate of descent will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most important problem of ice accretion on an aeroplane during flight is:",
    "feedback": "reduction in CLmax."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming all bodies have the same cross-sectional area and are in motion, place these bodies in order of increasing pressure drag. The correct answer is:",
    "feedback": "3, 4, 1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rolling is the rotation of the aeroplane about the:",
    "feedback": "longitudinal axis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding a positively cambered aerofoil section, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The angle of attack has a negative value when the lift coefficient equals zero\n2) A nose down pitching moment exists when the lift coefficient equals zero",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "By what percentage does VA (EAS) alter when the aeroplane's weight decreases by 19%?",
    "feedback": "10% lower."
  },
  {
    "question": "The most aft CG location may be limited by:  1) insufficient stick force stability 2) insufficient flare capability 3) excessive in-flight manoeuvrability 4) insufficient in-flight manoeuvrability  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The elevator deflection required for a given manoeuvre will be:",
    "feedback": "smaller at high IAS when compared to low IAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the CG position is moved aft, the elevator deflection to achieve a decrease in load factor will be:",
    "feedback": "smaller"
  },
  {
    "question": "The L/D ratio in flight will be at its highest value at:",
    "feedback": "the optimum angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane entering ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL increases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The induced angle of attack is:",
    "feedback": "the angle by which the relative airflow is deflected due to downwash"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the manoeuvre stability of an aeroplane is 150 N/g. The stick force required to achieve a load factor of 2.5 from steady level trimmed flight is:",
    "feedback": "225 N."
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider an aircraft in a glide descent. If trailing-edge flaps are extended, the glide angle will ....",
    "feedback": "become steeper, as the L/D ratio will decrease to a value less than L/D Max."
  },
  {
    "question": "Some aeroplanes have a 'waist' or 'coke bottle' contoured fuselage. This is done to",
    "feedback": "apply area rule."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the gyroscopic effect of a clockwise rotating propeller on a single engine aeroplane?\n\n1) Pitch down produces left yaw\n2) Left yaw produces pitch up",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 300 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value 1.69:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 90 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The purpose of correctly setting the leading and trailing edge devices on the wing of an aeroplane during take-off, approach and landing is to:",
    "feedback": "Reduce stall speed, increase CLMAX with minimum increase in drag for take-off, but with a relatively high drag for approach and landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "When \"spoilers\" are used as speed brakes:",
    "feedback": "at same angle of attack, CD is increased and CL is decreased."
  },
  {
    "question": "During straight and level flight, the pilot starts to extend flaps to the landing configuration. Due to a malfunction, the trailing edge flaps on the right wing remain retracted. If the malfunction goes unnoticed, the possible consequence is;",
    "feedback": "The aircraft will roll to the right and the right wing could stall"
  },
  {
    "question": "The negative manoeuvring limit load factor for a transport aeroplane in the clean configuration at VD may not be less than:",
    "feedback": "zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "The terms \"q\" and \"S\" in the lift formula are:",
    "feedback": "dynamic pressure and the area of the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The torque reaction of a rotating fixed pitch propeller will be greatest at:",
    "feedback": "low aeroplane speed and maximum engine power"
  },
  {
    "question": "A normal, cambered aerofoil accelerates to transonic speeds. The lower shock wave moves aft ......",
    "feedback": "more quickly than the upper shockwave"
  },
  {
    "question": "One advantage of mounting the horizontal tailplane on top of the vertical fin is:",
    "feedback": "to improve the aerodynamic efficiency of the vertical fin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The speed of the airflow in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is possible to have an aileron control aerodynamically balanced by:",
    "feedback": "setting the hinge back into the control surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure does not change as the streamlines diverge\n2) the velocity increases as the streamlines diverge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Located on the underside of a wing's leading edge, Vortilons produce a vortex on the wing's...",
    "feedback": "upper surface, at high angles of attack, to reduce the spanwise flow of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The static temperature behind an oblique shock wave is lower than in front of it\n2) The static pressure behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the devices in the graph will increase the critical angle of attack?",
    "feedback": "Figure 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pitch angle is defined as the angle between the:",
    "feedback": "longitudinal axis and the horizontal plane"
  },
  {
    "question": "A rotating propeller blade element produces an aerodynamic force F that may be resolved into two components:\n- a force T perpendicular to the plane of rotation (thrust)\n- a force R generating a torque absorbed by engine power\n\nThe diagram representing a rotating propeller blade element during reverse operation is:",
    "feedback": "diagram 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the limiting value of 5 degrees bank angle during VMCA determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) As the bank angle is decreased from 5 degrees to 0 degrees, the value of VMCA will remain approximately constant\n1) At any bank angle above 5 degrees, VMCA will decrease correspondingly",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does pressure affect lift?",
    "feedback": "Lift decreases with decreasing pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "The wing area divided by the span of a wing is called:",
    "feedback": "\"Mean cord\""
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure decreases as the streamlines diverge\n2) the velocity increases as the streamlines diverge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) During a push-over manoeuvre the buffet free range increases\n2) When the mass increases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aerofoil with positive camber at a positive angle of attack will have the highest flow velocity:",
    "feedback": "on the upper side"
  },
  {
    "question": "The variation of propeller efficiency of a fixed pitch propeller with TAS at a given RPM is shown in:",
    "feedback": "figure 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main effect of leading-edge slats is to ......",
    "feedback": "delay boundary layer separation and therefore decrease the stalling speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet aeroplane cruises buffet free at high constant altitude in significant turbulence. Which type of stall can occur if this aeroplane decelerates?",
    "feedback": "Accelerated stall."
  },
  {
    "question": "Skin friction drag is caused by the....",
    "feedback": "air's viscosity, producing shear forces within the boundary layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flutter sensitivity of an aeroplane wing is reduced by:",
    "feedback": "locating the engine ahead of the torsional axis of the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane leaving ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle increases\n2) The induced angle of attack decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a steady flow through a stream tube at a given constant velocity. An increase in the flow's temperature will:",
    "feedback": "lower the mass flow."
  },
  {
    "question": "A scheduled flight is heavily delayed due to maintenance. During this time, the Outside Air Temperature OAT increases significantly. What impoact does the temperature change have on VMCG?",
    "feedback": "VMCG decreases, due to the decreasing thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens if a pilot flying an aeroplane with a propeller turning counter-clockwise, when seen from the rear, performs a go-around?",
    "feedback": "Asymmetric thrust is generated, leading to increased yaw to the right"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line in the diagram represents decreasing positive static longitudinal stability at higher angles of attack?",
    "feedback": "Line 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Shock induced separation results in",
    "feedback": "decreasing lift."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following would cause an increase in downwash behind a wing?",
    "feedback": "Stronger wing tip vortices"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the stick force required to achieve a load factor of 2.5 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is 150 N, the value of the manoeuvre stability of that aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "100 N/g"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing spoilers are deflected symetrically in flight in order to:",
    "feedback": "decelerate the aeroplane and/or increase its rate of descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nAt a mass of 140 tons:",
    "feedback": "at FL 400 buffet free flight is possible at M = 0.80 only"
  },
  {
    "question": "(1) ...... the mass of an aircraft will lead to (2) ...... in MCRIT.",
    "feedback": "(1) Increasing, (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will happen in ground effect ?",
    "feedback": "the induced angle of attack and induced drag decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "On an asymmetrical, single curve aerofoil, in subsonic airflow, at low angle of attack, when the angle of attack is increased, the centre of pressure will (assume a conventional transport aeroplane) :",
    "feedback": "move forward."
  },
  {
    "question": "VA is:",
    "feedback": "the maximum speed at which maximum elevator deflection up is allowed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst maintaining straight and level flight with a lift coefficient CL=1, what will be the new value of CL after the speed is increased by 41 %?",
    "feedback": "0.50"
  },
  {
    "question": "On an airfoil the centre of pressure will be most forward:",
    "feedback": "just below the stalling angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a slipping turn (the nose pointing outwards), compared with a co-ordinated turn, the bank angle (i) and the \"ball\" or slip indicator (ii) are respectively:",
    "feedback": "(i) too large, (ii) displaced towards the low wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "While flying under icing conditions, the largest ice build-up will occur, principally, on:",
    "feedback": "the frontal areas of the aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Mcrit is higher than the drag divergence Mach number\n2) Assuming a given angle of attack and for M < 1 the drag coefficient CD increases above the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An increase in geometric dihedral in a steady sideslip condition at constant speed would:",
    "feedback": "increase the required lateral control force"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tuck under is a phenomenon which occur:",
    "feedback": "on a/c in transsonic flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will happen if a large transport aeroplane slowly decelerates in level flight from its cruise speed in still air at high altitude?",
    "feedback": "Stick shaker activation or low speed buffeting"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a trimmable horizontal stabiliser is correct?",
    "feedback": "A trimmed aeroplane with an aft CG requires the stabiliser leading edge to be higher than in the case of a forward CG in the same condition"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transition point is where the boundary layer changes from:",
    "feedback": "laminar into turbulent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ground effect has the following influence on the landing distance :",
    "feedback": "increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet aeroplane is rolled into a turn, while maintaining airspeed and holding altitude. In such a case, the pilot has to:",
    "feedback": "increase thrust and angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The drag divergence Mach number is lower than Mcrit\n2) Below the drag divergence Mach number and for a given angle of attack the drag coefficient CD is practically constant as the Mach number changes",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the pitching moment coefficient Cm versus angle of attack diagram?",
    "feedback": "Line 1 shows an aeroplane with reducing static longitudinal instability at very high angles of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which figure represents the change in the drag vs. true airspeed (TAS) curve with increasing altitude?",
    "feedback": "Figure 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line in the diagram illustrates an aeroplane which is statically longitudinally stable at all angles of attack?",
    "feedback": "Line 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A rotating propeller blade element produces an aerodynamic force F that may be resolved into two components:\n- a force T perpendicular to the plane of rotation (thrust)\n- a force R generating a torque absorbed by engine power\n\nThe diagram representing a windmilling propeller is:",
    "feedback": "diagram 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "When moving the centre of gravity forward the stick force per g will:",
    "feedback": "increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lift and drag on an aerofoil are vertical respectively parallel to the",
    "feedback": "relative wind/airflow."
  },
  {
    "question": "When air has passed through a shock wave the speed of sound is",
    "feedback": "increased."
  },
  {
    "question": "Extending flaps will (1) ...... the wing's effective camber and, consequently, (2) ..... the stall speed",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming subsonic incompressible flow, how will air density change as air flows through a tube of increasing cross-sectional area? The air density:",
    "feedback": "does not vary"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pitching moment versus angle of attack line in the diagram, which corresponds to a CG located at the neutral point of a given aeroplane at low and moderate angles of attack is:",
    "feedback": "line 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure decreases as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why are vortex generators mounted on the upper wing surface?",
    "feedback": "To energise the boundary layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared with an oblique shock wave at the same Mach number a normal shock wave has a",
    "feedback": "higher compression."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about VMCG determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) In order to simulate a wet runway, nose wheel steering may not be used during VMCG determination\n2) During VMCG determination, the CG should be on the aft limit",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When supersonic airflow passes through an oblique shock wave, how do (1) static pressure, (2) density, and (3) local speed of sound change?",
    "feedback": "(1) increases, (2) increases, (3) increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two points are marked on the wing: V1 and V2. Given an air velocity of V, select the correct option.",
    "feedback": "V1 = 0V2 > V"
  },
  {
    "question": "A light twin-engine piston aircraft with clockwise rotating propellers has suffered a failure of the right engine in flight. Which of the following situations would give the worst handling characteristics if the aircraft has to perform a balked landing (go-around) after touchdown?",
    "feedback": "Low weight, crosswind from the right"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Mach trim system will:",
    "feedback": "adjust the stabilizer, depending on the Mach Number."
  },
  {
    "question": "Slat extension:",
    "feedback": "delays the stall to a higher angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect of a high wing with zero dihedral is as follows:",
    "feedback": "Positive dihedral effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed range from approximately M=1.3 to approximately M=5 is called the:",
    "feedback": "supersonic range."
  },
  {
    "question": "The point in the diagram giving the lowest speed in unaccelerated flight is:",
    "feedback": "point 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In twin engine aeroplanes with propellers turning clockwise as seen from behind:",
    "feedback": "the left engine is the critical engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane's sideslip angle is defined as the angle between the:",
    "feedback": "speed vector and the plane of symmetry"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the air is passing through a shock wave the density will",
    "feedback": "increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When trimmed for zero elevator stick force an elevator trim tab causes more drag\n2) An elevator trim tab enables a larger CG range",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The speed of the airflow in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements concerning flight in turbulence is correct?",
    "feedback": "VRA is the recommended turbulence penetration air speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle between the aeroplane longitudinal axis and the chord line is the:",
    "feedback": "angle of incidence."
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a graph showing lift coefficient vs. angle of attack (CL vs. α) for a symmetrical aerofoil. Which of the following is defined by the point which crosses the vertical axis of this graph?",
    "feedback": "Zero lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The speed of the airflow in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane's bank angle is defined as the angle between its:",
    "feedback": "lateral axis and the horizontal plane"
  },
  {
    "question": "The purpose of a dorsal fin is to:",
    "feedback": "maintain static directional stability at large sideslip angles"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decreasing the aspect ratio of a wing:",
    "feedback": "increases induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the air is passing through an expansion wave the local speed of sound will",
    "feedback": "decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "For shallow flight path angles in straight and steady flight, the following formula can be used:",
    "feedback": "sin gamma = T/W - CD/CL"
  },
  {
    "question": "When trailing edge flaps are extended whilst maintaining straight and level flight at constant IAS:",
    "feedback": "the centre of pressure moves aft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in flight has a CL of 0.6, CDI value is 0.1. CL is increased by a factor of 1.5\nThe new value of CDI is:",
    "feedback": "0.225"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft with trailing-edge flaps and leading-edge slats is flying at a speed close to the clean wing stall speed when the flaps are extended to the landing configuration. The slats on the left wing remain retracted. If the speed is decreased, what are the possible consequences?",
    "feedback": "The left (port) wing could stall when the trailing-edge flaps are extended and speed decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the \"CL vs. angle of attack\" graph of a non-symmetrical airfoil with the X axis representing angle of attack, and Y axis representing CL.\nThe angle of attack at which the aerofoil achieves CLMAX  can be found on the graph ........",
    "feedback": "at its highest Y value"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices increases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices is not affected by aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n1) A propeller with a small blade angle is referred to as being in coarse pitch\n2) A propeller with a large blade angle is referred to as being in fine pitch",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deflecting the elevator up, when the trim tab is in neutral, will cause the tab to:",
    "feedback": "remain in line with the elevator"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vortex generators on the upper side of the wing surface will:",
    "feedback": "decrease the intensity of shock wave induced air separation."
  },
  {
    "question": "At the tip of the wing in level flight, the air flows",
    "feedback": "from the lower surface to the upper surface and then down at the trailing edge"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the airflow around a positively cambered aerofoil that is producing lift, the point of minimum static pressure is found ......",
    "feedback": "at the highest speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the gyroscopic effect of a clockwise rotating propeller on a single engine aeroplane?\n\n1) Pitch up produces right yaw\n2) Right yaw produces pitch down",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gyroscopic precession of the propeller is induced by:",
    "feedback": "pitching and yawing."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is fitted with a constant speed propeller. If the aeroplane speed increases while manifold pressure remains constant (1) propeller pitch and (2) propeller torque will:",
    "feedback": "(1) increase (2) remain constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement with respect to the speed of sound is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Varies with the square root of the absolute temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is greater than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "when lift is greater than weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "What moments along the longitudinal axis do these aircraft have if the control laws fail?",
    "feedback": "Underslung = positive, fuselage mounted = negative"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the trailing-edge flaps are extended, the centre of pressure will move (1) ......, producing a pitch (2) ...... moment.",
    "feedback": "(1) aft, (2) down"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the manoeuvre stability of an aeroplane is 150 N/g. The stick force required to achieve a load factor of 4 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is:",
    "feedback": "450 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about weight or mass is correct?",
    "feedback": "The weight of an object depends on the acceleration due to gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at 230 kts with a CL of 0.3. ATC instructs you to reduce the speed to 200 kts. What is the new CL?",
    "feedback": "0.40"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about VMCG determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) VMCG must be determined using rudder control alone\n2) During VMCG determination, the lateral deviation from the runway centreline may be not more than 30 ft",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are means to reduce induced drag?",
    "feedback": "Increasing the aspect ratio and wing twist, adding winglets"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to fly a rate one turn at a higher airspeed, the bank angle must be:",
    "feedback": "increased and the turn radius will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "If an aeroplane is in a steady co-ordinated horizontal turn at a TAS of 200 kt and a turn radius of 2000 m, the load factor (n) will be approximately:",
    "feedback": "1.1"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a steady horizontal turn, the stall speed:",
    "feedback": "increases with the square root of load factor"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do\n1) static pressure\n2) dynamic pressure\n3) total pressure\n4) static temperature\n5) total temperature\n6) velocity\n\nchange in a divergent inlet duct of a turbine engine flying as transonic speed?",
    "feedback": "1, 4 increase, 2, 6 decrease, 3, 5 remain constant."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements concerning propellers is correct?",
    "feedback": "The blade angle of a feathered propeller is approximately 90 degrees"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure decreases as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aerospace company needs to attach a meteo testing device to the outside of the aircraft. How can the least amount of drag be achieved?",
    "feedback": "By fitting an aerodynamic fairing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Line 1 corresponds to aerofoil 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the slope of the lift versus angle of attack curve increases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the wing loading increases, the gust load factor decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no compressibility effects, induced drag at constant IAS is affected by:",
    "feedback": "aeroplane mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does VMCG change with increasing field elevation and temperature ?",
    "feedback": "decreases, because the engine thrust decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed decreases the buffet free range does not change\n2) When the CG moves forward the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming all bodies have the same cross-sectional area and are in motion, which body will have the lowest pressure drag?",
    "feedback": "Body 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are advantages associated with the use of vortex generators?\n1) Increase in maximum CL/CD2) Decrease in form drag3) Delay in the separation of the boundary layer4) Increase in critical angle of attack",
    "feedback": "3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are in the transonic speed range and compressibility comes into effect. Which of the following factors is affected?",
    "feedback": "Density"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift to drag ratio is highest when the flight speed is:",
    "feedback": "Equal to best glide speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.8 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2.8, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "n = 3.00"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a turn is initiated, adverse yaw is:",
    "feedback": "the tendency of an aeroplane to yaw in the opposite direction of turn mainly due to the difference in induced drag on each wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the image. Which graph or combination of graphs represents a negative cambered aerofoil?",
    "feedback": "3 only"
  },
  {
    "question": "When are outboard ailerons (if present) de-activated ?",
    "feedback": "Flaps (and slats) retracted or speed above a certain value."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following flight phenomena can only occur at Mach nhumbers above the critical Mach number?",
    "feedback": "Mach buffet."
  },
  {
    "question": "The vane of a stall warning system with a flapper switch is activated by the change of the:",
    "feedback": "stagnation point."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the purpose of an auto-slat system ?",
    "feedback": "extend automatically when a certain value of angle of attack is exceeded."
  },
  {
    "question": "To perform a co-ordinated turn the aeroplane in diagram 2 should use:",
    "feedback": "more bank angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is in level flight and has a coefficient of lift 0.6 and a coefficient of induced drag 0.1. The aircraft slows down while maintaining level flight. In order to maintain lift at the lower speed, the lift coefficient increases by a factor of 1.5. What is the new coefficient of induced drag if there is no change in configuration?",
    "feedback": "0.225"
  },
  {
    "question": "The unit of density is:",
    "feedback": "kg/m³"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing sweep angle is the angle between:",
    "feedback": "the quarter-chord line of the wing and the lateral axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The speed of the airflow in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The Mach number behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it\n2) The total pressure behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cambered airfoil with zero angle of attack, will in flight produce:",
    "feedback": "some lift and some drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The drag divergence Mach number is equal to Mcrit\n2) Below the drag divergence Mach number and for a given angle of attack the drag coefficient CD increases as the Mach number increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a left turn, the slip indicator is right of neutral. One way to co-ordinate the turn is to apply:",
    "feedback": "less left rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about the effects on drag of removing external tip tanks from the wings of an aeroplane, is correct?\n\n1) Parasite drag decreases\n2) Induced drag decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flutter of control surfaces is:",
    "feedback": "a divergent oscillatory motion of a control surface caused by the interaction of aerodynamic forces, inertia forces and the stiffness of the structure"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of attack of a wing controls the",
    "feedback": "Distribution of positive and negative pressure acting on the wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "At speeds above the critical Mach number, vortex generators fitted to a wing's upper surface will ......",
    "feedback": "retard shock-induced separation"
  },
  {
    "question": "A downward adjustment of a trim tab in the longitudinal control system has the following effect:",
    "feedback": "the stick position stability remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane accelerates from 80 kt to 160 kt at a load factor equal to 1. The induced drag coefficient (i) and the induced drag (ii) alter with the following factors:",
    "feedback": "(i) 1/16 (ii) 1/4"
  },
  {
    "question": "An example of differential aileron deflection during initiation of left turn is:",
    "feedback": "Left aileron: 5° up\nRight aileron: 2° down"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Induced drag decreases as angle of attack increases\n2) At constant load factor, induced drag decreases with increasing aeroplane mass",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst maintaining straight and level flight, extending trailing edge flaps enables an aircraft to fly at (1) ...... indicated air speeds due to a higher (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) lower, (2) CL"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation, which of these statements about the flow around an aerofoil as the angle of attack decreases are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The stagnation point moves up\n2) The point of lowest static pressure moves aft",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared with the clean configuration, the angle of attack at CLMAX with trailing edge flaps extended is:",
    "feedback": "smaller."
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number of a conventional aerofoil section decreases if:",
    "feedback": "its thickness to chord ratio is increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "If S is the frontal area of the propeller disc, propeller solidity is the ratio of:",
    "feedback": "the total frontal area of all the blades to S"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nAt a mass of 140 tons:",
    "feedback": "the buffet free range in a level 30 degree bank turn at FL 360 is from approximately M = 0.74 to M = 0.84"
  },
  {
    "question": "A control surface has its limitations in movement by:",
    "feedback": "primary stops at the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) A stick pusher activates at a lower angle of attack than a stick shaker\n2) A stick pusher prevents the pilot from increasing the angle of attack further",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does VMCL change with increasing density altitude?",
    "feedback": "It decreases due to the decreased engine thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "In level flight, an aircraft has a CL value of 0.35 at a speed of 1.6 VS.\nDetermine the value of CL if speed is reduced to 1.1 VS:",
    "feedback": "0.74"
  },
  {
    "question": "One method to compensate adverse yaw is a",
    "feedback": "differential aileron."
  },
  {
    "question": "When comparing a stabiliser trim system with an elevator trim system, which of these statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "a stabiliser trim is less sensitive to flutter"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about an aeroplane, that has experienced a left engine failure and continues afterwards in straight and level cruise flight with wings level ?",
    "feedback": "turn indicator neutral, slip indicator neutral."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices increases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Speedbrakes are a device used on large transport category aircraft:",
    "feedback": "to increase drag in order to maintain a steeper gradient of descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "The point in the figure corresponding to CL for minimum horizontal flight speed is:",
    "feedback": "point c"
  },
  {
    "question": "With increasing altitude and constant IAS the static lateral stability (1) and the dynamic lateral/directional stability (2) of an aeroplane with swept-back wing will:",
    "feedback": "(1) increase (2) decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nAt a mass of 140 tons:",
    "feedback": "buffet free flight at 1g at FL 410 is not possible"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The static temperature behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it\n2) The static pressure behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming zero thrust, the point on the diagram corresponding to the value for minimum sink rate is:",
    "feedback": "point 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mcrit is the speed at which",
    "feedback": "sonic flow is first achieved above the surface of the airfoil"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the aspect ratio increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct at the speed for minimum drag (subsonic) ?",
    "feedback": "The gliding angle is minimum (assume zero thrust)"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the airspeed reduces in level flight below the speed for maximum L/D, the total drag of an aeroplane will:",
    "feedback": "increase because of increased induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Flying at M = 0.84 provides the optimum margin with respect to buffet onset\n2) The maximum altitude that can be achieved with respect to buffet onset according EASA/CS regulations is higher at M = 0.82 than at M = 0.75",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Examples of aerodynamic balancing of control surfaces are:",
    "feedback": "seal between wing's trailing edge and leading edge of a control surface, horn balance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Before take-off, the pilot decides for an intermediate flap setting due to climb performance. After engine start, a greater flap setting is selected by mistake. Under these circumstances, the rotation speed will be (1) ...... and climb performance will be (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) lower, (2) worse"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the SI unit of measurement for power?",
    "feedback": "Nm/s"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the effect of wing sweep on centre of pressure location are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The centre of pressure on a straight wing moves aft after the angle of attack approaches and exceeds the critical angle of attack\n2) The centre of pressure on a strongly swept back wing moves forward as the angle of attack approaches and exceeds the critical angle of attack",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the requirements for dynamic stability is:",
    "feedback": "positive static stability."
  },
  {
    "question": "To maintain level flight, if the angle of attack is increased, the speed must be:",
    "feedback": "reduced"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effects of the yawing moment caused by an engine failure in a twin-engine aeroplane will be greater when the distance between the operating engine and the CG (thrust arm) is ....",
    "feedback": "greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct when comparing a fixed pitch propeller with a constant speed propeller?\n\n1) A constant speed propeller reduces fuel consumption over a range of cruise speeds\n2) A coarse fixed pitch propeller is more efficient during take-off",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of a flap overspeed, a flap load relief system will ......",
    "feedback": "retract the trailing edge flaps to an intermediate position, to protect the flaps"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a fixed-pitch propeller in flight at a given TAS, the blade angle of attack will:",
    "feedback": "increase if RPM increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The result of spoiler surfaces deploying are:",
    "feedback": "drag increases and lift decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The total pressure in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bernoulli's equation can be written as:\n(pt= total pressure, ps = static pressure and q=dynamic pressure)",
    "feedback": "pt = ps + q"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which situation would the wing lift of an aeroplane in straight and level flight have the highest value ? (The engines are mounted below the wing)",
    "feedback": "Forward centre of gravity and idle thrust."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a descent below the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "lift coefficient decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram shows a right turn, where there is not enough bank for a co-ordinated turn?",
    "feedback": "6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure does not change as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity decreases as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "From a polar curve of the entire aeroplane one can read:",
    "feedback": "the maximum CL/CD ratio and maximum lift coefficient"
  },
  {
    "question": "When is a turn co-ordinated?",
    "feedback": "When the longitudinal axis of the aeroplane at the CG is tangential to the flight path"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effects of very heavy rain (tropical rain) on the aerodynamic characteristics of an aeroplane are:",
    "feedback": "decrease of CLMAX and increase of drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the components of wave drag?",
    "feedback": "Energy drag and boundary layer separation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The four forces acting on an aeroplane in level flight are:",
    "feedback": "thrust, lift drag and weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effects of very heavy rain (tropical rain) on the aerodynamic characteristics of an aeroplane are:",
    "feedback": "decrease of CLmax and increase of drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "Shock stall:",
    "feedback": "occurs when the lift coefficient, as a function of Mach number, reaches its maximum value"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure does not change as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the transonic region, the coefficient of drag:",
    "feedback": "Varies, depending on Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the trailing edge flaps are stuck in the position shown in the picture, the pilot would have to....",
    "feedback": "trim ailerons to lower the right wing down and apply rudder to put the nose to the left"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the Mach number increases the buffet free range does not change\n2) When the load factor decreases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared with level flight, the angle of attack must be increased in a steady, co-ordinated, horizontal turn:",
    "feedback": "to compensate for the reduction in the vertical component of lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 10\nThrust per engine: 60000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a twin engine aeroplane, the all-engines climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "14 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following will reduce induced drag?",
    "feedback": "Elliptical lift distribution."
  },
  {
    "question": "Drag is in the direction of - and lift is perpendicular to the:",
    "feedback": "relative wind/airflow."
  },
  {
    "question": "How will each aircraft react during a go around?",
    "feedback": "A is more likely to over rotate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "Flap extension causes a reduction in stall speed and the maximum glide distance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aspect ratio of the wing:",
    "feedback": "is the ratio between the wing span and the mean geometric chord."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about stall speed is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Increasing sweepback increases stall speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "The CG of an aeroplane is in a fixed position forward of the neutral point. Which of these statements about the stick force stability is correct?",
    "feedback": "An increase of 10 kt from the trimmed position at high speed has less effect on the stick force than an increase of 10 kt from the trimmed position at low speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "The manoeuvrability of an aeroplane is best when the:",
    "feedback": "C.G. is on the aft C.G. limit."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Mcrit is lower than the drag divergence Mach number\n2) Assuming a given angle of attack and for M < 1 the drag coefficient CD decreases above the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n1) A propeller with little blade twist is referred to as being in fine pitch\n2) A propeller with a large blade angle is referred to as being in coarse pitch",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When altitude increases, the stall speed (IAS) will:",
    "feedback": "increase due to increasing compressibility effects as a result of increasing Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.5 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "44%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stagnation point is the point:",
    "feedback": "where the velocity of the relative airflow is reduced to zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which kind of ''tab'' is commonly used in case of manual reversion of fully powered flight controls ?",
    "feedback": "Servo tab"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding a symmetric aerofoil section, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The angle of attack is zero when the lift coefficient equals zero\n2) The pitching moment is zero when the lift coefficient equals zero",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of attack of an aerofoil section is defined as the angle between the:",
    "feedback": "undisturbed airflow and the chord line"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rudder controls:",
    "feedback": "Yaw."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying close to thunderstorms and you don't want to stall the aircraft or experience Mach buffet. Select the correct statements from the list:\n1) Descend to a lower altitude2) Increase the Mach number3) Climb above the thunderstorms4) Avoid cells by using weather radar",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A large turbojet aeroplane is being flown at its optimum altitude and the crew try to achieve the most efficient flight performance. If the speed were to be increased slightly above the Critical Mach number, the coefficient of lift would (1) ...... , requiring (2) ...... of the angle of attack.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dotted line in the figure represents how a lift curve changes when a high-lift device is deployed. To which of these devices could the curve apply to?\n1) Krueger Flap2) Fowler Flap3) Slats and slots",
    "feedback": "1) and 3)"
  },
  {
    "question": "While being in straight and level flight, maintaining a constant IAS, one engine of a twin-engine propeller aircraft suddenly becomes inoperative. If density decreases, thrust will (1) .... and the yawing moment will (2) .... .",
    "feedback": "(1) decrease; (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the air is passing through a shock wave the static temperature will",
    "feedback": "increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which ratio is defined as the \"aspect ratio\" of a wing?",
    "feedback": "ratio between span and mean chord"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The dynamic pressure in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The total pressure in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flat plate, when positioned in the airflow at a small angle of attack, will produce:",
    "feedback": "both lift and drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of an aeroplane provides the greatest positive contribution to the static longitudinal stability ?",
    "feedback": "The horizontal tailplane."
  },
  {
    "question": "The use of a slot in the leading edge of the wing enables the aeroplane to fly at a slower speed because :",
    "feedback": "it delays the stall to a higher angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "In comparison to a conventional aerofoil section, typical shape characteristics of a supercritical aerofoil section are:",
    "feedback": "a larger nose radius, flatter upper surface and negative as well as positive camber"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the total sum of moments about one of its axis is not zero, an aeroplane would:",
    "feedback": "experience an angular acceleration about that axis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about a constant speed propeller is correct?",
    "feedback": "The blade angle increases with increasing speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "The highest value of the CL/CD ratio of an aeroplane is obtained:",
    "feedback": "in the clean configuration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Just above the critical Mach number the first evidence of a shock wave will appear at the",
    "feedback": "upper side of the wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "Air passes a normal shock wave. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "The static temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a constant load factor, which of these statements about the variation of induced drag with changes of speed and mass are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed increases, induced drag decreases\n2) When mass increases, induced drag increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect on the aeroplane's static longitudinal stability of a shift of the centre of gravity to a more aft location and on the required control deflection for a certain pitch up or down?",
    "feedback": "The static longitudinal stability is smaller and the required control deflection is smaller."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane entering ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL remains constant\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two identical aeroplanes A and B, with the same mass, are flying steady level co-ordinated 20 degree bank turns. If the TAS of A is 130 kt and the TAS of B is 200 kt:",
    "feedback": "the rate of turn of A is greater than that of B"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a wing's angle of attack increases, the pressure differential (1) ......, leading to a/an (2) ...... in the intensity of the wing tip vortices.",
    "feedback": "(1) increases, (2) increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which relationship is correct when comparing drag and airspeed?",
    "feedback": "If you double the airspeed the induced drag is reduced to 1/4."
  },
  {
    "question": "The extreme right limitation for both V-n (gust and manoeuvre) diagrams is created by the speed:",
    "feedback": "VD"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is stall warning presented to the pilots of a large transport aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "Stick shaker and/or aerodynamic buffet"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a high speed descent at MMO  you will reach VMO at:",
    "feedback": "FL270"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a straight steady descent, which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Lift is less than weight, load factor is less than 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect does a vortilon attached to the underside of the leading edge of a wing have?",
    "feedback": "Stops spanwise flow at high angles of attack over the upper surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will the extension of the leading-edge flaps result in?",
    "feedback": "A greater reduction of the stalling speed, compared to the reduction achieved by the extension of the trailing-edge flaps"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the heading change of an aeroplane after 15 seconds in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "45 degrees"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Mach number is the ratio between:",
    "feedback": "TAS of the aeroplane and the speed of sound of the undisturbed flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning control is correct?",
    "feedback": "In a differential aileron control system the control surfaces have a larger upward than downward maximum deflection."
  },
  {
    "question": "Rotation around the lateral axis is called :",
    "feedback": "pitching"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following systems suppresses the tendency to \"Dutch roll\"?",
    "feedback": "Yaw damper."
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens during an engine failure with two similar aeroplanes with wing mounted engines, one of them with jet engines, the other one with co-rotating propellers?",
    "feedback": "More roll tendency for the propeller aeroplane."
  },
  {
    "question": "The additional increase of drag at Mach Numbers above the critical Mach Number is due to:",
    "feedback": "wave drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation, when speed is decreased in straight and level flight on a positively cambered aerofoil, what happens to the:\n\n1) centre of pressure and\n2) the magnitude of the total lift force?",
    "feedback": "1) moves forward and 2) remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a given CG position, the aeroplane has an MCRIT of Mach 0.82. With an aft movement of the CG, the MCRIT would (1) ...... , as the local air velocity on the top surface of the wing would (2) ...... , due to the (3) ...... angle of attack required to maintain level flight.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) decrease, (3) decreased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming all bodies have the same cross-sectional area and are in motion, which body will have the highest pressure drag?",
    "feedback": "Body 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is greater than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "during recovery after a wings level stall"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of exceeding Mcrit on the stick force stability of an aeroplane with swept-back wings without any form of stability augmentation?",
    "feedback": "A decrease, due to loss of lift in the wing root area"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most important factor determining the required position of the Trimmable Horizontal Stabiliser (THS) for take off is the:",
    "feedback": "position of the aeroplane's centre of gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift coefficient (CL) of an aeroplane in steady horizontal flight is 0.4. Increase of angle of attack of 1 degree will increase CL by 0.09. A vertical up gust instantly changes the angle of attack by 5 degrees. The load factor will be :",
    "feedback": "2.13"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about wing sweepback are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Increasing wing sweepback decreases Mcrit\n2) Increasing wing sweepback increases the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens to a wing's critical angle of attack when it enters ground effect?",
    "feedback": "Decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "In level flight, an aircraft has a CL value of 1.22 at a speed of 1.1 VS.\nDetermine the value of CL at a speed of 1.8 VS:",
    "feedback": "0.45"
  },
  {
    "question": "When compared to a clean configuration, the wing in the figure has a:",
    "feedback": "lower CL-CD ratio"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the wing profile(s) that matches the graph:",
    "feedback": "Profile 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about the effects on drag of fitting external tip tanks to the wings of an aeroplane, is correct?\n\n1) Parasite drag increases\n2) Induced drag decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What changes in aircraft control must be made to maintain altitude while the airspeed is being decreased?",
    "feedback": "Increase the angle of attack to compensate for the decreasing lift."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is fitted with an external piece of scientific equipment. Which of the following factors will minimise the increase in form (pressure) drag?",
    "feedback": "An aerodynamically-shaped fairing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed increases the buffet free range decreases\n2) When altitude decreases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Floating due to ground effect during an approach to land will occur :",
    "feedback": "when the height is less than halve of the length of the wing span above the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "An increase in angle of attack (below the stalling angle of attack) increases lift because",
    "feedback": "the lift coefficient increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a straight steady descent, lift is:",
    "feedback": "less than weight, because lift only needs to balance the weight component perpendicular to the flight path"
  },
  {
    "question": "The high speed buffet is induced by",
    "feedback": "boundary layer separation due to shock waves."
  },
  {
    "question": "The tab in the figure represents:",
    "feedback": "a balance tab that also functions as a trim tab"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about Bernoulli's equation is correct?",
    "feedback": "Dynamic pressure is zero when the flow velocity is zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the gyroscopic effect of a clockwise rotating propeller on a single engine aeroplane?\n\n1) Pitch down produces right yaw\n2) Left yaw produces pitch up",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "During take-off, the right slat does not extend. What might happen on rotation?",
    "feedback": "The right wing will stall on rotation"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a slipping turn (nose pointing outwards), compared with a co-ordinated turn, the bank angle (i) and the \"ball\" or slip indicator (ii) are respectively:",
    "feedback": "(i) too large; (ii) displaced towards the low wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The negative manoeuvring limit load factor for a light aeroplane in the aerobatic category in the clean configuration may not be less than:",
    "feedback": "-3.0"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of failure of the Mach trimmer:",
    "feedback": "the Mach number must be limited"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane leaving ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL increases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of the slot between an extended slat and the leading edge of the wing is to:",
    "feedback": "cause a venturi effect which energizes the boundary layer."
  },
  {
    "question": "In a skidding turn (the nose pointing inwards), compared with a co-ordinated turn, the bank angle (i) and the \"ball\" or slip indicator (ii) are respectively:",
    "feedback": "(i) too small, (ii) displaced towards the high wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the air is passing through an expansion wave the Mach number will",
    "feedback": "increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "A propeller is turning to the right, seen from behind. The asymmetric thrust effect is mainly induced by:",
    "feedback": "high angles of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number of a conventional aerofoil section decreases if:",
    "feedback": "its camber is increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The Mach number behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it\n2) The total pressure behind an oblique shock wave is lower than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat\n2) The speed in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "VMO :",
    "feedback": "should be not greater than VC."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The drag divergence Mach number is lower than Mcrit\n2) Below the drag divergence Mach number and for a given angle of attack the drag coefficient CD decreases as the Mach number decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "During which type of stall does the angle of attack have the smallest value?",
    "feedback": "shock stall."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly decreases the speed by 20 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "decrease to 0.81"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to maintain constant speed during a level, co-ordinated turn, compared with straight and level flight, the pilot must:",
    "feedback": "increase thrust/power and angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the wing's centre of pressure move with increasing angle of attack?",
    "feedback": "Forward."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect on an aeroplane's characteristics of extending Fowler flaps to their fully extended position?",
    "feedback": "wing area and camber increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n1) A propeller with a small blade angle is referred to as being in fine pitch\n2) A propeller with a large blade angle is referred to as being in coarse pitch",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The local speed of sound in front of an oblique shock wave is higher than behind it\n2) The Mach number in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Slat extension will:",
    "feedback": "increase critical angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a go-around at an airport with a temperature of negative 15°C, a light twin-engine aircraft with normally aspirated piston engines experiences an engine failure. How will the environment described affect VMCA?",
    "feedback": "High engine performance on the operating engine due to high air density will increase VMCA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The static temperature in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it\n2) The static pressure in front of an oblique shock wave is higher than behind it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding a positively cambered aerofoil section, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The angle of attack has a positive value when the lift coefficient equals zero\n2) A nose down pitching moment exists when the lift coefficient equals zero",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What should the pilot do to prevent uncontrollable yaw in a twin-engine aircraft if one engine fails and the speed is below VMC?",
    "feedback": "Retard the throttle on the operating engine until directional control can be maintained"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the limit load factor of a large transport aeroplane in the manoeuvring diagram?",
    "feedback": "2.5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the wing area increases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the EAS increases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the mass decreases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the altitude increases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stalling speed in IAS will change according to the following factors:",
    "feedback": "May increase with altitude, especially high altitude, will increase during icing conditions and will increase when the c.g. moves forward"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider two aircraft, the only difference between the two is that one has larger winglets than the other. Regarding the aircraft with the larger winglets, ground effect is expected to ......",
    "feedback": "decrease because the winglets reduce overall wing tip vortices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pitch is movement around the",
    "feedback": "lateral axis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane leaving ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle decreases\n2) The induced angle of attack increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is in a steady horizontal turn at a TAS of 194.4 kt. The turn radius is 1000 m. The bank angle is: (assume g = 10m/s2)",
    "feedback": "45°"
  },
  {
    "question": "What decreases the maximum ground distance during a glide with zero thrust?",
    "feedback": "A headwind with constant aeroplane mass compared with zero wind."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of aeroplane mass on shock wave intensity at constant Mach number?",
    "feedback": "Increasing mass increases shock wave intensity"
  },
  {
    "question": "In high speed flight, as an aeroplane exceeds the Drag Divergence Mach number, it becomes (1) ...... stable with respect to speed, because of the (2) ...... movement of the centre of pressure.",
    "feedback": "(1) less, (2) rearward"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors determines the maximum flight altitude in the \"Buffet Onset Boundary\" graph?",
    "feedback": "Aerodynamics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which has the effect of increasing load factor ? (all other relevant factors being constant)",
    "feedback": "Vertical gusts"
  },
  {
    "question": "A turboprop aeroplane has suffered an engine failure. The use of bank angle towards the live engine to tilt the lift vector ....",
    "feedback": "balances the rudder side force, creating a sideways component opposite to the rudder force"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the equilibrium of forces and moments at VMCA are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Because VMCA must be determined for the case where the critical engine suddenly fails, there is no need to obtain equilibrium of moments about the normal axis\n2) Equilibrium of forces along the lateral axis does not require any side slip during a wings level condition",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The graph represents a wing in two configurations: the black line in clean configuration and the blue line with a lift augmentation device extended. What type of profile does the basic wing have and what type of lift augmentation device is used?",
    "feedback": "Symmetrical wing with flaps extended"
  },
  {
    "question": "The diagram representing a feathered propeller is:",
    "feedback": "diagram 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. X, Y and Z correspond to:",
    "feedback": "Angle of Attack, climb angle, pitch angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is greater than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "during a steady co-ordinated horizontal turn"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the purpose of vortex generators?",
    "feedback": "To increase the kinetic energy of the boundary layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The regime of flight from the critical Mach number up to M = 1.3 is called the",
    "feedback": "transonic range."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a phugoid, the speed:",
    "feedback": "varies significantly, whereas during a short period oscillation it remains approximately constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flaps are retracted whilst maintaining straight and level flight at constant IAS, the lift coefficient will:",
    "feedback": "eventually remain the same"
  },
  {
    "question": "A body is placed in a certain airstream. The density of the airstream decreases to half of the original value. The aerodynamic drag will decrease with a factor :",
    "feedback": "2 ."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack increases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the aspect ratio increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The blade angle of a propeller is usually referenced at:",
    "feedback": "75 % of blade radius"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly increases the speed by 20 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "increase to 1.21"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The drag divergence Mach number is equal to Mcrit\n2) Below the drag divergence Mach number and for a given angle of attack the drag coefficient CD is practically constant as the Mach number changes",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following flight phenomena can happen at Mach Numbers below the critical Mach Number?",
    "feedback": "Dutch roll."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The the CG moves aft the buffet free range increases\n2) When the Mach number decreases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What changes in angle of attack must be made to maintain altitude while the airspeed is being increased?",
    "feedback": "Decrease the angle of attack to compensate for the increasing lift."
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle between the chord line of the wing and the longitudinal axis of the airplane is known as the angle of",
    "feedback": "incidence"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a normal spin recovery:",
    "feedback": "the ailerons are held in the neutral position."
  },
  {
    "question": "A typical fixed pitch propeller (C-172) is designed to achieve its optimum angle of attack at:",
    "feedback": "cruise speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what speed does the front of a shock wave move across the earth's surface?",
    "feedback": "The ground speed of the aeroplane."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane entering ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle increases\n2) The induced angle of attack increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is taking off from an aerodrome where the take-off performance is limited by the runway length. Given the following information at which of the following heights will the value for induced drag (Cdi) be lowest?\nWing span: 20 mAerodrome elevation: 52 ft\nConsider no changes in pitch attitude, speed, or wing configuration",
    "feedback": "30 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure increases as the streamlines diverge\n2) the velocity decreases as the streamlines diverge",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Propeller efficiency is defined as the ratio between:",
    "feedback": "usable (power available) power of the propeller and shaft power."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the mass increases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the altitude decreases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does the pitch-angle of a constant-speed propeller alter in medium horizontal turbulence?",
    "feedback": "Yes slightly."
  },
  {
    "question": "With increasing angle of attack, the stagnation point will move (I) ...and the point of lowest pressure will move (II) ...Respectively (I) and (II) are:",
    "feedback": "(I) down, (II) forward."
  },
  {
    "question": "A dual-channel Mach trim failure is experienced in flight. Select the correct option from the answers below:",
    "feedback": "The aircraft can be flown at a specified lower Mach speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider an aerofoil with a certain camber and a positive angle of attack. At which location will the highest flow velocities occur ?",
    "feedback": "Upper side"
  },
  {
    "question": "An example of a combined lateral and directional aperiodic motion is a:",
    "feedback": "spiral dive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given an aeroplane in steady, straight and level flight at low speed and considering the effects of CG location and thrust, the lowest value of wing lift occurs at:",
    "feedback": "aft CG and take-off thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "Limiting factors in severe turbulence are the possibility of a stall and the margin to the structural limitations"
  },
  {
    "question": "The asymmetric blade effect on a single engine aeroplane with a clockwise rotating propeller:",
    "feedback": "produces left yaw"
  },
  {
    "question": "Some aeroplanes have a local reduction in fuselage cross-section (waistline or \"coke bottle\" shape). \nThis is to:",
    "feedback": "reduce wave drag through application of the area rule"
  },
  {
    "question": "The positive manoeuvring limit load factor for a large jet transport aeroplane with flaps extended is:",
    "feedback": "2.0"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?\nI When the critical engine fails during take-off the speed VMCL can be limiting.\nII The speed VMCL is always limited by maximum rudder deflection.",
    "feedback": "I is incorrect, II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What increases the maximum ground distance during a glide with zero thrust?",
    "feedback": "A tailwind with constant aeroplane mass compared with zero wind."
  },
  {
    "question": "Bernoulli's theorem states that in a perfect and constant airstream:",
    "feedback": "The sum of static and dynamic pressure is constant."
  },
  {
    "question": "The sonic boom of an aeroplane flying at supersonic speed is created by:",
    "feedback": "shock waves around the aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "When speed is increased in straight and level flight on a positively cambered aerofoil, what happens to the:\n\n1) centre of pressure and\n2) the magnitude of the total lift force?",
    "feedback": "1) moves aft and 2) remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight is subjected to a strong vertical gust. The point on the wing, where the instantaneous variation in wing lift effectively acts is known as the:",
    "feedback": "aerodynamic centre of the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can the designer of an aeroplane with straight wings increase the static lateral stability?",
    "feedback": "By increasing the aspect ratio of the vertical stabiliser, whilst maintaining a constant area"
  },
  {
    "question": "Extension of FOWLER type trailing edge lift augmentation devices, will produce:",
    "feedback": "a nose-down pitching moment."
  },
  {
    "question": "Static lateral stability should not be too small because:",
    "feedback": "the aeroplane would show too strong a tendency to spiral dive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which aircraft design would be the most sensitive to changes in airflow patterns when entering ground effect?",
    "feedback": "A low-wing aircraft with a low-mounted tailplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices increases as the angle of attack increases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices is not affected by aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the aspect ratio of a wing increases whilst all other relevant factors remain constant, the critical angle of attack will:",
    "feedback": "decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the nose of an aeroplane yaws left, this causes:",
    "feedback": "a roll to port (left)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming that the RPM remains constant throughout, the angle of attack of a fixed pitch propeller will:",
    "feedback": "decrease with increasing airspeed"
  },
  {
    "question": "When deploying speedbrakes, you can expect the minimum drag to (1) ...... and the minimum drag speed to (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "The consequences of exceeding Mcrit in a swept-wing aeroplane may be : (assume no corrective devices, straight and level flight)",
    "feedback": "buffeting of the aeroplane and a tendency to pitch down."
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the airfoil profile(s) that matches the corresponding CL graph, i.e. which augmentation increases your CL while your angle of attack remains the same?",
    "feedback": "1 & 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Parasite drag can be divided into:\n1) Tip-vortex drag2) Interference drag3) Pressure drag4) Friction drag\nThe combination regrouping all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift coefficient CL versus angle of attack curve of a positive cambered aerofoil section intersects the vertical axis of the graph:",
    "feedback": "above the origin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift formula can be written as:\n(rho = density)",
    "feedback": "L= CL 1/2 RHO V² S"
  },
  {
    "question": "After reaching its cruising altitude, an aircraft accelerates to a speed where compressibility in the airflow becomes aerodynamically significant. The term \"compressibility\" means that there are changes in the ...... of the free stream airflow.",
    "feedback": "density"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nA jet transport aeroplane with a mass of 90 tons carries out a manoeuvre with a load factor of 1.6 at FL 380. The buffet free speed range extends approximately from:",
    "feedback": "M = 0.74 to M = 0.84"
  },
  {
    "question": "While performing the \"After Engine Start\" procedures, the pilots of a commercial jet aircraft forget to set the slats/flaps to the calculated take-off position. What could be a consequence of this action?",
    "feedback": "After rotation, the aircraft will stall after getting airborne"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure below.\n\nThe correct sequence of cross-sections representing propeller blade twist is:",
    "feedback": "sequence 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the stick force required to achieve a load factor of 3 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is 360 N, the value of the manoeuvre stability of that aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "180 N/g"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the propeller pitch of a windmilling propeller is increased during a glide at constant IAS the propeller drag in the direction of flight will:",
    "feedback": "decrease and the rate of descent will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing loading is the ratio between:",
    "feedback": "aeroplane weight and wing area"
  },
  {
    "question": "The negative manoeuvring limit load factor for a transport aeroplane in the clean configuration up to VC may not be less than:",
    "feedback": "-1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about weight or mass is correct?",
    "feedback": "Weight is a force"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is less than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "during a push-over manoeuvre"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure\nWhich of the following statements is/are correct or incorrect?\n1) There is a higher margin for buffet onset at Mach 0.74 than at 0.812) According to specific operational requirements regarding buffet onset, you can fly at a higher maximum altitude with a higher Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is maintaining straight and level flight at the stalling speed.\nIf the pilot now reduces the angle of attack and accelerates, the total drag will initially:",
    "feedback": "Decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?\nI When the critical engine fails during take-off the speed VMCL can be limiting.\nII The speed VMCL can be limited by the available maximum roll rate",
    "feedback": "I is incorrect, II is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An engine failure can result in a windmilling (1) propeller and a feathered (2) propeller. \n\nWhich statement about propeller drag is correct?",
    "feedback": "(1) is larger than (2)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the effect of wing sweep on centre of pressure location are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The centre of pressure on an unswept wing moves forward as the angle of attack approaches and exceeds the critical angle of attack\n2) When sweep back increases the centre of pressure has an increased tendency to move forward as the angle of attack approaches and exceeds the critical angle of attack",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the limiting value of 5 degrees bank angle during VMCA determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) As the bank angle is decreased from 5 degrees to 0 degrees, the value of VMCA increases\n2) At any bank angle beyond 5 degrees, VMCA will decrease correspondingly",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The force vector which correctly represents thrust force is:",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what way do (1) induced drag and (2) parasite drag alter with increasing speed?",
    "feedback": "(1) decreases and (2) increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "One important advantage a turbulent boundary layer has over a laminar layer is that the turbulent boundary layer:",
    "feedback": "has less tendency to separate from the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "By lowering the trailing edge flaps ......",
    "feedback": "wing tip vortex decrease due to CP closer to the wing root"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most common stall sensing devices are normally located:",
    "feedback": "at or near the wing leading edge"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nDetermine the maximum altitude with respect to buffet onset according EASA/CS regulations for a mass of 120 tons:",
    "feedback": "FL 380 at M = 0.80"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transonic speed is:",
    "feedback": "a speed at which locally around the aeroplane both supersonic and subsonic speeds exist"
  },
  {
    "question": "To perform a co-ordinated turn the aeroplane in diagram 3 should use:",
    "feedback": "less right rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly decreases the speed by 10 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "decrease to 0.90"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement regarding the gust load factor on an aeroplane is correct (all other factors of importance being constant) ?\n\n1.  Increasing the aspect-ratio of the wing will increase the gust load factor.\n\n2.  Increasing the speed will increase the gust load factor.",
    "feedback": "1 and 2 are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "The flow on the upper surface of the wing has a component in wing root direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Propeller gyroscopic effect occurs during aeroplane yaw changes\n2) Propeller gyroscopic effect is most noticeable during low speed flight at high propeller RPM",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements is true with regard to the operation of a Mach trim system?",
    "feedback": "It only operates above a pre-determined Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "Icing on the wing can lead to the absence of a stall warning by:",
    "feedback": "decreasing the critical angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Upon wing spoiler extension in straight and level flight, if the speed and load factor remain constant:",
    "feedback": "CD increases but CL remains unaffected"
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A stabiliser trim is more suitable to cope with the large trim changes generated by the high lift devices on most jet transport aeroplanes\n2) A trim tab runaway causes less control difficulty",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The reference stall speed is represented by the following:",
    "feedback": "VSR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where on the curve in the diagram does the aeroplane exhibit static longitudinal instability?",
    "feedback": "Part 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When altitude increases the buffet free range increases\n2) When load factor increases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The boundary layer of a wing is:",
    "feedback": "a layer on the wing in which the stream velocity is lower than the free stream velocity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about negative tail stall is correct?",
    "feedback": "When negative tail stall occurs, the aeroplane will show an uncontrollable pitch-down moment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following creates induced drag on a wing?",
    "feedback": "Angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "The propeller blade angle of attack on a fixed pitch propeller is increased when :",
    "feedback": "RPM increases and forward velocity decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "When considering the design certification requirements for certification of an aircraft, which has leading edge slats that are not mechanically interlinked, what flying qualities must it display?",
    "feedback": "Handling must be acceptable at all stages of flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "The figure illustrates an aeroplane suffering an engine failure, while flying at the normal cruising speed. After handling the failure appropriately, the pilot prepares the aeroplane for landing. Wings level is maintained as the aeroplane is slowing down; as the airspeed decreases, larger variations of rudder input are required to maintain direction, while thrust remains constant. One reason for this is because the ....",
    "feedback": "amount of sideslip increases as speed decreases, airflow affects the vertical stabilizer at a greater angle, thus, reducing the rudder's effectiveness"
  },
  {
    "question": "An increase in wing loading will:",
    "feedback": "increase the stall speeds."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which device could you use to change from curve 1 to curve 2?",
    "feedback": "Speed brakes"
  },
  {
    "question": "When comparing a rectangular wing and a swept back wing of the same wing area and wing loading, the swept back wing has the advantage of :",
    "feedback": "Higher critical Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the letter which correctly represents the Angle of Attack in the diagram:",
    "feedback": "B"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lift is generated when:",
    "feedback": "a certain mass of air is accelerated downwards."
  },
  {
    "question": "With increasing altitude flying at a constant IAS will result in:",
    "feedback": "no change in the stalling angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "That portion of the aircraft's total drag created by the production of lift is called:",
    "feedback": "Induced drag, and is greatly affected by changes in airspeed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements on shock stall is correct?",
    "feedback": "Shock stall is a stall due to flow separation caused by a shock wave"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct statement:",
    "feedback": "Aerofoil 3 corresponds to line 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What would happen to an aircraft's rate of descent and the angle of descent when deploying the speed brakes in flight?",
    "feedback": "Both the rate of descent and the descent angle will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "The unit of measurement of pressure is:",
    "feedback": "psi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Taper ratio is:",
    "feedback": "equal to 1 or less than 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Induced drag is the result of:",
    "feedback": "downwash generated by tip vortices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding a propeller?\n\n1) Increasing tip speed to supersonic speed increases propeller noise\n2) Increasing tip speed to supersonic speed decreases propeller efficiency",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane entering ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL increases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi remains constant",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a load factor of 1 and the aeroplane's minimum drag speed, what is the ratio between induced drag Di and parasite drag Dp?",
    "feedback": "Di/Dp = 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the wing area decreases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the EAS decreases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a steady horizontal, co-ordinated turn with 45 degrees of bank at 230 kt TAS. The same aeroplane with the same bank angle and speed, but at a higher mass will turn with:",
    "feedback": "the same turn radius, but might stall"
  },
  {
    "question": "Increasing air density will have the following effect on the drag of a body in an airstream (angle of attack and TAS are constant):",
    "feedback": "the drag increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed increases the buffet free range does not change\n2) When altitude decreases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a trailing edge flap is lowered during flight from take-off position to fully down position, one will experience",
    "feedback": "a small increase in lift and a large increase in drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "What needs to be considered when descending at MMO/VMO?",
    "feedback": "Aerodynamic limitations at high altitude and structural limitations at low altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number of a conventional aerofoil section decreases if:",
    "feedback": "it is flown at higher angles of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "At an aircraft weight of 80.000 lbs in 1 G level flight at FL350, your low speed buffet boundary will be:",
    "feedback": "222 kts"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 200 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value of 1.69:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 60 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The positive manoeuvring limit load factor for a light aeroplane in the aerobatic category in the clean configuration may not be less than:",
    "feedback": "6.0"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no pilot input the motion of the aeroplane in the diagram shows:",
    "feedback": "neutral dynamic longitudinal stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aileron flutter can be caused by:",
    "feedback": "cyclic deformations generated by aerodynamic, inertial and elastic loads on the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The density in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it\n2) The total pressure in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "From an initial condition of level flight the flaps are retracted at a constant pitch attitude. The aeroplane will subsequently:",
    "feedback": "start to sink"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the manoeuvre stability of an aeroplane is 100 N/g. The stick force required to achieve a load factor of 2.5 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is:",
    "feedback": "150 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct when comparing a fixed pitch propeller with a constant speed propeller?\n\n1) A constant speed propeller reduces fuel consumption over a range of cruise speeds\n2) A constant speed propeller improves take-off performance as compared with a coarse fixed pitch propeller",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure below.\n\nThe correct sequence of cross-sections representing propeller blade twist is:",
    "feedback": "sequence 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.8 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "31%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which moments or motions interact in a dutch roll?",
    "feedback": "Rolling and yawing."
  },
  {
    "question": "The greatest drag produced by the variable pitch propeller on a piston engine will occur when the propeller is:",
    "feedback": "windmilling"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 100 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value of 1.21:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 10 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift coefficient (CL) of an aeroplane in steady horizontal flight is 0.42, increase in angle of attack of 1 degree increases CL by is 0.1. A vertical up gust instantly changes the angle of attack by 3 degrees. The load factor will be :",
    "feedback": "1.71"
  },
  {
    "question": "An example of a combined lateral and directional periodic motion is a:",
    "feedback": "Dutch roll"
  },
  {
    "question": "The reference section of a propeller blade with radius R is usually taken at a distance from the propeller axis equal to:",
    "feedback": "0.75 R"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a steady co-ordinated horizontal turn, lift is:",
    "feedback": "greater than in straight and level flight, because it must balance the weight and generate the centripetal force"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane entering ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL remains constant\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A variable pitch propeller during take-off  will move towards:",
    "feedback": "fine pitch to ensure that the engine can develop its maximum power"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most effective flap system?",
    "feedback": "Fowler flap."
  },
  {
    "question": "A deployed slat will:",
    "feedback": "increase the boundary layer energy, move the suction peak from the fixed part of the wing to the slat, so that the stall is postponed to higher angles of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the bodies in motion (all bodies have the same cross section area) will have lowest drag?",
    "feedback": "Body c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Examples of aerodynamic balancing of control surfaces are:",
    "feedback": "servo tab, spring tab, seal between the wing trailing edge and the leading edge of control surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Line 4 corresponds to aerofoil 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where on the curve in the diagram does the aeroplane exhibit neutral static longitudinal stability?",
    "feedback": "Point 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Positive static longitudinal stability means that a:",
    "feedback": "nose down moment occurs after encountering an upgust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about propeller noise is correct?\n\n1) Propeller noise decreases when the blade tip speed increases\n2) For a given engine and propeller blade shape, an increase in the number of propeller blades allows for a reduction in propeller noise",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of an aft shift of the centre of gravity on (1) static longitudinal stability and (2) the required control deflection for a given pitch change?",
    "feedback": "(1) reduces, (2) reduces"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying through the transonic range whilst maintaining straight and level flight. As the Mach number increases the centre of pressure of the wing will move aft. This movement requires:",
    "feedback": "a pitch up input of the elevator or the stabilizer."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements regarding induced drag is correct?",
    "feedback": "An increase in speed will decrease induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "On FAR 23 airplane, the limit load factor in normal category is",
    "feedback": "+3,8 G"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line in the diagram illustrates an aeroplane neutral static longitudinally stability at all angles of attack?",
    "feedback": "Line 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The negative manoeuvring limit load factor for a light aeroplane in the normal category in the clean configuration may not be less than:",
    "feedback": "-1.52"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The density behind an oblique shock wave is higher than in front of it\n2) The local speed of sound behind an oblique shock wave is lower than in front of it",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Increasing the number of propeller blades will:",
    "feedback": "increase the maximum absorption of power."
  },
  {
    "question": "During flight testing, the minimum control speeds are established. The VMCG must be established with the (1) .... CG position and (2) .... the use of nose wheel steering",
    "feedback": "(1) most unfavourable; (2) without"
  },
  {
    "question": "The induced angle of attack is the result of:",
    "feedback": "downwash due to tip vortices"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the continuity equation is applicable, what will happen to the air density (rho) if the cross sectional area of a tube changes ? (low speed, subsonic and incompressible flow)",
    "feedback": "rho1 = rho2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider two-engine aeroplanes:\nAeroplane 1 has clockwise-rotating propellersAeroplane 2 has inward-rotating propellers\nIf, on both aeroplanes, the left engine fails, which aeroplane will give the largest yawing moment, and from which side will it be?",
    "feedback": "Aeroplane 1 will have the greatest yawing moment, and it will produce a yaw to the left"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane entering ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle remains constant\n2) The induced angle of attack decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 100 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly increases the speed by 20 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "increase to 1.44"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the unit of measurement for power ?",
    "feedback": "Nm/s"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing twist (geometric and aerodynamic) is used to:\n\n1) improve stall characteristics\n2) reduce induced drag\n3) reduce interference drag\n4) increase VMO\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum speed at which lift equals weight is called:",
    "feedback": "VS1g"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure does not change as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity increases as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lift is the:",
    "feedback": "component of the total aerodynamic force, perpendicular to the undisturbed airflow"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number of a conventional aerofoil section increases if:",
    "feedback": "its camber is decreased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a climb above the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "IAS decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a straight, steady climb the thrust must be:",
    "feedback": "greater than the drag because it must also balance a component of weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flaps are deployed at constant angle of attack the lift coefficient will:",
    "feedback": "increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "In what phase of flight are the outboard ailerons (if fitted) not active?",
    "feedback": "Cruise"
  },
  {
    "question": "The local speed of sound in air is proportional to the ......",
    "feedback": "square root of the air temperature in Kelvin (K)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Induced drag decreases as angle of attack decreases\n2) At constant load factor, induced drag decreases with decreasing aeroplane mass",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure increases as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity decreases as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Line 2 corresponds to aerofoil 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Aero-elastic coupling does not affect flutter characteristics\n2) Occurrence of flutter is independent of IAS",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement regarding the manoeuvre and gust load diagram in the clean configuration is correct?\n\n1) The gust load diagram has a symmetrical shape with respect to the n=1 line for speeds above VB\n2) The manoeuvre load diagram does not extend beyond the speed VC",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number of a conventional aerofoil section increases if:",
    "feedback": "its leading edge radius is decreased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Trailing edge flaps once extended :",
    "feedback": "degrade the minimum glide angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "As an aeroplane slows down to flap-limiting speed during the early part of an approach, the wing tip vortices and downwash will vary in intensity. How does this affect the induced Angle of Attack along the wing?\nInduced Angle of Attack will....",
    "feedback": "increase, especially near the wing tip"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about Bernoulli's equation is correct?",
    "feedback": "Dynamic pressure decreases as static pressure increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane leaving ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle decreases\n2) The induced angle of attack decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Shock induced separation can occur:",
    "feedback": "behind a strong normal shock wave, independent of angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "The calibrated airspeed during the take-off run at which, when the critical engine is suddenly made inoperative, it is possible to maintain control of the aeroplane using the rudder control alone, and the lateral control to the extent of keeping the wings level to enable the take-off to be safely continued using normal piloting skills, is called ....",
    "feedback": "VMCG"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure does not change as the streamlines diverge\n2) the velocity decreases as the streamlines diverge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift coefficient CI versus angle of attack curve of a positively cambered aerofoil section intersects the horizontal axis of the graph:",
    "feedback": "to the left of the origin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift coefficient (CL) of an aeroplane in steady horizontal flight is 0.35. Increase in angle of attack of 1 degree will increase CL by 0.079. A vertical up gust instantly changes the angle of attack by 2 degrees. The load factor will be :",
    "feedback": "1.45"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.4 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "51%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Induced drag increases as angle of attack increases\n2) At constant load factor, induced drag increases with increasing aeroplane mass",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about stall speed is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Decreasing forward sweep decreases stall speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 100 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value of 1.44:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 20 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying near sea level with a true air speed of 200 knots.  You then\nclimb to 10000 feet and keep the same true speed. The drag and IAS",
    "feedback": "Are both smaller"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following (1) aerofoils and (2) angles of attack will produce the highest Mcrit values?",
    "feedback": "(1) thin and (2) small."
  },
  {
    "question": "A forward CG shift:",
    "feedback": "increases static longitudinal stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you decrease the propeller pitch during a glide with idle-power at constant IAS the lift to drag ratio will",
    "feedback": "decrease and the rate of descent will increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When initiating a steady horizontal turn from steady straight and level flight the buffet free range increases\n2) When mass decreases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "From an initial condition of level flight the flaps are extended at a constant pitch attitude. The aeroplane will subsequently:",
    "feedback": "start to climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane leaving ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL increases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which formula or equation describes the relationship between force (F), acceleration (a) and mass (m)?",
    "feedback": "F=m. a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation and no compressibility effects, the location of the aerodynamic centre of an aerofoil section:",
    "feedback": "is at approximately 25 % chord irrespective of angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Stall speeds are determined with the CG at the aft limit\n2) Minimum control speeds are determined with the CG at the forward limit",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Positive static lateral stability is the tendency of an aeroplane to:",
    "feedback": "roll to the left in the case of a sideslip (with the aeroplane nose pointing to the left of the incoming flow)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding a positively cambered aerofoil section, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The angle of attack has a positive value when the lift coefficient equals zero\n2) A nose up pitching moment exists when the lift coefficient equals zero",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A light-weight fillet is installed at the wing root of an airplane, blending the wing shape into the fuselage with a gentle curve. The main aerodynamic effect of the fillet is to ....",
    "feedback": "reduce interference drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given two identical aeroplanes with wing mounted engines, one fitted with jet engines and the other with counter rotating propellers, which of these statements is correct about roll behaviour after an engine failure?",
    "feedback": "The propeller aeroplane has more roll tendency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ignoring thrust effects in a steady straight climb at a climb angle \"gamma\", the lift of an aeroplane with weight W is:",
    "feedback": "W * cos gamma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared to straight wings, swept back wings have",
    "feedback": "Better directional stability."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Mcrit is equal to the drag divergence Mach number\n2) Assuming a given angle of attack and for M < 1 the drag coefficient CD increases above the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "One SI unit of measurement for pressure is:",
    "feedback": "N/m2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number can be increased by",
    "feedback": "sweepback of the wings."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements are correct or incorrect regarding a sideslip, with the relative airflow coming from the right, on an aeroplane that exhibits both directional and lateral stability?\n\n1) The initial tendency of the nose of the aeroplane is to move to the right\n2) The initial tendency of the right wing is to move down",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has a stall speed of 100 kt at a mass of 1000 kg. If the mass is increased to 2000 kg, the new value of stall speed will be:",
    "feedback": "141 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aspect ratio of a wing is the ratio between:",
    "feedback": "wing span squared and wing area"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pilot flying an aircraft extends the trailing edge flaps. This will allow for (1) ...... lift, with (2) ...... speed and (3) ...... drag.",
    "feedback": "(1) the same, (2) less, (3) higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct statement:",
    "feedback": "Aerofoil 2 corresponds to line 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the slope of the lift versus angle of attack curve increases, the gust load factor decreases\n2) When the wing loading increases, the gust load factor decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the CG position is moved aft, the elevator deflection to achieve an increase in load factor will be:",
    "feedback": "smaller"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider two elevator control systems:\n\n1) is fitted with a trim tab\n2) is fitted with fully powered hydraulic controls and an adjustable horizontal stabiliser\n\nFor both cases and starting from a trimmed condition, how will the neutral position of the control column change, after trimming for a speed decrease?",
    "feedback": "1 moves aft, 2 does not change"
  },
  {
    "question": "Balancing of the weight component along the flight path in a glide is achieved by:",
    "feedback": "drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Winglets",
    "feedback": "decrease the induced drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 10\nThrust per engine: 30000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a three-engine aeroplane, the all-engines climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "8.0 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following (1) aerofoils and (2) angles of attack will produce the lowest Mcrit values?",
    "feedback": "(1) thick and (2) large."
  },
  {
    "question": "Flaps are used in order to:",
    "feedback": "Decrease stalling speed and reduce max angle of attack thereby achieving a     more nose down attitude near and at stalling speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a right turn, the slip indicator is left of neutral. One way to co-ordinate the turn is to apply:",
    "feedback": "more right bank"
  },
  {
    "question": "Upon extension of a wing spoiler, if the angle of attack remains constant:",
    "feedback": "CD increases and CL decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The induced drag coefficient, CDi is proportional with:",
    "feedback": "CL²"
  },
  {
    "question": "The figure shows an aeroplane in cruise flight, suffering an engine failure with significant damage. The pilot knows that, if the clouds are entered, it will cause significant turbulence making it more difficult to handle the failure. To avoid entering the clouds and to maintain the current flight path tracking, the pilot must apply ....",
    "feedback": "right rudder to balance any yawing moments and to maintain straight flight, and right aileron to generate a sideslip towards the operating engine, achieving a net zero sideslip"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the airflow around a positively cambered aerofoil that is producing lift, the point of minimum static pressure is found ......",
    "feedback": "where the streamlines are closest together"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the reason for mass balancing a control surface?",
    "feedback": "To move the centre of gravity forward thereby preventing flutter."
  },
  {
    "question": "A shock wave on a lift generating wing will:",
    "feedback": "move aft as Mach number is increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "VMCL is the:",
    "feedback": "minimum control speed approach and landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane's flight path angle is defined as the angle between its:",
    "feedback": "speed vector and the horizontal plane"
  },
  {
    "question": "The image shows a flap position indicator. After departure, one of the flaps has jammed during retraction and the above indication is displayed.\nWhat control inputs are required to maintain straight flight?",
    "feedback": "Right aileron input and opposite rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the Mach number is slowly increased in straight and level flight the first shockwaves will occur:",
    "feedback": "at the wing root segment, upperside."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about a propeller is correct?\n\n1) Asymmetric blade effect increases when engine power is increased\n2) Asymmetric blade effect reduces when the angle between the propeller axis and airflow through the propeller disc increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of an engine failure on a twin engine aeroplane, the most aerodynamically efficient way ouf counteracting the yawing moment from the asymmetric thrust is by using ....",
    "feedback": "the rudder and ailerons"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a wing flying in supersonic flow, the normal shock wave forms at an angle of ......",
    "feedback": "90° to the wing surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "The correct drag formula can be written as:\n(rho = density)",
    "feedback": "D= CD 1/2 RHO V² S"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the equilibrium of forces and moments at VMCA are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Equilibrium of moments about the normal axis is provided by rudder deflection\n2) Equilibrium of forces along the lateral axis does not require any side slip during a wings level condition",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing flutter may be caused by a:",
    "feedback": "combination of bending and torsion of the wing structure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nA jet transport aeroplane with a mass of 100 tons carries out a steady level 50 degree bank turn at FL 360. The buffet free speed range extends approximately from:",
    "feedback": "M = 0.72 to M > 0.84"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stalling speed in IAS will change according to the following factors:",
    "feedback": "May increase during turbulence and will always increase when banking in a turn"
  },
  {
    "question": "Extending flaps will (1) ...... CL , (2) ...... speed and (3) ...... stall speed.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) decrease, (3) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is correct regarding VMC?",
    "feedback": "Bank angle not more than 5° and maximum power"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation, which of these statements about the flow around an aerofoil as the angle of attack increases are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The stagnation point moves up\n2) The point of lowest static pressure moves forward",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approximately how long does it take to fly a complete circle during a horizontal steady co-ordinated turn with a bank angle of 45° and a TAS of 380 kt?",
    "feedback": "125 s"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the manoeuvre stability of an aeroplane is 250 N/g. The stick force required to achieve a load factor of 2.5 from steady level trimmed flight is:",
    "feedback": "375 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the Mach angle calculated?",
    "feedback": "sin(mu) = 1/M"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?\nI VMCL is the minimum control speed in the landing configuration.\nII The speed VMCL can be limited by the available maximum roll rate",
    "feedback": "I is correct, II is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet aeroplane is cruising at high altitude with a Mach-number, that provides a buffet margin of 0.3g incremental. In order to increase the buffet margin to 0.4g incremental the pilot must :",
    "feedback": "fly at a lower altitude and the same Mach-number"
  },
  {
    "question": "During landing of a low-winged jet aeroplane, the greatest elevator up deflection is normally required when the flaps are:",
    "feedback": "fully down and the C.G. is fully forward."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answers is correct regarding the formation of ice on a propeller?",
    "feedback": "The presence of ice on propeller blades causes propeller efficiency to be reduced by up to 20 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "If an aeroplane exhibits insufficient stick force per g, this problem can be resolved by installing:",
    "feedback": "a bobweight in the control system which pulls the stick forwards"
  },
  {
    "question": "The characteristics of  a \"high aspect ratio\" wing has are:",
    "feedback": "short chord, long span"
  },
  {
    "question": "While a multi-engine aeroplane is taking off on a wet runway, the aeroplane starts becoming uncontrollable with significant yaw. This is due to ....",
    "feedback": "asymmetric thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is performing an approach with one engine inoperative. The outside air temperature at sea level is minus ten degrees. The aircraft is unstable on final approach and the pilot decides to perform a missed approach. What is the effect on VMCA?",
    "feedback": "High engine performance due to higher air density, thus, VMCA increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dynamic pressure increases proportionally with:",
    "feedback": "Density and the square of the velocity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the wing area decreases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the EAS decreases, the gust load factor decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram shows a left turn, where there is not enough bank for a co-ordinated turn?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions, climbing at a constant Mach number up to the tropopause the TAS will:",
    "feedback": "decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet transport aeroplane is in a straight climb at a constant IAS and constant weight. The operational limit that may be exceeded is:",
    "feedback": "MMO."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which combination produces the least amount of induced drag?",
    "feedback": "Low wing at landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of icing or other airframe contaminants on the value of CLMAX stall speed, and critical angle of attack?\nThe CLMAX .....",
    "feedback": "decreases, stall speed increases, and critical angle of attack decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no pilot input the motion of the aeroplane in the diagram shows:",
    "feedback": "static longitudinal stability and dynamic longitudinal instability"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Mach trimmer:",
    "feedback": "corrects insufficient stick force stability at high Mach Numbers."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) If flutter occurs, IAS should be kept constant\n2) Resistance to flutter increases with increasing wing stiffness",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The diagram shows the parameter Y against TAS. If horizontal flight is considered axis Y represents:",
    "feedback": "the induced drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "In cruising flight, with the centre of gravity forward of main wing centre of pressure, the force on the horizontal tailplane is directed:",
    "feedback": "Downward in order to balance the aerodynamic moment about the centre of gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a constant load factor, which of these statements about the variation of induced drag with changes of speed and mass are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed increases, induced drag increases\n2) When mass increases, induced drag decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a climb below the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "lift coefficient increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 2 VS. If a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 1.3 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "n = 1.65"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about propeller noise is correct?\n\n1) Propeller noise remains the same when the blade tip speed increases\n2) For a given engine and propeller blade shape, a decrease in the number of propeller blades allows for a reduction in propeller noise",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a constant load factor, which of these statements about the variation of induced drag with changes of speed and mass are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed decreases, induced drag decreases\n2) When mass decreases, induced drag increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst maintaining straight and level flight with a lift coefficient CL=1, what will be the new value of CL after the speed has doubled?",
    "feedback": "0.25"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about propeller icing is correct?\n\n1) Propeller icing increases blade element drag and reduces blade element lift\n2) Propeller icing does not affect propeller efficiency",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rotation around the normal axis is called :",
    "feedback": "yawing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given an aeroplane in steady, straight and level flight at low speed and considering the effects of CG location and thrust, the highest value of wing lift occurs at:",
    "feedback": "forward CG and idle thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The drag divergence Mach number is higher than Mcrit\n2) Below the drag divergence Mach number and for a given angle of attack the drag coefficient CD is practically constant as the Mach number changes",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "One advantage of a supercritical wing aerofoil over a conventional one is:",
    "feedback": "it allows a wing of increased relative thickness to be used for approximately the same cruise Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "The formula for the Mach Number is:\n(a= speed of sound)",
    "feedback": "M= TAS / a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.\nWhat is the correct combination of letters identifying the airfoils with the corresponding numbers from the CD graph?",
    "feedback": "1 - d, 2 - a, 3 - c, 4 - b"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"A line connecting the leading- and trailing edge midway between the upper and lower surface of an aerofoil\". This definition is applicable for :",
    "feedback": "the camber line"
  },
  {
    "question": "Static stability means that:",
    "feedback": "following a disturbance from the equilibrium condition, a force and/or moment is generated that tends to counter the effects of that disturbance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The location of the wing centre of pressure (CP) forward or aft of the CG, influences the:",
    "feedback": "Pitching moment and consequently the direction of the stabiliser balancing force"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the mass decreases, the gust load factor decreases\n2) When the altitude decreases, the gust load factor decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the location of the CG influence VMCG?",
    "feedback": "A forward CG reduces VMCG"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approximately how long does it take to fly a complete circle during a horizontal steady co-ordinated turn with a bank angle of 45° and a TAS of 288 kt?",
    "feedback": "95 s"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane leaving ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL decreases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is VMCG determined with the nosewheel steering disconnected?",
    "feedback": "Because the value of VMCG must also be applicable on wet and/or slippery runways."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the danger when recovering from an emergency descent?",
    "feedback": "structural damage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about propellers is correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A cruise propeller has a greater geometric pitch compared with a climb propeller\n2) A coarse pitch propeller is more efficient during take off and in the climb, but less efficient in cruise, when compared with a fine pitch propeller",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "After an aeroplane has been trimmed:",
    "feedback": "the stick position stability will be unchanged"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are used as stall warning devices?",
    "feedback": "Stick shaker and angle of attack indicator."
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A stabiliser trim is less suitable for jet transport aeroplanes because of their large speed range\n2) A trim tab is a more powerful means of trimming",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dihedral of the wing is:",
    "feedback": "the angle between the 0.25 chord line of the wing and the lateral axis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A trim tab is less suitable for jet transport aeroplanes because of their large speed range\n2) A trim tab is a more powerful means of trimming",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dynamic pressure is expressed as",
    "feedback": "(rho/2)* V^2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What locations are the most susceptible to ice build-up during flight?",
    "feedback": "Parts of the aircraft that have a small radius, bend sharply, and hence have a higher curvature, such as narrow leading edges of the wings and tail, probes and antennas"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Mcrit is higher than the drag divergence Mach number\n2) Assuming a given angle of attack and for M < 1 the drag coefficient CD remains practically constant above the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed decreases the buffet free range does not change\n2) When the CG moves forward the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Induced drag decreases as angle of attack decreases\n2) At constant load factor, induced drag increases with decreasing aeroplane mass",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to maintain straight and level flight at a constant airspeed, whilst the flaps are being retracted, the angle of attack will:",
    "feedback": "increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane that tends to return to its pre-disturbed equilibrium position after the disturbance has been removed is said to have:",
    "feedback": "positive static stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Upward deflection of a trim tab in the longitudinal control results in:",
    "feedback": "the stick position stability remaining constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aerofoil is cambered when:",
    "feedback": "the line, which connects the centres of all incscribed circles, is curved"
  },
  {
    "question": "The tab in the figure represents:",
    "feedback": "a servo tab"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about propeller noise is correct?\n\n1) Propeller noise decreases when the blade tip speed increases\n2) For a given engine and propeller blade shape, a decrease in the number of propeller blades allows for a reduction in propeller noise",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Propeller gyroscopic effect occurs during flight at constant aeroplane attitude\n2) Propeller gyroscopic effect is most noticeable during low speed flight at high propeller RPM",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the gyroscopic effect of a clockwise rotating propeller on a single engine aeroplane?\n\n1) Pitch up produces right yaw\n2) Right yaw produces pitch up",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about weight or mass is correct?",
    "feedback": "The mass of an object is independent of the acceleration due to gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is taking off from an aerodrome at sea level with an outside air temperature below 15°C. What should a pilot be aware of, regarding the controllability, with one engine inoperative?",
    "feedback": "A high VMC due to the engine's high performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following provides a positive contribution to static directional stability?",
    "feedback": "A dorsal fin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the supersonic speed range is correct?",
    "feedback": "The airflow everywhere around the aeroplane is supersonic"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed in the landing configuration is represented by the following:",
    "feedback": "VS0"
  },
  {
    "question": "To perform a co-ordinated turn the aeroplane in diagram 2 should use:",
    "feedback": "less left rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nA jet transport aeroplane with a mass of 100 tons carries out a steady level 50 degree bank turn at FL 320. The buffet free speed range extends approximately from:",
    "feedback": "M = 0.65 to M > 0.84"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack increases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the correct relationship between the true air speed for (i) minimum sink rate and (ii) minimum glide angle, at a given altitude?",
    "feedback": "(i) is less than (ii)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about a propeller is correct?\n\n1) Asymmetric blade effect increases when engine power is increased\n2) Asymmetric blade effect is independent of the angle between the propeller axis and airflow through the propeller disc",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.6 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "39%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding a symmetric aerofoil section, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The angle of attack has a positive value when the lift coefficient equals zero\n2) A nose down pitching moment exists when the lift coefficient equals zero",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What limits are raken into account when defining VMC?",
    "feedback": "5 bank angle and max TO thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the difference between Krueger flaps and slats is correct?",
    "feedback": "Deploying a slat will form a slot, deploying a Krueger flap does not."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about VMCG determination are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) During VMCG determination, nose wheel steering may be used\n2) During VMCG determination, the CG should be on the aft limit",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does temperature influence the speed of sound?",
    "feedback": "Speed of sound increases with temperature increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "How would the exterior appearance of an aeroplane change, when trimming for speed increase ?",
    "feedback": "Elevator deflection is increased further downward by an upward deflected trim tab"
  },
  {
    "question": "Increasing dynamic pressure will have the following effect on the drag of an aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "at speeds above the minimum drag speed, total drag increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the throat is the same as in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The speed of the airflow in the throat is lower than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing tip vortices have the highest intensity during:",
    "feedback": "Take off"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spoilers mounted on the wing upper surface can be used to:",
    "feedback": "assist the ailerons"
  },
  {
    "question": "Increasing air pressure will have the following effect on the drag of an aeroplane (angle of attack, OAT and TAS are constant):",
    "feedback": "The drag increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Some wings are designed with a smaller angle of incidence towards the wing tip or a profile with a different camber towards the wing tip. The reason for this is to ......",
    "feedback": "delay the stall at the wing tip to reduce the likelihood of the aeroplane experiencing significant rolling moments when stalled"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the wing planform represented in the diagram and the following dimensions:\nSpan 12.5 mRoot chord 1.5 mTip chord 1.0 m\n\nThe correct values of wing area and taper ratio or aspect ratio are:",
    "feedback": "Wing area: 15.625 m2, taper ratio: 0.666"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a jet transport aeroplane takes off with the CG at the forward limit and the trimmable horizontal stabiliser (THS) is positioned at the maximum allowable nose down position for take-off:",
    "feedback": "rotation will require a higher than normal stick force"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation and no compressibility effects, the location of the centre of pressure of a positively cambered aerofoil section:",
    "feedback": "moves backward when the angle of attack decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main function of a trailing edge flap is to:",
    "feedback": "increase the maximum lift coefficient of the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The point, where the single resultant aerodynamic force acts on an aerofoil is called:",
    "feedback": "centre of pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about \"tuck under\" are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) \"Tuck under\" is caused by an aft movement of the centre of pressure of the wing\n2) \"Tuck under\" is caused by a reduction in the downwash angle at the location of the horizontal stabiliser",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Stick force per g is independent of altitude\n2) Stick force per g increases when the centre of gravity moves forward",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Match the letters identifying the aerofoils with the corresponding curve numbers from the CL vs. Αlpha chart.",
    "feedback": "Aerofoil A - Curve 2, Aerofoil B - Curve 3, Aerofoil C - Curve 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following unit of measurement: kgm/s² is expressed in the SI-system as :",
    "feedback": "Newton"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is on an approach with flaps in the landing position. ATC instructs the pilot to go around, at which point, a left engine failure is experienced. How will the aircraft behave when established in a nose up attitude?",
    "feedback": "Bank towards the left, flaps increase the roll"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) An rectangular spanwise lift distribution generates less induced drag than an elliptical lift distribution\n2) Induced drag increases with increasing aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) Propeller gyroscopic effect occurs during flight at constant aeroplane attitude\n2) Propeller gyroscopic effect is most noticeable during low speed flight at low propeller RPM",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which combination of design features is known to be responsible for deep stall?",
    "feedback": "Swept back wings and a T-tail."
  },
  {
    "question": "The aerodynamic centre of the wing is the point relative to which:",
    "feedback": "assuming no flow separation, the pitching moment coefficient does not change with varying angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the influence of decreasing aeroplane weight on Mcrit at constant IAS ?",
    "feedback": "Mcrit increases as a result of flying at a smaller angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "Trailing edge flap extension will:",
    "feedback": "decrease the critical angle of attack and increase the value of CLmax."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the heading change after 10 seconds of an aeroplane performing a rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "30 degrees"
  },
  {
    "question": "The positive manoeuvring limit load factor for a light aeroplane in the normal category in the clean configuration may not be less than:",
    "feedback": "3.8"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has a stall speed of 100 kt at a load factor n=1. In a turn with a load factor of n=2, the stall speed is:",
    "feedback": "141 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about stall speed is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Decreasing sweepback decreases stall speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "A twin-engine propeller aircraft suffers an engine failure. Under which of the following circumstances is retention of control likely to be most difficult?",
    "feedback": "Aerodrome at low density altitude, critical engine failure at the point of go-around"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When altitude increases the buffet free range increases\n2) When load factor increases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The primary purpose of dihedral is to:",
    "feedback": "increase static lateral stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify the significant point on the polar curve:",
    "feedback": "1) Stall speed; 2) VMP; 3) VMD; 4) 1.32 VMD"
  },
  {
    "question": "When Fowler type trailing edge flaps are extended at a constant angle of attack, the following changes will occur:",
    "feedback": "CL and CD increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "At higher altitudes, the stall speed (IAS):",
    "feedback": "increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a co-ordinated horizontal turn, the magnitude of the centripetal force at 45 degrees of bank:",
    "feedback": "is equal to the weight of the aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would the TODR (take-off distance required) for a fixed wing aircraft vary with increasing flap settings, from retracted to full flaps?",
    "feedback": "It would decrease and then increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "The output of a turboprop engine is usually indicated by,",
    "feedback": "torque"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is less than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "during a wings level stall before recovery"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a graph showing lift coefficient vs. angle-of-attack (CL vs. α) for a symmetrical aerofoil. Which of the following is defined by the point which crosses the vertical axis of this graph?",
    "feedback": "Zero lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "One disadvantage of wing sweepback is:",
    "feedback": "the tendency of the wingtip section to stall prior to the wing root section"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical angle of attack:",
    "feedback": "remains unchanged regardless of gross weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight flight, as speed is increased, whilst trimming to keep the stick force zero:",
    "feedback": "the elevator is deflected further downwards and the trim tab further upwards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming constant IAS, when an aeroplane enters ground effect:",
    "feedback": "downwash reduces"
  },
  {
    "question": "If excessive rudder is used to tighten a low-speed turn, this can result in ....",
    "feedback": "a skid, which could lead to a spin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The shape of the gust load diagram is also determinated by the following three vertical speed in ft/s (clean configuration) :",
    "feedback": "25, 50, 66"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deploying a Fowler flap, the flap will:",
    "feedback": "move aft, then turn down."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the wing area decreases, the gust load factor decreases\n2) When the EAS decreases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to remain in level balanced flight:",
    "feedback": "the wing lift must be greater than weight, if the tailplane is giving a download for balance"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 100 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value of 1.69:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 30 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct? \nThe lift to drag ratio provides directly the",
    "feedback": "glide distance from a given altitude at zero wind."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which definition of propeller parameters is correct?",
    "feedback": "Helix angle is the angle between the actual path of the propeller and the plane of rotation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following configurations will give the highest Lift/Drag ratio?",
    "feedback": "Clean wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "A slat will",
    "feedback": "increase the boundary layer energy and prolongs the stall to a higher angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "The Mach-trim function is installed on most commercial jets in order to minimize the adverse effects of :",
    "feedback": "changes in the position of centre of pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "A spin could arise from:",
    "feedback": "Large rudder deflection during a stall"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about wing sweepback are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Increasing wing sweepback decreases Mcrit\n2) Increasing wing sweepback decreases the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which definition of propeller parameters is correct?",
    "feedback": "Propeller angle of attack is the angle between the blade chord line and relative airflow"
  },
  {
    "question": "One feature of a wing is the \"Mean Chord\" which is the:",
    "feedback": "wing area divided by the span"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a given elevator deflection, aeroplane longitudinal manoeuvrability increases when:",
    "feedback": "the CG moves aft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In transonic flight the ailerons will be less effective than in subsonic flight because:",
    "feedback": "aileron deflection only partly affects the pressure distribution around the wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most correct option with regard to skin friction drag?",
    "feedback": "Skin friction drag is caused by the air's viscosity producing shear forces within the boundary layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the induced drag of an aeroplane in straight and level flight at constant mass varies linearly with:",
    "feedback": "1/V²"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach number of a conventional aerofoil section increases if:",
    "feedback": "it is flown at lower angles of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "If flaps are deployed at constant IAS in straight and level flight, the magnitude of tip vortices will eventually : (flap span less than wing span)",
    "feedback": "decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "The SI unit of measurement for density is:",
    "feedback": "kg/m3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure decreases as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity increases as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aerofoil at its stalling angle will have a  Lift/Drag ratio which is:",
    "feedback": "low"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sweepback of a wing positively influences:\n\n1) static longitudinal stability\n2) static lateral stability\n3) dynamic longitudinal stability\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line in the diagram represents an aeroplane with static longitudinal instability at all angles of attack?",
    "feedback": "Line 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the wing area increases, the gust load factor decreases\n2) When the EAS increases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about the gust load on an aeroplane (IAS and all other factors of importance remaining constant) ?\n\n1. the gust load increases, when the weight decreases.\n\n2. the gust load increases, when the altitude increases.",
    "feedback": "1 is correct and 2 is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about the dynamic longitudinal stability of a conventional aeroplane is correct?",
    "feedback": "Damping of the phugoid is normally very weak"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 200 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value 1.21:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 20 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "High Aspect Ratio, as compared with low Aspect Ratio, has the effect of :",
    "feedback": "Decreasing induced drag and critical angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "A CG location beyond the aft limit can cause:",
    "feedback": "an unacceptably low value of the manoeuvre stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "With the propeller windmilling after an engine failure, the",
    "feedback": "ATM and CTM will act in the same direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "A transport aircraft needs to be flown back to the maintenance facility empty, following a cabin pressurisation issue. What should the crew be aware of regarding the one-engine inoperative controllability after takeoff?",
    "feedback": "A decreased safety margin to VMC due to the low operating speeds associated with low mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the heading change of an aeroplane after 30 seconds in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "90 degrees"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.3 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2.3, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "irrelevant, since the aeroplane would already be in a stalled condition at 1.3 VS with that gust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about \"tuck under\" are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A contributing factor to \"tuck under\" is a forward movement of the centre of pressure of the wing\n2) A contributing factor to \"tuck under\" is an increase in the downwash angle at the location of the horizontal stabiliser",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\ntheta = pitch angle\ngamma = flight path angle\nalpha = angle of attack\nno wind, bank or sideslip\n\nThe relationship between these three paramets is:",
    "feedback": "theta = gamma + alpha"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the Mach number increases the buffet free range decreases\n2) When the load factor decreases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In straight and level flight at a speed of 1.2 VS, the lift coefficient, expressed as a percentage of its maximum CLMAX, would be:",
    "feedback": "69%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation and no compressibility effects, the location of the centre of pressure of a symmetrical aerofoil section:",
    "feedback": "is at approximately 25 % chord irrespective of angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "As altitude increases, the stall speed (IAS):",
    "feedback": "initially remains constant but at higher altitude increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The effects of a trim tab runaway are more serious\n2) A jammed trim tab causes less control difficulty",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aerodynamic centre of a wing is the point relative to which:",
    "feedback": "assuming no flow separation, the pitching moment coefficient does not change with varying angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about static longitudinal stability is correct or incorrect?\n\n1) A requirement for positive static longitudinal stability of an aeroplane is, that the neutral point is behind the centre of gravity\n2) A wing with positive camber provides a positive contribution to static longitudinal stability, when the centre of gravity of the aeroplane is in front of the aerodynamic centre of the wing",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the density altitude increases, what happens to the Minimum Control Speed (VMC)?",
    "feedback": "As thrust decreases, VMC decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum cruise altitude can be limited by a 1.3g load factor because when exceeding that altitude:",
    "feedback": "turbulence may induce high speed or low speed buffet"
  },
  {
    "question": "By what percentage does the lift increase in a steady level turn at 45° angle of bank, compared to straight and level flight?",
    "feedback": "41%."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming standard atmospheric conditions, in order to generate the same amount of lift as altitude is increased, an aeroplane must be flown at:",
    "feedback": "a higher TAS for any given angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a right turn, the slip indicator is left of neutral. One way to co-ordinate the turn is to apply:",
    "feedback": "more left rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a short period oscillation, the altitude:",
    "feedback": "remains approximately constant, whereas during a phugoid it varies significantly"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a mechanically controlled aeroplane, the most forward allowable position of the centre of gravity could be limited by the:",
    "feedback": "elevator capability, elevator control forces."
  },
  {
    "question": "During landing, when the aeroplane enters ground effect ....",
    "feedback": "the intensity of the wing tip vortices decreases, leading to more efficient lift generation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Extending flaps from clean to landing configuration will (1) ..... the wing's effective camber and (2) ..... the stall speed.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the trailing edge flaps are deflected in level flight, the change in pitch moment will be:",
    "feedback": "nose down."
  },
  {
    "question": "When the stick force required to achieve a load factor of 3 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is 150 N, the value of the manoeuvre stability of that aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "75 N/g"
  },
  {
    "question": "To reduce friction drag, some aeroplanes are equipped with modified wing designs to:",
    "feedback": "Delay the transition point and have a larger laminar flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft accelerates towards the transonic speed region. What happens to CLMAX and the stalling speed?",
    "feedback": "CLMAX will decrease and the stalling speed will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of flap is shown in the picture 3?",
    "feedback": "Split flap"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mass balancing of control surfaces is used to:",
    "feedback": "prevent flutter of control surfaces"
  },
  {
    "question": "What increases the stalling angle of attack ? Use of :",
    "feedback": "slats"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the location of the CG influence VMCL?",
    "feedback": "A forward CG reduces VMCL"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure\nGiven:Aircraft mass: 110 tBank angle: 45°Flight level: FL370\nWhich of the following statements are correct or incorrect?\n1) Speed M = 0.80 is within the buffet free range2) Speed M = 0.76 allows for higher altitude than speed M = 0.82",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect of a wing sweep back to static directional stability is:",
    "feedback": "positive"
  },
  {
    "question": "When spoilers are used as speed brakes:",
    "feedback": "at the same angle of attack, CD is increased and CL is decreased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about the trim position is true related to centre of gravity and adjustable stabiliser position ?",
    "feedback": "A nose heavy aeroplane requires that the stabiliser leading edge is lower than compared with a tail heavy aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared to a cambered airfoil, the zero lift angle of attack of a symmetrical airfoil is",
    "feedback": "higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mcrit is the free stream Mach Number at which:",
    "feedback": "somewhere about the airframe Mach 1 is reached locally."
  },
  {
    "question": "Modern jet aeroplanes usually fly at speeds faster than MCRIT, since the increase in speed is more significant than the increase in drag. How is this achieved?",
    "feedback": "By using a supercritical aerofoil to reduce the severity of shock waves and the amount of wave drag at a given Mach number, when compared to a conventional aerofoil"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the time for a heading change of 30 degrees in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "10 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flutter damping of control surfaces is obtained by mass balancing, these weights will be located with respect to the hinge of the control surface:",
    "feedback": "in front of the hinge."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Aero-elastic coupling does not affect flutter characteristics\n2) The risk of flutter increases as IAS increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat\n2) The speed in the undisturbed airflow is lower than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a constant load factor, which of these statements about the variation of induced drag with changes of speed and mass are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed increases, induced drag decreases\n2) When mass increases, induced drag decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "To perform a co-ordinated turn the aeroplane in diagram 1 should use:",
    "feedback": "less bank angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 100 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value of 2.25",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 50 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "While cruising at M 0.78, an airliner receives a TCAS RA climb command. The manoeuvre causes the angle of attack to temporarily increase. What is the effect on critical alpha?",
    "feedback": "Critical alpha decreases due to compressibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a symmetrical aerofoil is accelerated from subsonic to supersonic speed, the aerodynamic centre will move:",
    "feedback": "aft to approximately mid chord"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Wing mounted engines extending ahead of the wing contribute to wing flutter suppression\n2) Excessive free play or backlash increases the speed at which control surface flutter occurs",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about minimum control speed is correct?",
    "feedback": "VMCA depends on the airport density alitude and the location of the engine on the aeroplane (fuselage or wing)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will happen to the effective angle of attack when the aircraft enters ground effect?",
    "feedback": "It increases due to the decreased downwash"
  },
  {
    "question": "The manoeuvring speed VA, expressed as indicated airspeed, of a transport aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "depends on aeroplane mass and pressure altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane entering the ground effect during the landing phase will experience ......",
    "feedback": "a nose-down pitching moment"
  },
  {
    "question": "The SI units of air density (I) and force (II) are:",
    "feedback": "(I) kg/m3, (II) N"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which point marks the value for minimum sink rate?",
    "feedback": "Point c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nThe maximum achievable load factor without buffet onset at FL 250 at a mass of 140 tons is approximately:",
    "feedback": "2g at M = 0.80"
  },
  {
    "question": "In  a level turn with 60° lateral bank, the load factor is 2.0 and the stall speed increases by:",
    "feedback": "40 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "A shock wave on a lift generating wing will:",
    "feedback": "move forward as Mach number is decreased"
  },
  {
    "question": "A propeller rotating clockwise as seen from the rear tends to rotate the aircraft to the",
    "feedback": "left around the vertical axis, and to the left around the longitudinal axis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about weight or mass is correct?",
    "feedback": "In the SI system the unit of measurement for mass is the kilogram"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the stick force required to achieve a load factor of 2.5 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is 375 N, the value of the manoeuvre stability of that aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "250 N/g"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane climbs to cruising level with a constant pitch attitude and maximum climb thrust (assume normal thrust decay with altitude).\n\nHow do the following variables change during the climb? (Gamma = flight path angle)",
    "feedback": "Gamma decreases, angle of attack increases, IAS decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram shows a left turn, where there is too much bank for a co-ordinated turn?",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "The polar curve of an aerofoil is a graphic relationship between :",
    "feedback": "lift coefficient CI and drag coefficient Cd"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of attack of an aerofoil section is the angle between the:",
    "feedback": "chord line and the relative undisturbed airflow."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has a CL (lift coefficient) of 0.6 and a CDI (induced drag coefficient) value of 0.1 in level flight. The aeroplane slows down while maintaining level flight. The lift coefficient increased by a factor of 1.5 to maintain lift at the lower speed. If there is no change in configuration, what is the new CDI?",
    "feedback": "0.225"
  },
  {
    "question": "The point in the figure showing zero lift is:",
    "feedback": "point a"
  },
  {
    "question": "As the Mach number increases from subsonic to supersonic, the centre of pressure moves:",
    "feedback": "to the mid chord position."
  },
  {
    "question": "The neutral point is the point where:",
    "feedback": "the aeroplane becomes longitudinally unstable when the CG is moved beyond it in an aft direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "As angle of attack is increased on a conventional low speed aerofoil at low subsonic speeds, flow separation normally starts on the:",
    "feedback": "upper surface near the trailing edge"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the parasite drag in straight and level flight at constant weight varies linearly with the:",
    "feedback": "square of the speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift force, acting on an aerofoil :",
    "feedback": "is mainly caused by suction on the upperside of the aerofoil."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane with a mass of 2000 kg is performing a co-ordinated level turn at a constant TAS of 160 kt and a bank angle of 60°. The lift is approximately:",
    "feedback": "40000 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "How will the graph change if spoilers are deployed?",
    "feedback": "B"
  },
  {
    "question": "VMCL is determined under the following aircraft flight configuration and trim setting;",
    "feedback": "Landing flap, trimmed for all engines operating"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a constant load factor, which of these statements about the variation of induced drag with changes of speed and mass are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed decreases, induced drag decreases\n2) When mass decreases, induced drag decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing tip vortices are formed by the ......",
    "feedback": "spanwise flow of higher pressure air from beneath the wing outward and upward into the lower pressure air above the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Mcrit is lower than the drag divergence Mach number\n2) Assuming a given angle of attack and for M < 1 the drag coefficient CD increases above the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these statements about Bernoulli's equastion is correct?",
    "feedback": "Dynamic pressure increases as static pressure decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Vortex generators mounted on the upper wing surface will",
    "feedback": "decrease the shock wave induced separation."
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens to parasite drag if the true airspeed of an aircraft is multiplied by two, and all other parameters are kept constant?\nThe parasite drag ......",
    "feedback": "will be multiplied by four"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aileron deflection causes a rotation around the longitudinal axis by:",
    "feedback": "changing the wing camber and the two wings therefore produce different lift values resulting in a moment about the longitudinal axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) During a push-over manoeuvre the buffet free range decreases\n2) When the mass increases the buffet free range decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Turning motion in a steady, level co-ordinated turn is created by:",
    "feedback": "the centripetal force"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding a propeller?\n\n1) Increasing tip speed to supersonic speed does not affect propeller noise\n2) Increasing tip speed to supersonic speed increases propeller efficiency",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation and no compressibility effects, the location of the centre of pressure of a positively cambered aerofoil section:",
    "feedback": "moves forward when the angle of attack increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "If density is kept constant, the dynamic pressure increases proportionally with:",
    "feedback": "The square of the velocity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following increases the maximum duration of a glide?",
    "feedback": "A decrease in mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are components of parasite drag?\n1) Tip-vortex drag2) Interference drag3) Pressure drag4) Friction drag",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a climb below the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "IAS decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Geometric washout means that",
    "feedback": "the tip of the wing has less angle of attack than the root."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) During a push-over manoeuvre the buffet free range decreases\n2) When the mass increases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the recommended action follwing failure of the yaw damper(s) of a jet aeroplane, flying at normal cruise altitude and speed prior to encountering Dutch roll problems?",
    "feedback": "Reduce altitude and Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane with a mass of 4000 kg is performing a co-ordinated level turn at a constant TAS of 160 kt and a bank angle of 45°. The lift is approximately:",
    "feedback": "56000 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an approach and coming to land, the pilots configure the aeroplane for a full flaps landing. However, the left leading edge slats do not extend. Which statement is true?",
    "feedback": "The left wing may stall if speed decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach Number of an aeroplane is the free stream Mach Number, which produces the first evidence of :",
    "feedback": "local sonic flow."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no compressibility effects, the correct relationship between stall speed, limit load factor (n) and VA is:",
    "feedback": "VA>=VS*SQRT(n)"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a take-off roll with a strong crosswind from the left, a four-engine jet aeroplane with wing-mounted engines experiences an engine failure.  The failure of which engine will cause the greatest control problem?",
    "feedback": "The left outboard engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a training flight you want to demonstrate engine failures by producing the greatest possible yawing moment. For a twin-engined aeroplane with counter-rotating propellers, you would fail:",
    "feedback": "Any engine, as the thrust arm for both engines is equal"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the pitching moment coefficient Cm versus angle of attack diagram?",
    "feedback": "Line 3 shows an aeroplane with greater static longitudinal stability at low angles of attack than that shown in line 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Static lateral stability will be decreased by:",
    "feedback": "increasing wing anhedral"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flap extension at constant IAS whilst maintaining straight and level flight will increase the:",
    "feedback": "maximum lift coefficient (CLMAX) and the drag."
  },
  {
    "question": "The pitch up tendency of an aeroplane with swept back wings during a stall is caused by the:",
    "feedback": "forward movement of the centre of pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about a Mach trimmer is correct?",
    "feedback": "A  Mach trimmer corrects the change in stick force stability of a swept wing aeroplane above a certain Mach number."
  },
  {
    "question": "The strength of the yawing moment caused by an engine failure on a twin-engine aeroplane ....",
    "feedback": "is independent of the location (fore or aft) of the CG"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle between the direction of the undisturbed airflow (relative wind) and the chord line of an aerofoil is the:",
    "feedback": "angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which phenomenon is counteracted with differential aileron deflection?",
    "feedback": "Adverse yaw."
  },
  {
    "question": "The tab in the figure represents:",
    "feedback": "A balance tabe that also functions as a trim tab"
  },
  {
    "question": "As the stability of an aeroplane decreases:",
    "feedback": "its manoeuvrability increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the lift coefficient CI of a symmetrical aerofoil section is zero, the pitching moment is:",
    "feedback": "zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming constant IAS, when an aeroplane leaves ground effect:",
    "feedback": "the effective angle of attack decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical speed where the speed is too low and too high at the same time is called:",
    "feedback": "Coffin corner"
  },
  {
    "question": "When compared to a clean wing, a wing contaminated with ice has (1) ..... stall speed and (2) ..... critical angle of attack.",
    "feedback": "(1) a higher, (2) a lower"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider an aeroplane with:\n\n1) a trim tab\n2) fully powered hydraulic controls and an adjustable horizontal stabiliser\n\nFor both cases and starting from a trimmed condition, how will the neutral position of the control column change, after trimming for a speed increase?",
    "feedback": "1 moves forward, 2 does not change"
  },
  {
    "question": "While extending the trailing edge flaps, the downwash (1) …. . If ice has accumulated on the tail, the risk of premature stabiliser stall (2) ….",
    "feedback": "(1) increases, (2) increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The construction feature of a wing called \"wash out\" is:",
    "feedback": "a decrease in the angle of incidence from root to tip"
  },
  {
    "question": "Yaw is followed by roll because the:",
    "feedback": "yawing motion generated by rudder deflection causes a speed increase of the outer wing, which increases the lift on that wing so that the aeroplane starts to roll in the same direction as the yaw"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aeroplane's angle of incidence is defined as the angle between the:",
    "feedback": "longitudinal axis and the wing root chord line"
  },
  {
    "question": "The sensor of a stall warning system can be activated by a change in the location of the",
    "feedback": "stagnation point."
  },
  {
    "question": "The bank angle in a rate-one turn depends on:",
    "feedback": "TAS."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Induced drag increases as angle of attack decreases\n2) At constant load factor, induced drag increases with decreasing aeroplane mass",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what way is the longitudinal stability affected by the degree of positive camber of the aerofoil?",
    "feedback": "No effect, because camber of the aerofoil produces a constant pitch down moment coefficient, independent of angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "Asymmetric propeller blade effect is mainly induced by:",
    "feedback": "the inclination of the propeller axis to the relative airflow"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aft CG limit can be determined by the:",
    "feedback": "minimum acceptable static longitudinal stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens to induced drag when airspeed increases?",
    "feedback": "Induced drag decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A vortex generator is an aerodynamic device and is used to ......",
    "feedback": "transfer energy from the free airflow into the boundary layer."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a left turn, the slip indicator is left of neutral. One way to co-ordinate the turn is to apply:",
    "feedback": "less left bank"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed decreases the buffet free range increases\n2) When the CG moves forward the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "While performing an obstacle limited take-off, you inadvertently set a lower take-off flap setting (less flap) than calculated and required. Compared to a take-off with the correct flap setting, the aircraft will pass the departure end of the runway at ......",
    "feedback": "lower height, as the lower flap setting means that a greater take-off distance is required"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 12\nThrust per engine: 28000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a three-engine aeroplane, the all-engines climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "8.5 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nDetermine the maximum mass with respect to buffet onset according EASA/CS regulations for FL 400:",
    "feedback": "110 tons"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of horizontal control surface is shown in the figure?",
    "feedback": "All-flying tail"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the Mach number is 0.8 and the TAS is 480 kts, what is the speed of sound?",
    "feedback": "600 kts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The speed of the airflow in the throat is the same as in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which location on the aeroplane has the largest effect on the induced drag ?",
    "feedback": "Wing tip"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack increases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices is not affected by aspect ratio",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mach buffet occurs:",
    "feedback": "following boundary layer separation due to shock wave formation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the wing area decreases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the EAS decreases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under what circumstances is TAS equivalent to GS?",
    "feedback": "No wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "A yaw damper is a system which:",
    "feedback": "Increase directional stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following have an effect on rudder force in asymmetric flight?\n1) Rudder deflection2) Thrust setting3) CG4) Mass5) TAS6) IAS",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the following characteristic points on a jet engine aeroplane's polar curve:\n\n1) CLMAX\n2) long range cruise (zero wind)\n3) maximum lift to drag ratio\n4) minimum rate of descent (assume zero thrust)\n5) maximum range cruise (zero wind)\n\nArrange these points in order of increasing angle of attack:",
    "feedback": "2, 5, 3, 4, 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices is not affected by angle of attack\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a glide with idle power and constant IAS, if the RPM lever of a constant speed propeller is pulled back from its normal cruise position, the propeller pitch will:",
    "feedback": "increase and the rate of descent will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and an aircraft which is travelling at the same IAS, what happens to the drag of the aircraft at 6000 ft, compared to the drag at sea level?",
    "feedback": "It will not change"
  },
  {
    "question": "The descent angle of a given aeroplane in a steady wings level glide has a fixed value for a certain combination of\n(ignore compressibility effects and assume zero thrust)",
    "feedback": "configuration and angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) If flutter occurs, IAS should be reduced\n2) Resistance to flutter increases with reducing wing stiffness",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When speed increases the buffet free range does not change\n2) When altitude decreases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The windmilling of a propeller will cause:",
    "feedback": "drag to be produced instead of thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices increases as the angle of attack increases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Parasite drag of a wing in subsonic airflow includes only the components of total drag that are:",
    "feedback": "Still present when the wing is producing no lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the effect of wing sweep on centre of pressure location are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The centre of pressure on an unswept wing moves forward as the angle of attack approaches and exceeds the critical angle of attack\n2) When sweep back increases the centre of pressure has an increased tendency to move aft as the angle of attack approaches and exceeds the critical angle of attack",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stick force per g:",
    "feedback": "is dependent on CG location"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about induced drag are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Induced drag increases as angle of attack decreases\n2) At constant load factor, induced drag decreases with decreasing aeroplane mass",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about an expansion wave in supersonic flow ?  1) The temperature in front of an expansion wave is higher than the temperature behind it. 2) The speed in front of an expansion wave is higher than the speed behind it.",
    "feedback": "1 is correct and 2 is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the primary roll controls on a conventional aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "The ailerons"
  },
  {
    "question": "In asymmetric flight, rudder is used to stop yaw and ailerons to bank towards the operating engine. The bank angle must be limited to prevent ....",
    "feedback": "excessive loss of the vertical component of lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the pitching moment coefficient versus angle of attack lines in the diagram is correct?",
    "feedback": "Static longitudinal stability is greater at line 4 when compared with line 3 at low and moderate angles of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure increases as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a right turn, the slip indicator is right of neutral. One way to co-ordinate the turn is to apply:",
    "feedback": "less right bank"
  },
  {
    "question": "What could be the cause, when the stagnation point moves up?",
    "feedback": "A lower angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Flying at M = 0.84 provides the optimum margin with respect to buffet onset\n2) The maximum altitude that can be achieved with respect to buffet onset according EASA/CS regulations is lower at M = 0.82 than at M = 0.75",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate radius of a steady horizontal co-ordinated turn at a bank angle of 45° and a TAS of 200 kt?",
    "feedback": "1 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "From the buffet onset graph of a given jet transport aeroplane it is determined that at FL 310 at a given mass buffet free flight is possible between M = 0.74 and M = 0.88. In what way would these numbers change if the aeroplane is suddenly pulled up, e.g. in a traffic avoidance manoeuvre?",
    "feedback": "The lower Mach number increases and the higher Mach number decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct with regard to fin angle of attack, sideslip, and rudder effectiveness, following an engine failure?\n1) The greater the sideslip, the greater the fin angle of attack2) Excessive sideslip may cause a fin stall3) The greater the sideslip, the greater the rudder effectiveness4) Excessive sideslip may cause a fin stall, but only at a low aeroplane mass",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wing dihedral:",
    "feedback": "contributes to static lateral stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the lift generated by a given wing is 1000 kN, what will be the lift if the wing area is doubled?",
    "feedback": "2000 kN"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a jet aeroplane (engines mounted below the low wing) the thrust is suddenly increased. Which of these statements is correct about the elevator deflection required to maintain zero pitching moment?",
    "feedback": "The elevator must be deflected downward"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at a speed of 1.2 VS. If, at this speed, a vertical gust causes a load factor of 2.2, the load factor n caused by the same gust at a speed of 2 VS would be:",
    "feedback": "irrelevant, since the aeroplane would already be in a stalled condition at 1.2 VS with that gust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which aeroplane behaviour will be corrected by a yaw damper ?",
    "feedback": "Dutch roll."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following wing designs would have the least effective high lift devices (airspeed and all other factors being constant)?",
    "feedback": "Wing with a sweepback angle of 25 degrees"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you push forward the RPM lever of a constant speed propeller during a glide with idle power and constant speed, the propeller pitch will:",
    "feedback": "decrease and the rate of descent will increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which aeroplane design has the highest probability of a super stall?",
    "feedback": "Swept wings."
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of supersonic flow retarded by a normal shock wave a high efficiency (low loss in total pressure) can be obtained if the Mach number in front of the shock is",
    "feedback": "small but still supersonic."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about drag divergence Mach number are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Mcrit is higher than the drag divergence Mach number\n2) Assuming a given angle of attack and for M < 1 the drag coefficient CD decreases above the drag divergence Mach number",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The static temperature in front of an oblique shock wave is higher than behind it\n2) The static pressure in front of an oblique shock wave is higher than behind it",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the wing area decreases, the gust load factor decreases\n2) When the EAS decreases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most important problem of ice accretion on a transport aeroplane during flight is:",
    "feedback": "Reduction in CLMAX"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared with a level, co-ordinated turn, in order to maintain constant speed during straight and level flight, the pilot must:",
    "feedback": "decrease thrust and angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Above MCRIT in the transonic speed regime, at a constant angle of attack, the CD will ......",
    "feedback": "vary, depending on Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about dihedral is correct?",
    "feedback": "The \"effective dihedral\" of an aeroplane component means the contribution of that component to the static lateral stability."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following wing planforms produces the lowest induced drag? (assume zero wing twist)",
    "feedback": "Elliptical."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements concerning propellers is correct?",
    "feedback": "A feathered propeller causes less drag than a windmilling propeller"
  },
  {
    "question": "Comparing the differences between a horizontal trimmable stabiliser and an elevator trim tab, which of these statements are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When trimmed for zero elevator stick force a horizontal trimmable stabiliser causes more drag\n2) A horizontal trimmable stabiliser enables a larger CG range",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming constant IAS, when an aeroplane enters ground effect:",
    "feedback": "the induced angle of attack reduces"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared to a \"high aspect ratio\" wing a \"low aspect ratio\" wing will produce:",
    "feedback": "more induced drag and have a higher stalling angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has static directional stability; in a side-slip to the right, initially the:",
    "feedback": "nose of the aeroplane tends to move to the right."
  },
  {
    "question": "Stall speed (IAS) varies with:",
    "feedback": "weight"
  },
  {
    "question": "If, in a two-dimensional incompressible and subsonic flow, the streamlines converge the static pressure in the flow will:",
    "feedback": "decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft has been parked outside overnight, in freezing conditions. The crew decides to depart without having the airframe de-iced. What could be the principal danger during take-off?",
    "feedback": "Loss of control due to frozen deposits on the wings, which reduce CLMAX"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane exhibits static longitudinal stability, if, when the angle of attack changes:",
    "feedback": "the change in total aeroplane lift acts aft of the centre of gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the undisturbed airflow is the same than in the throat\n2) The speed in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following factors increase stall speed :",
    "feedback": "an increase in load factor, a forward c.g. shift, decrease in thrust."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is on final approach is flying at a CAS lower than VMD, which means it is speed unstable. If the speed suddenly decreases, what effect do parasite and induced drag have on total drag?",
    "feedback": "Parasite drag reduces, induced drag increases by a larger amount, so total drag increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane flying at 200 kt in straight and level flight is subjected to a disturbance that suddenly increases the speed by 100 kt. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant, the load factor will initially:",
    "feedback": "increase to 2.25"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which condition is least favourable handling-wise during take-off for a twin engine propeller aircraft with the engines wing mounted, both being right-turning engines?",
    "feedback": "A left engine failure, with a left quartering wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect of a positive wing sweep on static directional stability is as follows:",
    "feedback": "Stabilizing effect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane leaving ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle decreases\n2) The induced angle of attack remains constant",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle between the airflow (relative wind) and the chord line of an aerofoil is:",
    "feedback": "angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical Mach Number can be increased by:",
    "feedback": "increasing wing sweepback"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about static lateral and directional stability is correct?",
    "feedback": "An aeroplane with an excessive static directional stability in relation to its static lateral stability, will be prone to spiral dive. (spiral instability)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a descent above the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "IAS increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A slotted flap will increase the CLMAX by:",
    "feedback": "increasing the camber of the aerofoil, re-energising the airflow"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wing of an aeroplane will never stall at low subsonic speeds as long as....",
    "feedback": "the angle of attack is smaller than the value at which the stall occurs."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about an aeroplane entering ground effect is correct?\n\n1) The downwash angle remains constant\n2) The induced angle of attack increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which component of drag increases most when an aileron is deflected upwards?",
    "feedback": "Form drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a subsonic flow the continuity equation states that if the cross-sectional area of a tube increases, the speed of the flow:",
    "feedback": "decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Some airplanes have spring tabs mounted into the control system:  This is to provide:",
    "feedback": "a reduction in the pilots effort to move the controls against high airloads"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of attack of a two dimensional wing section is the angle between :",
    "feedback": "the chord line of the aerofoil and the free stream direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the Buffet Onset Boundary Chart below.\n\nThe maximum achievable load factor without buffet onset at FL 400 at a mass of 140 tons is approximately:",
    "feedback": "1g at M = 0.80"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements, about a venturi in a sub-sonic airflow are correct?\n\n1. the dynamic pressure in the undisturbed flow and in the throat are equal.\n\n2. the total pressure in the undisturbed flow and in the throat are equal.",
    "feedback": "1 is incorrect and 2 is correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "The phugoid motion is a long term oscillation around the",
    "feedback": "Lateral axis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about the effects on drag of removing external tip tanks from the wings of an aeroplane, is correct?\n\n1) Parasite drag increases\n2) Induced drag increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements are correct or incorrect regarding a sideslip, with the relative airflow coming from the left, on an aeroplane that exhibits both directional and lateral stability?\n\n1) The initial tendency of the nose of the aeroplane is to move to the left\n2) The initial tendency of the right wing is to move down",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which point in the diagram gives the best glide condition?",
    "feedback": "Point b"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"short period mode\" is an:",
    "feedback": "oscillation about the lateral axis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the equilibrium of forces and moments at VMCA are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Equilibrium of moments about the normal axis is provided by rudder deflection\n2) Equilibrium of forces along the lateral axis requires either bank angle or side slip or a combination of both",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The tendency to Dutch Roll increases when:",
    "feedback": "the static lateral stability increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The relation between the Mach angle (mu) and the corresponding Mach number is:",
    "feedback": "sin mu = 1/M"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the slope of the lift versus angle of attack curve decreases, the gust load factor decreases\n2) When the wing loading decreases, the gust load factor decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is in steady, unaccelerated straight and level flight in the section of the graph with positive speed stability. Due to horizontal wind shear, the aircraft's CAS increases.\nWhich of the following happens due to the increased CAS?",
    "feedback": "the total drag increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The point, where the aerodynamic lift acts on a wing is:",
    "feedback": "the centre of pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the gyroscopic effect of a clockwise rotating propeller on a single engine aeroplane?\n\n1) Pitch down produces right yaw\n2) Left yaw produces pitch down",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which wing design feature decreases the static lateral stability of an aeroplane?",
    "feedback": "Anhedral."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The the CG moves aft the buffet free range decreases\n2) When the Mach number decreases the buffet free range does not change",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Calculate the Mach number, given the following:\nCAS: 293 ktTAS: 385 ktTemperature: -48°C",
    "feedback": "0.658"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angle of attack for a propeller blade is the angle between blade chord line and:",
    "feedback": "Local air speed vector."
  },
  {
    "question": "VMCA is the minimum speed at which directional control can be maintained when, amongst others:\n\n1) maximum take-off thrust was set and is maintained on the remaining engines\n2) a sudden engine failure occurs on the most critical engine\n3) flaps are in any position\n4) the gear is either up or down\n5) the aeroplane is either in or out of ground effect\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Based on the two-dimensional drag formula, if the altitude increases while all other parameters remain constant, the drag will (1) ......, because the air density will (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) decrease, (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about a normal shock wave ?",
    "feedback": "The airflow changes from supersonic to subsonic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Taper ratio of a wing is the ratio between:",
    "feedback": "tip chord and root chord"
  },
  {
    "question": "Low speed pitch up is caused by the:",
    "feedback": "spanwise flow on a swept back wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the total drag change, in straight and level flight at constant mass, as speed is increased from the stall speed (VS) to maximum IAS (VNE or VMO)?",
    "feedback": "Initially decreases, then increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a left turn, the slip indicator is left of neutral. One way to co-ordinate the turn is to apply:",
    "feedback": "more left rudder"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation and no compressibility effects, the location of the centre of pressure of a symmetrical aerofoil section:",
    "feedback": "is independent of angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does VMCG change with increasing field elevation and temperature?",
    "feedback": "decreases, because the engine thrust decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The relationship between induced drag and the aspect ratio is:",
    "feedback": "a decrease in the aspect ratio increases the induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the pitching moment coefficient versus angle of attack lines in the diagram is correct?",
    "feedback": "The CG position is further aft at line 1 when compared with line 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "By what approximate percentage will the stall speed increase in a horizontal coordinated turn with a bank angle of 45° ?",
    "feedback": "19%"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the speed of sound change with changing altitude in International Standard Atmosphere (ISA) conditions?\nAs the altitude increases, the speed of sound ......",
    "feedback": "decreases in the troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the skin of an aircraft, which drag is going to increase with increasing age?",
    "feedback": "Skin Friction Drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the spin is correct?",
    "feedback": "During spin recovery the ailerons should be kept in the neutral position."
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed decreases: \n(all other factors of importance being constant)",
    "feedback": "when, during a manoeuvre, the aeroplane nose is suddenly pushed firmly downwards (e.g. as in a push over)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which combination of speeds is applicable for structural strength in gust (clean configuration) ?",
    "feedback": "50 ft/sec and VC."
  },
  {
    "question": "The least ability to oppose the yawing moment from a failed engine occurs when the CG ....",
    "feedback": "is located at the aft limit of the CG range"
  },
  {
    "question": "If an increase in power tends to make the nose of the aircraft to dip, this is the result of the:",
    "feedback": "Line of thrust being above the centre of gravity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Negative tail stall is:",
    "feedback": "a sudden reduction in the downward aerodynamic force on the tailplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about an oblique shock wave are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The density in front of an oblique shock wave is higher than behind it\n2) The total pressure in front of an oblique shock wave is lower than behind it",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of flap is shown in the picture 4?",
    "feedback": "Fowler flap"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the pitching moment coefficient Cm versus angle of attack diagram?",
    "feedback": "Line 3 shows an aeroplane with reducing static longitudinal stability at high angles of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the value of the Mach number if the Mach angle equals 45°?",
    "feedback": "1.4"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft equipped with trailing edge flaps and leading edge slats is about to take off, and extends both devices to the take off position. Due to a malfunction the slats on the right wing remain retracted.\nIf the malfunction goes undetected, the possible consequences are:",
    "feedback": "The right wing could stall stortly after rotation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the manoeuvre stability of an aeroplane is 75 N/g. The stick force required to achieve a load factor of 4 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is:",
    "feedback": "225 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a symmetrical aerofoil, the pitch moment for which Cl=0 is:",
    "feedback": "zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "A common feature of leading and trailing edge flaps, when compared to the clean wing, are to:\n1) Increase CLMAX2) Increase CL/CD3) Decrease critical Angle of Attack4) Increase camber\nWhich of the following statements are correct?",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane in straight and level flight at 300 kt is subjected to a sudden disturbance in speed. Assuming the angle of attack remains constant initially and the load factor reaches a value of approximately 1.2:",
    "feedback": "the speed will have increased by 30 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a given elevator deflection, aeroplane longitudinal manoeuvrability decreases when:",
    "feedback": "the CG moves forward"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?\n\n1) A stick pusher activates at a higher angle of attack than a stick shaker\n2) A stick pusher prevents the pilot from increasing the angle of attack further",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The load factor is less than 1 (one):",
    "feedback": "when weight is greater than lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming constant IAS, when an aeroplane leaves ground effect:",
    "feedback": "downwash increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAeroplane mass:  50000 kg\nLift/drag ratio: 12\nThrust per engine: 60000 N\nAssumed g: 10m/s2\n\nFor a straight, steady, wings level climb of a twin engine aeroplane, the one-engine inoperative climb gradient is:",
    "feedback": "3.7 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "In supersonic flight, all disturbances produced by an aeroplane are:",
    "feedback": "within a conical zone, dependent on the Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aerofoil's thickness to chord ratio is:",
    "feedback": "less than 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices increases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has a servo-tab controlled elevator. What will happen when only the elevator jams during flight ?",
    "feedback": "Pitch control reverses direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming incompressible flow, when considering streamlines in the vicinity of an aerofoil, which of the following answers is correct?",
    "feedback": "Converging streamlines indicate that the speed of the flow is increasing and that the static pressure is decreasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "During initiation of a turn with speedbrakes extended, the roll spoiler function induces a spoiler deflection:",
    "feedback": "downward on the upgoing wing and upward on the downgoing wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and no compressibility effects, if an aeroplane maintains straight and level flight at the same angle of attack at two different altitudes, the:",
    "feedback": "IAS at both altitudes is the same"
  },
  {
    "question": "Define the term \"Mach number\".",
    "feedback": "The ratio between TAS and the speed of sound"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram shows a right turn, where there is too much bank for a co-ordinated turn?",
    "feedback": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the undisturbed airflow is higher than in the throat\n2) The speed in the undisturbed airflow is the same than in the throat",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mcrit is increased by:",
    "feedback": "sweepback, thin aerofoils and area ruling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vmcg is defined as the minimum speed which directional control on the ground can be recovered and maintained under which condition:",
    "feedback": "By use of rudder only"
  },
  {
    "question": "A twin-engine turboprop aeroplane has an engine failure in flight. Select the correct statements with regard to the asymmetric effects of the propeller slipstream.\n1) Slipstream-induced lift will be lost on the side of the failed engine2) A rolling moment towards the live engine will be induced3) Total lift will be reduced, giving a tendency to descend4) The use of leading edge devices can counter the effects of lost slipstream",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the CG position is moved forward, the elevator deflection to achieve a decrease in load factor will be:",
    "feedback": "larger"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the coefficient of lift for an aeroplane when flying at the stall speed, given the following information:\nWing area: 13.5 m2Density: 1.225 kg/m3VS: 70 ktsMass: 1400 kgG = 9.81 m/s2",
    "feedback": "1.28"
  },
  {
    "question": "Static lateral stability will be increased by:",
    "feedback": "the use of a high, rather than low, wing mounting"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the gust load factor on an aeroplane are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When the slope of the lift versus angle of attack curve increases, the gust load factor increases\n2) When the wing loading increases, the gust load factor increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Extension of leading edge flaps will:",
    "feedback": "increase critical angle of attack."
  },
  {
    "question": "When the stick force required to achieve a load factor of 3 from steady straight and level trimmed flight is 100 N, the value of the manoeuvre stability of that aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "50 N/g"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst setting up for landing, the crew are distracted by an external event on the radio. In doing so, they forget to set the final stage of flaps. The aircraft system automatically adjusts the approach speed for the reduced flap setting, but does not notify the pilots, so they land with a lower flap setting (less flaps) than planned and computed. The landing distance will (1) ...... due to (2) ...... being generated by the lower flap setting, which requires a (3) ...... touchdown speed.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) less lift, (3) higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stall speed in a specified configuration is represented by the following:",
    "feedback": "VS1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dangerous stall characteristics, in large transport aeroplanes that require stick pushers to be installed, include:",
    "feedback": "excessive wing drop and deep stall"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared to a conventional aerofoil at a given flight level, the MCRIT of a supercritical aerofoil will be ......",
    "feedback": "higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "When considering the properties of a laminar and turbulent boundary layer, which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "friction drag is higher in a turbulent layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for a propeller of given diameter and at constant RPM?\n\n1) Assuming blade shape does not change power absorption is independent of the number of blades\n2) Power absorption increases if the mean chord of the blades increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bernoulli's equation can be written as : (pt = total pressure, ps = static pressure, q = dynamic pressure)",
    "feedback": "pt - q = ps"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most forward CG location may be limited by:\n\n1) insufficent flare capability\n2) excessive in-flight manoeuvrability\n3) insufficient in-flight manoeuvrability\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack increases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices increases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Induced drag on a wing is:",
    "feedback": "greatest at the wing tip"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pilot use the rudder to provide control around the:",
    "feedback": "Normal axis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air loads on the horizontal tailplane (tail load) of an aeroplane in straight and level cruise flight are generally directed:",
    "feedback": "downwards and will reduce in magnitude as the CG moves aft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A shock wave that is perpendicular to the direction of the flow is ......",
    "feedback": "a normal shock wave"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal stall recovery procedure for a light single engined aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "full power and stick roll-neutral nose-down, correcting for angle of bank with rudder."
  },
  {
    "question": "Given an initial condition in straight and level flight with a speed of 1.4 VS. The maximum bank angle attainable without stalling in a steady co-ordinated turn, whilst maintaining speed and altitude, is approximately:",
    "feedback": "60°"
  },
  {
    "question": "The twisting of a propeller blade from root to tip has been made to:",
    "feedback": "provide a constant angle of attack from root to tip"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a jet transport aeroplane takes off with the CG at the forward limit and the trimmable horizontal stabiliser (THS) is positioned at the maximum allowable nose up position for take-off:",
    "feedback": "rotation will be normal using the normal rotation technique"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding a symmetric aerofoil section, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The angle of attack has a positive value when the lift coefficient equals zero\n2)The pitching moment is zero when the lift coefficient equals zero",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the Drag Divergence Mach number (MDRAGDIVERGENCE)?",
    "feedback": "The Drag Divergence Mach number is close to, and always greater than MCRIT"
  },
  {
    "question": "A twin engined aeroplane (mass = 59'000 kg) is established on a climb with all engines operating. The lift-to-drag ratio is 12. Each engine produces 60'000 newtons of thrust. The gradient of climb is: (assume g = 10 m/s^2)",
    "feedback": "12%"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a fixed-pitch propeller, the blade angle of attack:",
    "feedback": "can become negative during high-speed idle descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "A plain flap will increase CLMAX by",
    "feedback": "increasing the camber of the aerofoil."
  },
  {
    "question": "During the approach to landing, the crew inadvertently select a flap setting that is lower than planned and computed (i.e. less flaps). The reference speed for the approach is automatically adjusted for the actual flap setting. The landing distance will (1) ..... due to (2) ..... being generated by the lower flap setting, which requires a (3) ..... touchdown speed.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) less lift, (3) higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect of increasing angle of sweep is:",
    "feedback": "an increase in the critical Mach number"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dutch roll occurs when:",
    "feedback": "lateral stability is too great compared to directional stability."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for a propeller of given diameter and at constant RPM?\n\n1) Assuming blade shape does not change power absorption is independent of the number of blades\n2) Power absorption decreases if the mean chord of the blades increases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the airspeed is doubled, whilst maintaining the same control surface deflection the aerodynamic force on this control surface will:",
    "feedback": "become four times greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When initiating a steady horizontal turn from steady straight and level flight the buffet free range decreases\n2) When mass decreases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct,2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the buffet free range in a buffet onset boundary graph are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) When altitude increases the buffet free range decreases\n2) When load factor increases the buffet free range increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a trimmable horizontal stabiliser is correct?",
    "feedback": "A trimmed aeroplane with a forward CG requires the stabiliser leading edge to be lower than in the case of an aft CG in the same condition"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about flutter are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Aero-elastic coupling affects flutter characteristics\n2) Occurrence of flutter is independent of IAS",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of aeroplane will experience a larger decrease in induced drag at heights between ground level and a wingspan?",
    "feedback": "Low wing aeroplane during landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aerofoil polar is:",
    "feedback": "a graph of the relation between the lift coefficient and the drag coefficient."
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to asymmetric thrust conditions and an increase in density altitude, the minimum control speeds ....",
    "feedback": "decrease, due to less thrust being developed by the engines, and therefore control being able to be maintained at a lower CAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane leaving the ground effect after take-off will experience ......",
    "feedback": "an increase in induced drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "When vortex generators are fitted they will normally be found:",
    "feedback": "near the wing leading edge in front of control surfaces"
  },
  {
    "question": "The drag of an aeroplane is 850 Newton. What is the new value of drag if the wing surface area is increased by 10 %?",
    "feedback": "935 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "When an aeroplane enters ground effect:",
    "feedback": "the lift is increased and the drag is decreased."
  },
  {
    "question": "The lift- and drag forces, acting on an aerofoil:",
    "feedback": "depend on the pressure distribution around the aerofoil"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the low and high buffet onset speeds, given the following conditions?\n\nFL350\nMass: 110.000 kg\nBank angle: 50°",
    "feedback": "M 0,73 and M 0,83"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering subsonic incompressible airflow through a venturi, which statement is correct?\n\n1) The static pressure in the throat is the same as in the undisturbed airflow\n2)The speed of the airflow in the throat is higher than in the undisturbed airflow",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack decreases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stick pusher is installed in aircraft when:",
    "feedback": "the a/c has failed to meet the stalling requirements by normal category"
  },
  {
    "question": "The elevator deflection required for a given manoeuvre will be:",
    "feedback": "smaller for an aft CG position when compared to a forward position"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which factor should be taken into account when determining VA?",
    "feedback": "The limit load factor"
  },
  {
    "question": "The loss of total pressure in a shock wave is due to the fact that",
    "feedback": "kinetic energy in the flow is changed into heat energy."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about a spring tab ?",
    "feedback": "At high IAS it behaves like a servo tab"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a multi-engine aircraft equipped with clockwise-turning propellers, flying straight and level. If the critical engine fails, with crosswind from the left, this would result in a ....",
    "feedback": "yaw moment to the left, crosswind and p-factor increasing tendency"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do roll spoilers assist the ailerons during turns?",
    "feedback": "By decreasing the lift on the downward-going wing; they also reduce the adverse aileron yaw"
  },
  {
    "question": "A swept-back wing compared to a straight wing of the same dimensional thickness and free stream velocity increases MCRIT, because sweeping the wing back ......",
    "feedback": "increases the effective chord"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement, about an aeroplane leaving ground effect at constant angle of attack, is correct?\n\n1) The lift coefficient CL decreases\n2) The induced drag coefficient CDi increases",
    "feedback": "1) is correct 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can a pilot recognise static stick force stability in an aeroplane during flight?",
    "feedback": "To maintain a speed below the trim speed requires a pull force"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming constant IAS, when an aeroplane leaves ground effect:",
    "feedback": "induced drag increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has a stall speed of 100 kt. When the aeroplane is flying a level co-ordinated turn with a load factor of 1.5, the aeroplane will stall in this turn at:",
    "feedback": "122 kt."
  },
  {
    "question": "An advantage of locating the engines at the rear of the fuselage, in comparison to a location beneath the wing, is :",
    "feedback": "less influence on longitudinal control of thrust changes."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is provided with spoilers and both inboard and outboard ailerons. Roll control during cruise is provided by:",
    "feedback": "inboard ailerons and roll spoilers"
  },
  {
    "question": "To perform a co-ordinated turn the aeroplane in diagram 4 should use:",
    "feedback": "less bank angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the time for a heading change of 90 degrees in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "30 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "A transonic Mach number is a Mach number:",
    "feedback": "at which both subsonic and supersonic local speeds occur"
  },
  {
    "question": "The (1) stick force stability and the (2) manoeuvre stability are positively affected by:",
    "feedback": "(1) forward C.G. position (2) forward CG. position."
  },
  {
    "question": "A laminar boundary layer is a layer, in which:",
    "feedback": "no velocity components exist, normal to the surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "Minimum drag of an aeroplane in straight and level flight occurs at the:",
    "feedback": "maximum CL-CD ratio"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the initial climb after take-off, flaps are accidentally retracted prematurely. What may this action cause?",
    "feedback": "Stall warning, with a high risk of a full stall"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the extension of the flaps at a constant angle of attack the aeroplane starts to (all other factors of importance being constant)",
    "feedback": "climb."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about weight or mass is correct?",
    "feedback": "The mass of a body can be determined by dividing its weight by the acceleration due to gravity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The centre of gravity moving aft will:",
    "feedback": "increase the elevator up effectiveness."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions and a descent above the tropopause at constant Mach number and aeroplane mass, the:",
    "feedback": "TAS remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stick force per g of a heavy transport aeroplane is 300 N/g.  What stick force is required, if the aeroplane in the clean configuration is pulled to the limit manoeuvring load factor from a trimmed horizontal straight and steady flight?",
    "feedback": "450 N"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming ISA conditions, which statement with respect to the climb is correct?",
    "feedback": "At constant IAS the Mach number increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure does not change as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "Outboard ailerons (if present) are normally used:",
    "feedback": "in low speed flight only"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane performs a continuous descent with 160 kts IAS and 1000 feet/min vertical speed. In this condition:",
    "feedback": "weight is greater than lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the time for a heading change of 3 degrees in a steady co-ordinated horizontal rate one turn?",
    "feedback": "1 second"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about a steady subsonic airflow are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) the static pressure increases as the streamlines converge\n2) the velocity does not change as the streamlines converge",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "A strongly swept back wing stalls. If the wake of the wing contacts the horizontal tail, the effect on the stall behaviour can be:",
    "feedback": "nose up tendency and/or lack of elevator response."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which plane and situation experiences the least amount of lift reduction?",
    "feedback": "High wing on take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "A wing which accumulated dirt on its surface, compared to a clean wing, will be subject to what type of drag?",
    "feedback": "Parasite drag"
  },
  {
    "question": "When considering a swept-back wing, without corrective design features, at the stall:",
    "feedback": "tip stall will occur first, which produces a nose-up pitching moment."
  },
  {
    "question": "Behind the transition point in a boundary layer:",
    "feedback": "the mean speed and friction drag increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The blade angle of a rotating propeller blade element shown in the diagram is:",
    "feedback": "angle 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning control is correct?",
    "feedback": "In a differential aileron control system the control surfaces have a larger upward than downward maximum deflection"
  },
  {
    "question": "CL varies with:",
    "feedback": "angle of attack"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed for minimum sink rate (I) ....... is (II) ...... than the speed for minimum descent angle.",
    "feedback": "(I) VMP, (II) lower"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the Centre of Pressure  (CP) in relation to the Aerodynamic Centre (AC) on a positively cambered aerofoil?",
    "feedback": "The position of the AC is independent of the position of the CP"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming no flow separation, which of these statements about the flow around an aerofoil as the angle of attack decreases are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) The stagnation point moves down\n2) The point of lowest static pressure moves forward",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "The difference between IAS and TAS will:",
    "feedback": "decrease at decreasing altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "The contribution of the wing to the static longitudinal stability of an aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "depends on CG location relative to the wing aerodynamic centre"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the strength of wing tip vortices are correct or incorrect?\n\n1) Assuming no flow separation, the strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the angle of attack increases\n2) The strength of wing tip vortices decreases as the aspect ratio decreases",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens to the flow velocity over the wing when angle of attack decreases?",
    "feedback": "It decreases, and lift capability decreases"
  }
]